<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Canadians</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Canada</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Canadian</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Canada is a country in North America consisting of ten provinces and three territories. Located in the northern part of the continent, it extends from the Atlantic to the Pacific and northward into the Arctic Ocean. At 9.98 million square kilometres in total, Canada is the world's second-largest country by total area. Its common border with the United States is the world's longest land border shared by the same two countries. The land that is now Canada has been inhabited for millennia by various Aboriginal peoples. Beginning in the late 15th century, British and French colonies were established on the region's Atlantic coast. As a consequence of various conflicts, the United Kingdom gained and lost North American territories until left, in the late 18th century, with what mostly comprises Canada today. Pursuant to the British North America Act, on July 1, 1867 three colonies joined to form the autonomous federal dominion of Canada. This began an accretion of provinces and territories to the new self-governing dominion. In 1931, Britain granted Canada full independence in most matters with the Statute of Westminster 1931. The Canada Act 1982 severed the vestiges of legal dependence on the British parliament. Canada is a federal parliamentary democracy and a constitutional monarchy, with Queen Elizabeth II as its head of state. Canada is a member of the Commonwealth of Nations. The country is officially bilingual at the federal level. It is one of the world's most ethnically diverse and multicultural nations, the product of large-scale immigration from many countries, with a population of approximately 35 million as of December 2012. Its advanced economy is one of the largest in the world, relying chiefly upon its abundant natural resources and well-developed trade networks. Canada's long and complex relationship with the United States has had a significant impact on its economy and culture. Canada is a developed country and one of the wealthiest in the world, with the eighth highest per capita income globally, and the eighth highest ranking in the Human Development Index. It ranks among the highest in international measurements of education, government transparency, civil liberties, quality of life, and economic freedom. Canada's participation in economic international and intergovernmental institutions or groupings includes the G8 (Group of Eight); the Group of Ten (economic); the Group of Twenty (G-20 major economies); the North American Free Trade Agreement; and the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation forum. Canada's alliances include the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_TRUDEAU</Tag>
		<English>Trudeau</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_TRUDEAU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Joseph Philippe Pierre Yves Elliott Trudeau, PC CH CC QC FSRC (October 18, 1919 - September 28, 2000), usually known as Pierre Trudeau or Pierre Elliott Trudeau, was the 15th Prime Minister of Canada from April 20, 1968 to June 4, 1979, and again from March 3, 1980 to June 30, 1984. Trudeau began his political career as a lawyer, intellectual, and activist in Quebec politics. In the 1960s, he entered federal politics by joining the Liberal Party of Canada. He was appointed as Lester Pearson's Parliamentary Secretary, and later became his Minister of Justice. From his base in Montreal, Trudeau took control of the Liberal Party and became a charismatic leader, inspiring "Trudeaumania". From the late 1960s until the mid-1980s, he dominated the Canadian political scene and aroused passionate reactions. "Reason before passion" was his personal motto. He retired from politics in 1984, and John Turner succeeded him as Prime Minister. Admirers praise the force of Trudeau's intellect and salute his political acumen in preserving national unity against the Quebec sovereignty movement, suppressing a violent revolt, and establishing the Charter of Rights and Freedoms within Canada's constitution. Critics accuse him of arrogance, economic mismanagement, and unduly favouring the federal government relative to the provinces, especially in trying to distribute the oil wealth of the Prairies.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CANADA_CORVETTE</Tag>
		<English>Corvette</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CORVETTE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The modern corvette appeared during World War II as an easily built patrol and convoy escort vessel. The British naval designer William Reed drew up a small ship based on the single-shaft Smiths Dock Company whale catcher Southern Pride, whose simple design and mercantile construction standards lent itself to rapid production in large numbers in small yards unused to naval work. First Lord of the Admiralty Winston Churchill, later Prime Minister, had a hand in reviving the name "corvette". During the arms buildup leading to World War II, the term "corvette" was almost attached to the Tribal-class destroyer. The Tribals were so much larger than and sufficiently different from other British destroyers that some consideration was given to resurrecting the classification of "corvette" and applying it to them. This idea was dropped, and the term applied to small, mass-produced antisubmarine escorts such as the Flower class of World War II. The first modern corvettes were the Flower class (Royal Navy corvettes were named after flowers, and ships in Royal Canadian Navy service took the name of smaller Canadian cities and towns). Their chief duty was to protect convoys throughout the Battle of the Atlantic and on the routes from the UK to Murmansk carrying supplies to the Soviet Union. The Flower-class corvette was originally designed for offshore patrol work, and was not ideal as an antisubmarine escort; they were really too short for open ocean work, too lightly armed for antiaircraft defence, and little faster than the merchantmen they escorted, a particular problem given the faster German U-boat designs then emerging. They were very seaworthy and manoeuvrable, but living conditions for ocean voyages were appalling. Because of this, the corvette was superseded in the Royal Navy as the escort ship of choice by the frigate, which was larger, faster, better armed, and had two shafts. However, many small yards could not produce vessels of frigate size, so an improved corvette design, the Castle class, was introduced later in the war, with some remaining in service until the mid-1950s.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CANADA_RCMP</Tag>
		<English>Royal Mounted Police</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CANADA_RCMP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP) (French: Gendarmerie royale du Canada (GRC), literally 'Royal Gendarmerie of Canada'; colloquially known as the Mounties, and internally as 'the Force') is both a federal and a national police force of Canada, and one of the most recognized of its kind in the world. It is unique in the world as a national, federal, provincial, and municipal policing body. The RCMP provides policing services to all of Canada at a federal level, and also on a contract basis to the three territories, eight of Canada's provinces (the RCMP does not provide provincial or municipal policing in either Ontario or Quebec), more than 190 municipalities, 184 aboriginal communities, and three international airports.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOORS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Moors</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOORS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Moors</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOORS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Moorish</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_RAHMAN</Tag>
		<English>Abd-ar-Rahman</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOORISH_CAMEL_GUNNER</Tag>
		<English>Camel Gunner</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MOORISH_NORIA</Tag>
		<English>Noria</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TAMILS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Tamils</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TAMILS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Tamils</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TAMILS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Tamil</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_RAJENDRA</Tag>
		<English>Rajendra Chola</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TAMIL_DHARANI</Tag>
		<English>Dharani</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TAMIL_SANGAM</Tag>
		<English>Sangam</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Tibetans</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Tibet</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Tibetan</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LOBSANG_GYATSO</Tag>
		<English>Lobsang Gyatso</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TIBETAN_KHAMPA</Tag>
		<English>Khampa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TIBETAN_GOMPA</Tag>
		<English>Gompa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TIB_EMB</Tag>
		<English>Tibetan Embassy</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Polish</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Poland</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Polish</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOBIESKI</Tag>
		<English>Sobieski</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_POLISH_WINGED_HUSSAR</Tag>
		<English>Winged Hussar</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_POLISH_SEJMIK</Tag>
		<English>Sejmik</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_POL_EMBASSY</Tag>
		<English>Polish Embassy</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HARAPPANS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Harappans</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HARAPPANS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Harappa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HARAPPANS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Harappan</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_VATAVELLI</Tag>
		<English>Vatavelli</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HARAPPAN_MILITIA</Tag>
		<English>Militia</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARAPPAN_BATH</Tag>
		<English>Bath</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KONGO_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Congolese</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KONGO_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Congo</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KONGO_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Congolese</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MBEMBA</Tag>
		<English>Mbemba</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KONGO_POMBOS</Tag>
		<English>Pombos</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KONGO_MBWADI</Tag>
		<English>Mbwadi</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CASIMIR</Tag>
		<English>Casimir III</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SONGTSEN</Tag>
		<English>Songtsen Gampo</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HARUN</Tag>
		<English>Harun al-Rashid</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_YAQUB</Tag>
		<English>Yaqub al-Mansur</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEXICO_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Mexicans</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEXICO_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mexico</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEXICO_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Mexican</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEXICO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Highly developed cultures, including those of the Olmecs, Mayas, Toltecs, and Aztecs, existed long before the Spanish conquest. Hernando Cortes conquered Mexico during the period 1519-21 and founded a Spanish colony that lasted nearly 300 years.[PARAGRAPH:2]Independence from Spain was proclaimed by Father Miguel Hidalgo on September 16, 1810. Father Hidalgo's declaration of national independence, known in Mexico as the "Grito de Dolores", launched a decade long struggle for independence from Spain. Prominent figures in Mexico's war for independence were Father Jose Maria Morelos; Gen. Augustin de Iturbide, who defeated the Spaniards and ruled as Mexican emperor from 1822-23; and Gen. Antonio Lopez de Santa Ana, who went on to dominate Mexican politics from 1833 to 1855. An 1821 treaty recognized Mexican independence from Spain and called for a constitutional monarchy. The planned monarchy failed; a republic was proclaimed in December 1822 and established in 1824.[PARAGRAPH:2]Throughout the rest of the 19th century, Mexico's government and economy were shaped by contentious debates among liberals and conservatives, republicans and monarchists, federalists and those who favored centralized government. During the two presidential terms of Benito Juarez (1858-71), Mexico experimented with modern democratic and economic reforms. President Juarez' terms of office, and Mexico's early experience with democracy, were interrupted by the Habsburg monarchy's rule of Mexico (1864-67), and was followed by the authoritarian government of Gen. Porfirio Diaz, who was president during most of the period between 1877 and 1911.[PARAGRAPH:2]Mexico's severe social and economic problems erupted in a revolution that lasted from 1910-20 and gave rise to the 1917 constitution. Prominent leaders in this period (some of whom were rivals for power) were Francisco Madero, Venustiano Carranza, Pancho Villa, Alvaro Obregon, Victoriano Huerta, and Emiliano Zapata. The Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI), formed in 1929 under a different name, emerged from the chaos of revolution as a vehicle for keeping political competition among a coalition of interests in peaceful channels. For 71 years, Mexico's national government was controlled by the PRI, which won every presidential race and most gubernatorial races until the July 2000 presidential election of Vicente Fox Quesada of the National Action Party (PAN).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SANTA_ANNA</Tag>
		<English>Santa Anna</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SANTA_ANNA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Mexico[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1794 - 1876 AD[NEWLINE] [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD] [PARAGRAPH:1]Santa Anna’s normal loyalty would be to ally with the wealthy and privileged, but his immediate concern was to be on the winning side in any battle. Switching allegiance never troubled him. Santa Anna declared himself retired, "unless my country needs me". He decided he was needed when Anastasio Bustamante led a coup, overthrowing and killing President Vicente Guerrero. Santa Anna was elected president in 1833.[PARAGRAPH:1]Gómez Farías did many reforms, introducing antimilitary and anticlergical reforms. He reduced the size of the army and worked hard to root out corruption in the military. He also changed some rules reflecting the power of the Church. Clergymen would be allowed to preach only for religious matters. He altered the education as a fully secular system.[PARAGRAPH:1] The mandatory tax for the support of the Church was abolished. These drastic reforms angered many of the powerful among the military, wealthy landowners, and the Catholic Church. When there was rebellion and violence against the reform that Farias had made, Santa Anna changed his side, again. Santa Anna reversed his support for the liberals and joined the conservatives, dismissed Farías, declared the Constitution suspended, disbanded the Congress, and worked to concentrate power in the central government. This was applauded by some conservatives, but met with considerable disapproval from other sectors. He established a Catholic, centralist dictatorship and replaced the Constitution of 1824(the one that Farias established), with a new document, called The Seven Laws. the Constitution of 1836. The regime was a centralized dictatorship led by the military.[PARAGRAPH:1]Several states went into open rebellion: Coahuila y Tejas, San Luis Potosí, Querétaro, Durango, Guanajuato, Michoacán, Yucatán, Jalisco, Nuevo León, Tamaulipas and Zacatecas. Several of these states formed their own governments, the Republic of the Rio Grande, the Republic of Yucatan, and the Republic of Texas. Only the Texans defeated Santa Anna and retained their independence. They and their allies from the United States declared independence from Mexico. Their fierce resistance was possibly fueled by reprisals Santa Anna committed against his defeated enemies.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Zacatecan militia, the largest and best supplied of the Mexican states, led by Francisco Garcia, was well armed with .753 caliber British 'Brown Bess' muskets and Baker .61 rifles. After two hours of combat, on 12 May 1835, the Santa Anna's "Army of Operations" defeated the Zacatecan militia and took almost 3,000 prisoners. Santa Anna allowed his army to ransack Zacatecas for forty-eight hours. After defeating Zacatecas, he planned to move on to Coahuila y Tejas.</English>
	</TEXT>
   	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SANTA_ANNA_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello, [CT_NAME]. I am General Santa Anna, Savior of Mexico!  What have you come to offer me in tribute?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JUAREZ</Tag>
		<English>Juarez</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JUAREZ_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Benito Ju&#225;rez[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Five Times President of Mexico[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]March 21, 1806 - July 18, 1872[PARAGRAPH:2:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Benito Pablo Ju&#225;rez Garc&#237;a was a Zapotec Amerindian who served five terms as president of Mexico, he was the first Mexican leader who did not have a military background, and also the first full-blooded indigenous national ever to serve as President of Mexico and to lead a country in the Western Hemisphere.[PARAGRAPH:1] Ju&#225;rez was born of Indian parents, both of whom died when he was three years old. When he was 12 he left the uncle who was caring for him and joined his sister in the city of Oaxaca, where he began his formal education. He originally studied for the priesthood, but in 1829 he entered the Oaxaca Institute of Arts and Sciences to study law and science. In 1831 he received his law degree and also won his first public office, a seat on the municipal council. Impeccably honest, he never used public office for personal gain, and his modest way of life reflected his simple tastes even after his marriage in 1843 to Margarita Maza, an Oaxaca girl 17 years younger than he. Politics soon became his life’s work: he was a member of both the state and national legislatures, he became a judge in 1841, and he served as governor of his state, a post that brought him into national prominence. During these years in politics Ju&#225;rez began to formulate liberal solutions for his country’s many problems. The road to economic health, he concluded, lay in substituting capitalism for the stifling economic monopoly held by the Roman Catholic Church and the landed aristocracy. He also believed that political stability could be achieved only through the adoption of a constitutional form of government based on a federal system.[PARAGRAPH:1] But the return of the conservatives to power in the elections of 1853 doomed imminent reform in Mexico. Many prominent liberals were exiled, including Ju&#225;rez. From December 1853 until June 1855 he lived in New Orleans in the United States in semi poverty, occupying himself by exchanging ideas with other Mexicans and laying plans to return home. The opportunity to put his ideas into action finally came in 1855 when the liberals took control of the national government, and Ju&#225;rez left the United States to join the new administration of Juan &#193;lvarez as minister of justice and public instruction.[PARAGRAPH:1] The liberals carried out three major reforms, all supported by Ju&#225;rez. As minister of justice he was responsible for the law bearing his name that abolished special courts for the clergy and military, for he felt that juridical equality would help promote social equality. In June 1856 the government published the Ley Lerdo ("Lerdo Law," named after the minister of finance). Although it forced the church to sell its property, it contained no threat of confiscation. By breaking up large landed estates, the government hoped that many Mexicans would be able to acquire property and thus create the middle class that it believed was essential for a strong and stable Mexico. The climax of the reform was the liberal constitution promulgated in February 1857. In the same year, Ignacio Comonfort was elected president, and the new Congress chose Ju&#225;rez to preside over the Supreme Court and therefore, according to the constitution, also to serve as the effective vice president of Mexico. The court position was critical in determining his future career, for when the conservatives revolted and ousted Comonfort in January 1858, Ju&#225;rez had a legal claim to the presidency. Lacking troops to control the area around Mexico City, however, he retired to the eastern port city of Veracruz. At Veracruz Ju&#225;rez faced serious difficulties, for he had to create a government and hold it together through quarrels, betrayals, and defeat; to enforce and implement the constitution; to maintain armies in the field and defeat the conservative forces. But he was an extraordinarily tenacious and self-sufficient man, able to concentrate his energy and interest, and he proved himself the master of his government. Because the clergy was supporting the conservatives against the legal government, Ju&#225;rez enacted several laws to curb ecclesiastical power. He nationalized all church property, exempting only those buildings actually used for worship and instruction. To weaken clerical influence still further, he also nationalized the cemeteries and put birth registrations and marriages under the civil authority. Finally, the government separated church and state and guaranteed religious liberty to all citizens. [PARAGRAPH:1] By late 1860 the conservatives were faltering, and in January 1861 Ju&#225;rez was able to return to Mexico City and was constitutionally elected president. He was, however, faced with many serious problems: the opposition’s forces still remained intact, the new Congress distrusted its president, and the treasury was virtually empty. As a solution to this latter problem Ju&#225;rez decided in July 1861 to suspend payment on all foreign debts for two years. To safeguard their investments, England, Spain, and France decided to intervene, and by January 1862 the three countries had landed troops at Veracruz. But when Britain and Spain realized that Napoleon III intended to conquer Mexico and control it through a puppet, Archduke Maximilian of Austria, they withdrew their forces. Despite a major defeat at Puebla on May 5, 1862, reinforcements enabled the French to occupy Mexico City in June 1863, and Maximilian soon followed to take control of the government. Forced to leave the capital again, Ju&#225;rez kept himself and his government alive by a long series of retreats that ended only at El Paso del Norte (later named Ciudad Ju&#225;rez) at the Mexican-U.S. border. Early in 1867, as a result of continued Mexican resistance, increased U.S. pressure, and criticism at home, Napoleon decided to withdraw his troops. Soon afterward, Mexican forces captured Maximilian and executed him.[PARAGRAPH:1] Ju&#225;rez then made the greatest mistake of his political career. In August 1867, shortly after his return to Mexico City, he issued a call for national elections and for a referendum on whether Congress should make five amendments to the constitution. Public opinion did not object to the president’s running for re-election, but the constitutional changes aroused immediate and violent reaction in many quarters, including those sympathetic to Ju&#225;rez. His proposed changes came under fire because amendments enacted by Congress alone were unconstitutional, and the changes would strengthen the executive power. Ju&#225;rez was re-elected, but the controversy had created such a crisis of confidence that the administration did not even bother to count the votes on the amendments. Despite illness and personal loss—in October 1870 Ju&#225;rez suffered a stroke and three months later his wife died—he decided to run again in 1871. After a bitter campaign he was re-elected, but many of his countrymen, refusing to accept the result as final, took up arms against him. Ju&#225;rez spent the last few months of his life trying to restore peace. He died of a heart attack in 1872.[PARAGRAPH:1] March 21 is a day set to commemorate Juarez. This date has become a national holiday in Mexico, which has continued to grow in acceptance within the Mexican Culture. </English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. My name is [OUR_NAME], and I am the president of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. My motto is: when there is respect, there is peace!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Get out of my office!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>The government of the [OUR_EMPIRE] will fulfill its duty to defend its independence, to repel foreign aggression, and accept the struggle to which it has been provoked!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! It is so great to be at peace with you glorious nation!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Oh, you again... What are you going to complain about?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Can you spare this for the people of the [OUR_EMPIRE]?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Please support [OUR_CIV_SHORT] and it's people. We depend on your help!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] needs this and demands your assistance!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CARDENAS</Tag>
		<English>Cardenas</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CARDENAS_1</Tag>
		<English>Hola. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I am convinced that the good intentions of a ruler are simply not enough and that the collective factor represented by the workers is indispensable. Don't you agree [CT_NAME]?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CARDENAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Lazaro Cardenas del Río[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Mexico [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] May 21, 1895 - October 19, 1970 AD [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Lázaro Cárdenas was born in a lower-middle class family in the village of Jiquilpan, Michoacán. He supported his family (including his mother and 7 younger siblings) from age 16 on after the death of his father. He worked in a printing shop; although he had little formal education he used every opportunity to educate himself.[PARAGRAPH:1]Cárdenas originally set his sights at becoming a teacher, but was drawn into politics and the military during the Mexican Revolution after Victoriano Huerta overthrew President Francisco Madero. He backed Plutarco Elías Calles, and after Calles became President, Cárdenas became governor of Michoacán in 1928. He became known for his progressive program of building roads and schools and the unusual strict honesty of his administration.[PARAGRAPH:1]Calles continued to dominate Mexico after his presidency with administrations which were his puppets. He selected Cárdenas to be the PRI's presidential candidate on the assumption that he could control Cárdenas as he had controlled others. Cárdenas's first move once in office was to have his presidential salary cut in half. Even more surprising moves would follow. After establishing himself in the presidency, Cárdenas had Calles and dozens of his corrupt associates arrested or deported to the United States, which was greeted with great enthusiasm by the majority of the public.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1938 Cárdenas nationalized Mexico's petroleum reserves and expropriated the equipment of the foreign oil companies in Mexico. Even though compensation for the expropriated assests was included in this legislation, this move aroused considerable hostility in the international business community and foreign governments, and Mexican oil and other goods were boycotted. However, with the outbreak of World War II, oil became a highly sought-after commodity and the boycott ended.[PARAGRAPH:1]After his presidential term he served as Mexico's secretary of defense through 1945.[PARAGRAPH:1]It is often said that Cárdenas was the only president from the PRI who did not use the office to make himself wealthy. He retired to a modest home by Lake Pátzcuaro and worked the rest of his life supervising irrigation projects and promoting free medical clinics and education for the nation's poor.[PARAGRAPH:1]Lázaro Cárdenas died of cancer in Mexico City. His son Cuauhtémoc Cárdenas is a prominent Mexican politician.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
