<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Alex Mantzaris (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARGENTINA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Argentinians</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARGENTINA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Argentina</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARGENTINA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Argentine</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PERON</Tag>
		<English>Perón</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ARGENTINA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Argentina is a sovereign state, organized as a representative and federal republic, located in the southeastern corner of America. Its territory is divided into 23 provinces and one autonomous city, Buenos Aires, which is the nation's capital and seat of the federal government. Its mainland, covers much of South America, it borders with Bolivia and Paraguay on the north, with Brazil on the north-east, with Chile in the west and south, with Uruguay on the east and with the Atlantic Ocean on the west. The last Spanish viceroy, who ruled from Buenos Aires, was deposed the 25 of May of 1810 and the First Board government was organized. The 9th of July of 1816 Argentina formally proclaimed its independence in Tucumán as a free and sovereign country.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>San Martin</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jose de San Martin[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Liberator of Chile, 1st President of Peru[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1778 - 1850[PARAGRAPH:2:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Groomed from a young age for the life of a soldier, Jose de San Martin would grow to lead the Peruvian and Chilean people to independence from Spain. [PARAGRAPH:1]Born in Argentina, but raised in Spain, by the age of 11, Jose de San Martin was already a member of the Spanish armed forces. In the Peninsular War between Spain and France in 1808, San Martin began as an aide to the Spanish leadership; by war's end he had attained the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. [PARAGRAPH:1]In the midst of the war, the Spanish king abdicated from power to be replaced by an appointment of the opposing French. The citizens of Argentina, upon hearing of the Spanish government's state of disarray, decided that there would be no better time to declare independence. When news of the Argentine revolution reached him, San Martin elected to support the rebels' cause, leaving Spain for the New World. Upon his arrival, he was immediately recruited by the rebel forces to begin mustering and training an elite regiment. His regiment, known as the Mounted Grenadiers, became some of the finest troops South America had to offer. [PARAGRAPH:1]Once his troops were ready, the normally reserved drillmaster suggested a daring move - marching an army from Argentina to Chile through the peaks of the Andes. His plan was regarded as madness by many, but San Martin managed to muster more than enough brave souls to join him in the endeavor. Dividing his forces into six columns for easier travel through the difficult terrain, San Martin planned for each column to arrive within two days of one another, a highly unlikely prospect given the extreme terrain and great danger that lay ahead. [PARAGRAPH:1]But on February 12, nearly all four thousand troops stepped out from the shadows of the Andes onto the plains of Chacabuco, prepared to face the numerically superior Spanish forces. Despite having just traversed some of the most inhospitable terrain on earth, San Martin's "Army of the Andes," soundly defeated the Royalists. They then marched on the Chilean capital of Santiago, taking the city with little fuss. Despite what many thought to be a crushing loss on the field of Tacla roughly a month later, Chile was to remain in the hands of San Martin and his revolutionary followers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The citizens of Chile attempted to appoint San Martin governor of their colony, but he refused. He had his sights set on the bastion of Spanish power in South America - Lima, Peru. San Martin took his forces north, offering the Spanish forces in Lima the opportunity to surrender and set up a new constitutional government. Their refusal sealed their fate - in 1821, San Martin marched into Lima, taking the city for the rebels. He was soon proclaimed the first President of Peru. [PARAGRAPH:1]Small pockets of Spanish forces remained scattered throughout the Peruvian countryside and in order to ensure their removal, San Martin requested a conference with Simon Bolivar, the Liberator of the north whose military zone of influence overlapped that of San Martin. [PARAGRAPH:1]The two met in the city of Guayaquil, Ecuador in 1822. What they discussed is unknown, but the result is - on that day San Martin stepped down from his position, leaving the fate of South America in the hands of Bolivar. San Martin had previously displayed a wavering of passion for his cause, but it took the words of Bolivar to force a decision. Upon stepping down, San Martin settled with his wife and children on a farm in Argentina for two years before migrating to Europe, where he spent the remainder of his days moving from country to country in order to escape the numerous revolutions sweeping the continent at the time. He died in France in 1850.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>Hello, friend. My name is [OUR_NAME], but you can call me Jose. Or you can call me Francisco. Or you can call me Martin. Just don't call me late for dinner. </English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>I will now use my cunning knowledge of tactics to ignore you. </English>
		<French>Allez vous faire voir !</French>
		<German>Fahrt zur H?lle!</German>
		<Italian>Sparisci.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Pod?is iros al cuerno.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>I knew you would beg for peace eventually, but there will be no peace until you surrender.</English>
		<French>Comme un ami m'a dit un jour, "Aucune condition ne saurait ?tre accept?e, hormis une capitulation imm?diate et inconditionnelle." Dommage, n'est-ce pas ?</French>
		<German>Wie ein Freund von mir zu sagen pflegte: 'Ich akzeptiere nur die sofortige und bedingungslose Kapitulation'. ?u?erst treffend, nicht wahr?</German>
		<Italian>Come disse una volta un mio amico: &quot;L'unica cosa accettabile ? una resa incondizionata e immediata.&quot; Conciso, non trovi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Como un amigo m?o dijo una vez: &quot;Ninguna condici?n es aceptable, salvo una rendici?n incondicional e inmediata&quot;. Es una l?stima, ¿no cre?is?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>Finally I get to talk to a worthy adversary. What can the [OUR_EMPIRE] do for you?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Asseyez-vous et bavardons un instant.</French>
		<German>Seid gegr??t, [CT_NAME]. Nehmt Platz und lasst uns ein wenig plaudern.</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]. Siediti e parliamo per un po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sentaos y charlemos un rato.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>You lack the guile to trick me. Be warned I will not react well to deceit. </English>
		<French>Que me vaut l'honneur peu enviable de votre pr?sence ?</French>
		<German>Was verschafft mir die zweifelhafte Ehre Eures Besuchs?</German>
		<Italian>E a cosa devo il dubbio onore della tua presenza?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y a qu? debemos el dudoso honor de vuestra compa??a?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>The simplest strategy is for me to ask you for what we need and hope your good will wins out.</English>
		<French>Pourriez-vous donner ceci ? un bon ami, [CT_NAME] ?</French>
		<German>Ihr werdet einem treuen Freund diese kleine Bitte doch nicht abschlagen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Avresti un po' di questi in nome della nostra amicizia, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podr?ais darles esto a unos buenos amigos, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>Our armies are evenly matched, but I believe in a battle I would win out. So that this does not occur I ask you to meet our demands.</English>
		<French>Partager, c'est le d?but de l'amiti?, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Helfen hei?t br?derlich teilen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Se ci tieni a me, condividi, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Compartir es de generosos, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>You are outgunned and outclassed. I suggest you give me what I demand.</English>
		<French>R?pondez ? nos exigences ou vous subirez la foudre de notre "terrible et rapide ?p?e".</French>
		<German>Schlagt ein, wenn Ihr kein zweites Gettysburg erleben wollt! </German>
		<Italian>Dammi ci? che chiedo o proverai l'ira della nostra &quot;terribile e rapida spada.&quot; </Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos esto o sentir?is la c?lera de nuestra &quot;terrible y veloz espada&quot;. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PERON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Juan Domingo Perón[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Argentina[\BOLD][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] Born in Lobos, Argentina, on October 8th of 1895, and died in Olivos, the on July 1st of 1974.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB] He was elected President of Argentina in three occasions. The first time he was elected president was on February 24th of 1946, for the period 1946-1952. He was reelected on November 11th of 1951, for the period 1952-1958, which failed to complete due to a military coup that overthrew him on September 16th of 1955. Finally, after 18 years in exile, he returned to Argentina and was elected president for the third time on September 23th of 1973 for the period 1973-1979, which he could not complete because of his death.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARGENTINE_GRENADIER_CAVALRY</Tag>
		<English>Grenadier Cavalry</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARGENTINE_GRENADIER_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>José de San Martín reached the La Plata River on March 9th of 1812 with the rank of Cavalry Lieutenant Commander, presenting to the goverment the need of creating a cavalry corps, in which human quality would be more important than quantity. He created a disciplined and modern cavalry equipped with the spirit to fight the well prepared royalists forces applying the new french cavalry tactics, seeking to emulate, in some way, the elite corps of Napoleon's conquering army, the french horse grenadiers.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARGENTINE_GRENADIER_CAVALRY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>This is a mounted unit specialized against Riflemen.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARGENTINE_REFRIGERATION_PLANT</Tag>
		<English>Cold Storage Plant</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FRIGORIFICO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A cold storage plant is an industrial plant in which meat or vegetables are stored for later marketing. Meat from animals (cattle, pigs, fish, birds) after slaughter follow a natural process: the attack of microorganisms, which, at room temperature, degrade tissues. The meat is no longer edible in 2-3 days. Keeping the meat at low temperatures, the process of deterioration can be avoided, and so, meat can be consumed several months after the slaughter. Offering the fruits and meats for a longer period of time has an economic and alimentary importance. For this, the products are stored in refrigerated rooms at a suitable temperature and humidity, what allows the consumption of the products long after they were harvested.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FRIGORIFICO_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Unique Argentinian building which replaces the supermarket. Provides additional gold with cow, pig and sheep.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARG_EMBASSY</Tag>
		<English>Argentine Embassy</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>

