<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ITALIAN_ART_STUDIO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A studio is an artist's or worker's workroom, or the catchall term for an artist and his or her employees who work within that studio. This can be for the purpose of architecture, painting, pottery (ceramics), sculpture, scrapbooking, photography, graphic design, filmmaking, animation, radio or television production broadcasting or the making of music. The term is also used for the workroom of dancers, often specified to dance studio.[PARAGRAPH:1]The studio of a successful artist, especially from the 15th to the 19th centuries, characterized all the assistants, thus the designation of paintings as "from the workshop of..." or "studio of..." An art studio is sometimes called an atelier, especially in earlier eras. In contemporary, English language use, "atelier" can also refer to the Atelier Method, a training method for artists that usually takes place in a professional artist's studio.[PARAGRAPH:1]The above mentioned "method" calls upon that zeal for study to play a significant role in the production which occurs in a studio space. A studio is more or less artful to the degree that the artist who occupies it is committed to the continuing education in his or her formal discipline. Academic curriculi categorize studio classes in order to prepare students for the rigors of building sets of skills which require a continuity of practice in order to achieve growth and mastery of their artistic expression. A versatile and creative mind will embrace the opportunity of such practice to innovate and experiment, which develops uniquely individual qualities of each artist's expression. Thus the method raises and maintains an art studio space above the level of a mere production facility or workshop.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CARAVANSERAI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A caravanserai was a roadside inn where travelers could rest and recover from the day's journey. Caravanserais supported the flow of commerce, information, and people across the network of trade routes covering Asia, North Africa, and South-Eastern Europe.[PARAGRAPH:1]Most typically a caravanserai was a building with a square or rectangular walled exterior, with a single portal wide enough to permit large or heavily laden beasts such as camels to enter. The courtyard was almost always open to the sky, and the inside walls of the enclosure were outfitted with a number of identical stalls, bays, niches, or chambers to accommodate merchants and their servants, animals, and merchandise. [PARAGRAPH:1]Caravanserais provided water for human and animal consumption, washing, and ritual ablutions. Sometimes they even had elaborate baths. They also kept fodder for animals and had shops for travellers where they could acquire new supplies. In addition, there could be shops where merchants could dispose of some of their goods.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TIBETAN_GOMPA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Gompas are Buddhist temples (typically forming monasteries or nunneries, Sanskrit name vihara), located in Tibet, Ladakh (India), Nepal, and Bhutan. Their design and interior details vary from region to region, however, all follow a general layout of a central prayer hall containing a Buddha statue, benches for the monks or nuns to engage in prayer or meditation and attached living accomodation. The gompa may also be accompanied by any number of stupas.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_THAI_HO_TRAI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A Ho Trai is the library of a Thai Buddhist temple.[PARAGRAPH:2]For many centuries, the sacred Tripitaka scriptures had been written on palm leaves. To preserve the scriptures against humidity and against termites, the library was often built on columns to raise the storage from the ground. Bricks were preferably used in constructions to battle termites. Sometimes the Ho trai would be built, especially for this reason, above man-made ponds.[PARAGRAPH:2]Traditionally, the Tripitaka scriptures consisted of individual palm leaves, each measuring around 50 cm in length and around 4 to 6 cm in width. They were perforated and threaded in order to combine them in stacks of 20 to 40 pages. These stacks are kept pressed between two pieces of teakwood which is then wrapped in cloth and stored in a special bookcase. These bookcases are sometimes exquisitely crafted with mother-of-pearl inlay or with gold leaf applied on black lacquer. Beautiful examples of bookcases can be seen in the Bangkok National Museum. Modern Tripitaka are now printed as books.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KONGO_MBWADI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Seven Kingdoms were also called momboares in the 17th century text of the Portuguese Jesuit priest, Mateus Cardoso, which offers an extensive description of the region. The term momboares certainly derives from the Kikongo, or Kongo language, word mbwadi, meaning seven. Cardoso noted that the region was famous in his day for the large amount of cloth that it produced, some of which was exported to the Portuguese colonial city of Luanda, Angola. Reports of the early 17th century suggest that the Seven Kingdoms exported as much as 100,000 meters of cloth annually to that market alone, suggesting that its total production must have been several times higher, putting in on a par with other major textile centers in the world, including areas of equivalent size in Europe and India.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MOORISH_NORIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A noria is a machine for lifting water into a small aqueduct, either for the purpose of irrigation or, in at least one known instance, to feed seawater into a saltern.[PARAGRAPH:2]Muslim engineers used norias to discharge water into aqueducts which carried the water to towns and fields. Some of the norias used in the medieval Islamic world were as large as 20 meters in diameter, the one in Hama being a surviving example still used in modern times. It has 120 water collection compartments and could raise as much as 95 litres of water per minute.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Eine Noria ist ein in Syrien gebräuchliche Form des Wasserschöpfrads.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die berühmten Wasserschöpfräder (Norias) in Hama in Syrien gelten als die größten der Welt. Sie überwinden mit entsprechend großen Raddurchmessern Höhenunterschiede von z. T. über 30 Metern. Die Wasserkunst von Mértola in Portugal hatte vermutlich ein Schöpfrad von 24 m Durchmesser.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PHOENICIAN_GLASSMAKER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>According to Pliny the Elder, Phoenician traders were the first to stumble upon glass manufacturing techniques at the site of the Belus River. Georgius Agricola, in De re metallica, reported a traditional serendipitous "discovery" tale of familiar type:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The tradition is that a merchant ship laden with nitrum being moored at this place, the merchants were preparing their meal on the beach, and not having stones to prop up their pots, they used lumps of nitrum from the ship, which fused and mixed with the sands of the shore, and there flowed streams of a new translucent liquid, and thus was the origin of glass."[PARAGRAPH:1]This account is more a reflection of Roman experience of glass production, however, as white silica sand from this area was used in the production of glass within the Roman Empire due to its low impurity levels.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the 1st century BCE glass blowing was discovered on the Syro-Palestinian coast, revolutionizing the industry. Glass vessels were now inexpensive compared to pottery vessels. A growth of the use of glass products occurred throughout the Roman world. Glass became the Roman plastic, and glass containers produced in Alexandria spread throughout the Roman Empire. With the discovery of clear glass (through the introduction of manganese dioxide), by glass blowers in Alexandria circa 100 CE, the Romans began to use glass for architectural purposes. Cast glass windows, albeit with poor optical qualities, began to appear in the most important buildings in Rome and the most luxurious villas of Herculaneum and Pompeii. Over the next 1,000 years glass making and working continued and spread through southern Europe and beyond.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TAMIL_SANGAM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Tamil Sangams were assemblies of Tamil scholars and poets that, according to traditional Tamil accounts, occurred in the remote past. Some scholars believe that these assemblies were originally known as kootal or gathering. Three assemblies are described. The legend has it that the first two of which were held in cities since "taken by the sea", and the third of which was held during the 5th century BC in the present-day city of Madurai.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_POLISH_SEJMIK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A sejmik was a name of various local parliaments throughout the history of Poland. The first sejmiks were regional assemblies in the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth, and earlier in the Kingdom of Poland. Sejmiks existed until the end of the Commonwealth in 1795 following the partitions of the Commonwealth. In a limited form, some sejmiks existed in partitioned Poland, and later, in the Second Polish Republic. In modern Poland, since 1999, the term has been revived as a voivodeship sejmik (sejmik województwa), referring to the elected council of each of the 16 voivodeships.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INDIAN_STEPWELL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Stepwells are wells in which the water can be reached by descending a set of steps. They are most common in the west of India. The main purpose of a stepwell is utilitarian, but many are elaborate architectural achievements. Many such constructions are found in Gujarat, e.g. the Rani Ki Vav built in Anhilwara (Patan) by the Solanki dynasty.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHINESE_EXAMINATION_HALL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Taixue (literally "Greatest Study or Learning"), or sometimes called the "Imperial Academy", "Imperial School", "Imperial University" or "Imperial Central University", was the highest rank of educational establishment in Ancient China between the Han Dynasty and Sui Dynasty. It was replaced by the Guozijian. The first nationwide government school system in China was established in 3 CE under Emperor Ping of Han, with the taixue located in the capital of Chang'an and local schools established in the prefectures and in the main cities of the smaller counties.[PARAGRAPH:1]Taixue taught Confucianism and Chinese literature among other things for the high level civil service, although a civil service system based upon examination rather than recommendation was not introduced until the Sui and not perfected until the Song Dynasty (960-1279).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARAPPAN_BATH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The ancient Indus Valley Civilization of Northwest South Asia, including Pakistan and parts of India, was prominent in hydraulic engineering, and had many water supply and sanitation devices that were the first of their kind.[PARAGRAPH:1]Among other things, they contain the world's earliest known system of flush toilets. These existed in many homes, and were connected to a common sewerage pipe. Most houses also had private wells. City walls functioned as a barrier against floods.[PARAGRAPH:1]Mohenjo-daro is one of the best excavated and studied settlements from this civilization. The Great Bath might be the first of its kind in pre-historic period. This ancient town had more than 700 wells, and most houses in Mohenjo-daro had one private well.[PARAGRAPH:1]Dholavira, located in Gujarat, India, had a series of water storing tanks and step wells, and its water management system has been called "unique". Dholavira had at least five baths, size of one is comparable with Great Bath, Mohenjadaro.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEXICO_CHARREADA</Tag>
		<English>Charreada Arena</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEXICO_CHARREADA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>A [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Charreada Arena[COLOR_REVERT] (the Mexican replacement for a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Amphitheatre[COLOR_REVERT]) increases a city's happiness and its happiness output from using the culture slider. It will also provide extra experience to your mounted units.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEXICO_CHARREADA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A charreada is a Mexican-style rodeo that is different from other rodeos. The Mexican cowboy or cowgirl is known as a charro or charra. In an American rodeo the competitors race against the clock, so the emphasis is on speed in any given event. On the other hand, in a Mexican charreada the excellent style and skills of the rider or roper are emphasized, and only one event is timed.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charrería (a word encompassing all aspects of the art) came to Mexico from Salamanca, Spain, in the 16th century. Interesting is the fact that when the Spaniards first settled in Mexico they were under the orders of the ruler to raise horses, but not to allow the Mexicans to ride them. By 1528 the Spaniards had very large cattle-raising estates. They soon found it necessary to employ the Mexicans as vaqueros or herdsman, and the natives soon became excellent horsemen. Small landholders, known as rancheros or ranchers, were the first genuine charros and invented charreadas.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>