<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NATIONAL_EPIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A triumphal arch is a structure in the shape of a monumental archway, usually built to celebrate a victory in war. The arch is invariably a free-standing structure, quite separate from city gates or walls. In its simplest form a triumphal arch consists of two pillars connected by an arch, crowned with a superstructure or attic on which a statue or commemorative inscriptions might be mounted. More elaborate triumphal arches have flanking subsidiary archways, typically a pair. Famous arches include the Arch of Titus in Rome and the Arc de Triomphe in Paris.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un arc de triomphe est un ouvrage en forme d'arche monumentale, généralement construit pour célébrer une victoire à la guerre. L'arc est toujours une structure indépendante, à l'écart des portes et des remparts de la ville. Dans sa forme la plus simple, l'arc de triomphe se compose de deux piliers reliés par un arc et surmontés d'un entablement ou d'un attique sur lequel peuvent être ajoutées une statue ou des inscriptions commémoratives. Les arcs de triomphe plus élaborés comportent des arches secondaires - généralement au nombre de deux - sur les côtés. Parmi les arcs de triomphes les plus célèbres, on trouve l'Arc de Titus à Rome et l'Arc de triomphe de l'Etoile à Paris.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Triumphbogen ist ein frei stehendes Bauwerk in Form eines monumentalen Tors oder Bogengangs, das üblicherweise zur Würdigung eines bedeutenden militärischen Sieges abseits von Stadttoren oder -mauern errichtet wird. In seiner einfachsten Form besteht ein Triumphbogen aus zwei Säulen, die durch einen Bogen verbunden und mit einer Attika versehen sind, auf der eine Statue thront oder eine Inschrift angebracht ist. Aufwändiger gearbeitete Triumphbögen haben zusätzlich noch angrenzende Seitenbogengänge, die meist paarweise angeordnet sind. Berühmte Triumphbögen sind beispielsweise der Titusbogen in Rom und der Arc de Triomphe in Paris.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Un arco di trionfo &#232; una struttura con la forma di una monumentale arcata, spesso costruita per celebrare la vittoria in una guerra. L'arco &#232; invariabilmente una struttura a s&#233; stante, separata dalle mura o dalle porte di una citt&#224;. Nella sua forma più semplice un arco di trionfo consiste di due colonne unite da un arco, sovrastato da una struttura o un attico su cui si possono trovare statue o iscrizioni. Gli archi di trionfo più elaborati possono avere arcate sussidiarie laterali, di solito una coppia. Tra i più famosi sono l'Arco di Tito a Roma e l'Arco di Trionfo a Parigi.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Un Arco de Triunfo es una enorme arcada monumental que se suele construir para celebrar una victoria en la guerra. El arco siempre es una estructura solitaria, separada de las puertas o muros de la ciudad. En su forma m&#225;s sencilla consiste en dos pilares conectados por un arco que a su vez est&#225; coronado por una estructura superior en la cual se suele colocar una estatua o una inscripci&#243;n conmemorativa. Los Arcos de Triunfo m&#225;s elaborados pueden tener un par de arcos secundarios en los laterales. Los m&#225;s famosos son el Arco de Tito en Roma y el Arco del Triunfo de Paris.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHICHEN_ITZA</Tag>
		<English>Temple of Kukulkan</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Temple de Quetzalcóatl</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Pyramide des Kukulc&#225;n</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Tempio di Kukulcan</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>el Templo de Kukulc&#225;n</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHICHEN_ITZA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Temple of Kukulkan (also known as El Castillo or the Temple of Quetzalcoatl) is one of the best-known Mayan buildings in Chichen Itza. The structure itself is a typical four-sided step temple, but at its base rests stone pillars carved with feathered serpents (revealing the strong Toltec/Aztec influence). Many archeologists believe that its design is based upon the Mayan calendar, since each stairway has 90 steps. Add the total steps to the number of stairways plus the top platform, and you reach the number of 365 (the number of days in [our] typical calendar year).</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le temple de Quetzalcóatl (aussi appelé la Citadelle ou le temple de Kukulcán) est l'un des bâtiments mayas les plus connus sur le site de Chichén Itzá. L'ouvrage est une simple pyramide à degrés à quatre côtés, mais on trouve à sa base des piliers en pierre sur lesquels sont gravés des serpents à plumes, révélant la forte influence toltèque et aztèque. Beaucoup d'archéologues pensent que ce temple fut conçu d'après le calendrier maya, car chaque escalier compte 90 marches. Si l'on fait le total des marches et des escaliers, et qu'on ajoute la plate-forme au sommet, on obtient le nombre 365, soit le nombre de jours d'une année civile classique.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Pyramide des Kukulc&#225;n (auch El Castillo oder Tempel des Quetzalcoatl genannt) ist eines der bekanntesten Maya-Bauwerke in Chichen Itza. Das Gebäude selbst ist eine typische vierseitige Stufenpyramide, an deren Fuß allerdings Steinsäulen mit eingemeißelten gefiederten Schlangen angebracht sind (was den starken toltekischen/aztekischen Einfluss widerspiegelt). Viele Archäologen glauben, dass dieses Design auf dem Maya-Kalender basiert, da jeder Treppenabschnitt 90 Stufen hat. Addiert man die Gesamtzahl der Stufen und zählt dann die Anzahl der Treppenabschnitte plus der Dachplattform hinzu, so erhält man die Zahl 365 (die Anzahl der Tage in [unserem] gew&#246;hnlichen Kalenderjahr).</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il Tempio di Kukulcan (conosciuto anche come El Castillo o Tempio di Quetzalcoatl) &#232; uno degli edifici maya meglio conosciuti di Chichen Itza. La struttura &#232; quella tipica di un tempo con quattro lati, ma alla base si trovano colonne di pietra scolpite con serpenti piumati (che rivelano la forte influenza tolteca/azteca). Molti archeologi credono che il progetto si basi sul calendario maya, visto che ogni scala ha 90 scalini. Sommando il numero di scalini delle quattro scale a quelli della piattaforma sovrastante si ottiene 365 (il numero di giorni nel [nostro] anno).</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El Templo de Kukulc&#225;n (tambi&#233;n conocido como &quot;El Castillo&quot; o el &quot;Templo de Quetzalcoatl&quot;) es uno de los edificios mayas m&#225;s conocidos de Chichen Itz&#225;. La estructura en s&#237; es un templo t&#237;pico con cuatro paredes inclinadas y con escalones, pero en su base descansan unos pilares de piedra grabados con serpientes emplumadas (lo cual evidencia la fuerte influencia tolteca/azteca). Muchos arque&#243;logos creen que su dise&#241;o est&#225; basado en el calendario maya, pues todas las escaleras tienen noventa pelda&#241;os. Al sumar el número de pelda&#241;os al de escaleras y a la plataforma superior, obtenemos los 365 d&#237;as que tiene el a&#241;o según nuestro calendario.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WEST_POINT</Tag>
		<English>The Bastille</English>
		<French>
			<Text>La Bastille</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Die Bastille</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Bastiglia</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>la Bastilla</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WEST_POINT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Bastille was a prison in Paris, known formally as Bastille Saint-Antoine, best known today because of the storming of the Bastille on July 14, 1789, which along with the Tennis Court Oath is considered the beginning of the French Revolution. Bastille is a French word meaning "castle" or "stronghold"; used as a single word ("la Bastide" in French), it refers to the prison. Built from 1370 to 1383 as part of the defences of Paris, the structure was later converted into a prison.</English>
		<French>[TAB]La Bastille, ou plus précisément la Bastille Saint-Antoine, était une prison de Paris. Elle devint célèbre avec la prise de la Bastille le 14 juillet 1789 qui marqua, avec le serment du jeu de paume, le début de la Révolution française. Dérivé de "bastide", le mot "bastille" signifie "château" ou "forteresse". Utilisé comme nom propre, il désigne la prison. Commencé en 1370 et achevé en 1383, l'ouvrage devait servir à la défense de Paris. Il fut par la suite transformé en prison.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Bastille war das Staatgefängnis in Paris, früher offiziell als "Bastille Saint-Antoine" bezeichnet, das heute vor allem durch den Sturm auf die Bastille am 14. Juli 1789 berühmt ist, der zusammen mit dem "Ballhausschwur" als Beginn der französischen Revolution erachtet wird. Das französische Wort "Bastille" bedeutet übersetzt etwa "kleine Bastion" oder "kleine Burg". Das Gebäude wurde von 1370 bis 1383 als Teil der Verteidigungsanlagen von Paris erbaut und später als Kerkeranlage genutzt, weshalb der Begriff "Bastille" heute gleichbedeutend mit Gefängnis verwendet wird.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La Bastiglia era una prigione di Parigi, il cui nome completo francese &#232; Bastille Saint-Antoine, conosciuta al giorno d'oggi per l'assalto che sub&#236; il 14 luglio 1789 e che, assieme al Giuramento della Sala della Pallacorda, &#232; considerato l'inizio della rivoluzione francese. Bastille &#232; una parola francese che significa &quot;castello&quot; o &quot;fortezza&quot;; usata da sola (&quot;la Bastide&quot; in francese) si riferisce a una prigione. Costruita nel periodo che va dal 1370 al 1383 come parte delle difese di Parigi, venne più tardi convertita in una prigione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La Bastilla fue una prisi&#243;n parisina, conocida antiguamente como &quot;Bastide Saint-Antoine&quot;. Hoy es m&#225;s conocida por la c&#233;lebre toma de la Bastilla que se produjo el 14 de julio de 1789, que, junto con el Juramento del Juego de la Pelota, se considera el comienzo de la Revoluci&#243;n Francesa. &quot;Bastide&quot; es una palabra francesa que significa &quot;castillo&quot; o &quot;fortaleza&quot;, mientras que &quot;Bastille&quot;, el nombre con el que ha pasado a la historia, significa &quot;prisi&#243;n&quot;. Fue construida entre 1370 y 1383 como parte del complejo defensivo de Par&#237;s, aunque m&#225;s tarde se convirti&#243; en una prisi&#243;n.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_COLOSSEUM</Tag>
		<English>Amphitheatre</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Amphithéâtre</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Amphitheater</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Anfiteatro</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Anfiteatro:Anfiteatros</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FLAVIAN_AMPHITHEATRE</Tag>
		<English>The Colosseum</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Le Colisée</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Das Kolosseum</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Il Colosseo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>el Coliseo</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FLAVIAN_AMPHITHEATRE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Colosseum or Coliseum, situated in Rome and originally known as the Flavian Amphitheatre (Latin: Amphitheatrum Flavium), is the largest amphitheatre built in the Roman Empire. Originally capable of seating 50,000 spectators, it was used for gladiatorial combat. Construction of the Flavian Amphitheatre began under the rule of Emperor Vespasian in 72 AD. It was completed by his son, Titus, in 80 AD, with later improvements by Domitian.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le Colisée de Rome, appelé à l'origine "amphithéâtre Flavien" (en latin : Amphitheatrum Flavium), est le plus grand amphithéâtre construit dans l'Empire romain. Il pouvait contenir à l'origine 50 000 spectateurs et servait à organiser des combats de gladiateurs. La construction de l'amphithéâtre Flavien fut lancée sous Vespasien, en 72 apr. J.-C. L'ouvrage fut achevé par son fils, Titus, en 80 apr. J.-C., puis amélioré par Domitien.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Kolosseum (Lateinisch: Amphitheatrum Novum oder Amphitheatrum Flavium) ist das gr&#246;ßte der im antiken Rom erbauten Amphitheater. Es fasste ursprünglich 50.000 Zuschauer und diente vor allem als Schauplatz für Gladiatorenkämpfe. Der Bau des Amphitheatrum Flavium wurde im Jahr 72 n. Chr. von Kaiser Vespasian in Auftrag gegeben und im Jahr 80 n. Chr. von seinem Sohn Titus vollendet. Dessen Bruder Domitian ließ später noch einige Erweiterungen und Verbesserungen an dem Gebäude vornehmen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il Colosseo, situato a Roma e originariamente conosciuto come Anfiteatro Flavio (in latino: Amphitheatrum Flavium), &#232; il più grande anfiteatro costruito nell'impero romano. In origine era in grado di ospitare 50.000 spettatori e veniva utilizzato per i giochi gladiat&#242;ri. La costruzione dell'Anfiteatro Flavio inizi&#242; sotto l'imperatore Vespasiano nel 72 d.C e venne completata sotto il regno del figlio, Tito, nell'80 d.C., con ulteriori modifiche apportate durante il regno di Domiziano.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El Coliseo de Roma, que en su origen fue conocido como Anfiteatro Flavio (del lat&#237;n, &quot;Amphitheatrum Flavium&quot;), es el anfiteatro m&#225;s grande construido por el Imperio Romano. Era capaz de alojar a 50.000 espectadores durante los combates de gladiadores. La construcci&#243;n del Anfiteatro Flavio se inici&#243; durante el mandato del emperador Vespasiano en el 72 d. C. Fue inaugurado por su hijo Tito en el 80 d. C., aunque en realidad fue Domiciano quien lo complet&#243;, dos a&#241;os m&#225;s tarde.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_LEANING_TOWER</Tag>
		<English>The Leaning Tower</English>
		<French>
			<Text>La tour de Pise</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Der schiefe Turm</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La torre pendente</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>la Torre Inclinada</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_LEANING_TOWER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Leaning Tower of Pisa, or simply The Tower of Pisa (Italian: La Torre di Pisa) is the campanile, or freestanding bell tower, of the cathedral of the Italian city of Pisa. It is situated behind the Cathedral and it is the third structure in Pisa's Campo dei Miracoli (field of Miracles). The tower is the most famous leaning building in the world. While intended to stand vertically, it began leaning to the southeast soon after the onset of construction in 1173 due to a poorly laid foundation and loose substrate that has allowed the foundation to shift.</English>
		<French>[TAB]La tour de Pise, que les Italiens appellent "torre di Pisa", est le campanile (clocher isolé) de la cathédrale de Pise, en Italie. Située derrière la cathédrale, elle est le troisième bâtiment sur la place des miracles de la ville. La tour est le plus célèbre des bâtiments penchés au monde. Verticale à l'origine, elle commença à s'incliner vers le sud-est peu après le début de sa construction en 1173, ses fondations glissant sur le sous-sol trop meuble.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der schiefe Turm von Pisa (Italienisch: La Torre di Pisa) ist ein "Campanile", ein frei stehender Glockenturm des Doms von Pisa. Er befindet sich auf der Rückseite des Doms und ist als drittes Bauwerk auf Pisas "Piazza dei Miracoli" (Platz der Wunder) das wohl bekannteste schiefe Gebäude der Welt. Das Gebäude sollte gemäß der Bauplaner normal gerade stehen, doch kurz nach Baubeginn im Jahr 1173 bekam es wegen eines Grundbruches, dem Nachgeben des Fundamentes, eine Schräglage Richtung Südosten.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La torre pendente di Pisa, o semplicemente la torre di Pisa &#232; il campanile della cattedrale di Pisa. Si trova dietro la cattedrale ed &#232; la terza struttura nel Campo dei Miracoli. La torre &#232; il più famoso edificio pendente al mondo. Pur essendo stata progettata per rimanere verticale, cominci&#242; a pendere poco dopo l'inizio dei lavori di costruzione nel 1173, a causa di fondamenta mal realizzate e di un sottostrato friabile che ha permesso alle fondamenta di spostarsi.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La Torre Inclinada de Pisa, o simplemente la Torre de Pisa, es una torre campanario individual de la catedral de la ciudad italiana de Pisa. Est&#225; situada detr&#225;s de la catedral y es la tercera estructura del &quot;Campo dei Miracoli&quot; de Pisa (&quot;Campo de los Milagros&quot;). La torre es el edificio inclinado m&#225;s famoso del mundo. Aunque se pretend&#237;a que fuera totalmente vertical, comenz&#243; a inclinarse hacia el sudeste poco despu&#233;s de su construcci&#243;n, en 1173, debido a unos cimientos defectuosos y la tierra reblandecida sobre la que reposa.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HERMITAGE</Tag>
		<English>National Gallery</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Galerie nationale</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Nationalgalerie</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Galleria nazionale</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>la National Gallery</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HERMITAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A national gallery is a country's major public art gallery. With different names, they are widespread in almost every nation capital. They are a space for the exhibition of art, usually visual art, and usually primarily paintings, illustrations, and sculpture. The art museum is considered a fairly modern invention, the first being the Louvre in Paris, which was established in 1793, soon after the French Revolution when the royal treasures were declared for the people.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Une galerie nationale est la principale galerie d'art ouverte au public dans un pays. Bien que les appellations changent suivant les pays, on en trouve une dans presque chaque capitale du monde. Ces bâtiments servent à exposer les arts _ généralement visuels _ et notamment les peintures, les illustrations et les sculptures. On considère que le musée d'art est une invention assez moderne ; le plus ancien est le Louvre, qui ouvrit en 1793, peu après la Révolution française, lorsque les trésors royaux ont été déclarés propriété du peuple.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Eine Nationalgalerie ist die größte öffentlich zugängliche Kunstgalerie eines Landes. Diese Galerien sind unter verschiedenen Bezeichnungen in fast allen Hauptstädten weit verbreitet und dienen als Ausstellungsorte für Kunst, meist bildende Kunst, und zwar in erster Linie für Gemälde, Illustrationen und Skulpturen. Das Kunstmuseum als solches ist eine relativ moderne Einrichtung: Die erste Institution dieser Art war der Pariser Louvre, der erst 1793 - kurz nach der französischen Revolution - gebaut wurde, nachdem die königlichen Schätze per Dekret dem Volk zugänglich gemacht worden waren. </German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Una galleria nazionale &#232; la principale galleria d'arte pubblica di una nazione. Con diversi nomi se ne trovano in quasi ogni capitale. Sono uno spazio per l'esibizione dell'arte, solitamente visiva, e principalmente dipinti, illustrazioni e sculture. Il museo d'arte &#232; considerato un'invenzione abbastanza moderna: il primo &#232; quello del Louvre a Parigi fondato nel 1793, poco dopo la rivoluzione francese, quando i tesori reali vennero dichiarati di propriet&#224; del popolo. </Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Una galer&#237;a nacional es un gran museo de arte público de un pa&#237;s. Recibe diferentes nombres, pero casi todas las capitales del mundo cuentan con una de ellas. Hay un espacio para la exhibici&#243;n de elementos art&#237;sticos, normalmente artes visuales, fundamentalmente pintura, ilustraci&#243;n y escultura. El museo de arte se considera una invenci&#243;n relativamente moderna. El primero de ellos fue el Louvre en Par&#237;s, fundado en 1793, al poco de finalizar la Revoluci&#243;n Francesa y tras declarar públicos los bienes de la realeza. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE</Tag>
		<English>Opera House</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Opéra</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Opernhaus</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Teatro dell'opera</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>el Teatro de la Ópera</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An opera house is a building where operas are performed. The venues are usually constructed specifically with opera in mind, although other performing arts may be performed there. Notable opera houses include London's Globe Theater, where most of the plays of William Shakespeare were first performed on the stage, the Sydney Opera House, one of the most distinctive and famous 20th century buildings and La Scala in Milan. </English>
		<French>[TAB]Un opéra est un bâtiment où sont représentés les opéras. Les lieux sont généralement pensés pour l'opéra, mais peuvent servir pour d'autres représentations artistiques. Parmi les opéras les plus célèbres, on trouve le théâtre du Globe de Londres, où eut lieu la première représentation de la plupart des oeuvres de William Shakespeare, l'opéra de Sydney, l'un des bâtiments les plus marquants et les plus célèbres du XXe siècle, et la Scala de Milan.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Opernhaus ist ein Gebäude, in dem Opern aufgeführt werden. Es ist baulich normalerweise speziell für derartige Aufführungen konzipiert, es können aber auch andere darstellende Künste dargeboten werden. Berühmte Opernhäuser sind zum Beispiel das Globe Theatre in London, in dem die meisten Stücke von William Shakespeare uraufgeführt wurden, das Sydney Opera House, eins der markantesten und berühmtesten Bauwerke des 20. Jahrhunderts, sowie das Teatro alla Scala in Mailand.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Un teatro dell'opera &#232; un teatro in cui vengono rappresentate le opere. Solitamente sono costruiti in maniera specifica con in mente l'opera, anche se vi si possono tenere anche altri spettacoli. Fra i teatri dell'opera più conosciuti si annovera anche il Globe Theatre di Londra, in cui vennero rappresentati per la prima volta quasi tutti i lavori di Shakespeare, e il teatro dell'opera di Sydney, uno dei più particolari e famosi edifici del 20° secolo, oltre alla Scala di Milano. </Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Un Teatro de la Ópera es un edificio en el que se interpretan &#243;peras. Las instalaciones se suelen construir espec&#237;ficamente para la representaci&#243;n de &#243;peras, aunque tambi&#233;n pueden albergar otro tipo de actuaciones. Algunos de los teatros de &#243;pera m&#225;s famosos son el Globe Theatre de Londres, donde se presentaron la mayor&#237;a de las obras de William Shakespeare por primera vez, la Opera House de Sydney, uno de los edificios m&#225;s famosos del siglo XX y La Scala de Mil&#225;n. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WALL_STREET</Tag>
		<English>Stock Exchange</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Bourse</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>B&#246;rse</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Borsa</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>la Bolsa</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WALL_STREET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A stock exchange, share market or bourse is a corporation or mutual organization which provides facilities for stock brokers and traders, to trade company stocks and other securities. Stock exchanges also provide facilities for the issue and redemption of securities, as well as, other financial instruments and capital events including the payment of income and dividends. The most famous one is New York Stock Exchange, based in Wall Street. </English>
		<French>[TAB]Une Bourse, ou un marché financier, est une organisation qui permet aux courtiers et aux opérateurs de négocier des actions et d'autres titres. Les Bourses fournissent aussi l'infrastructure pour l'émission et le remboursement de titres ainsi que divers outils financiers, et elles permettent des opérations de capitaux comme le paiement de revenus et de dividendes. La Bourse la plus célèbre est celle de New York, située sur Wall Street.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Eine Börse ist ein organisierter Markt für Geschäfte mit Aktien, Anleihen, Devisen, oder bestimmten Waren, die von so genannten Maklern oder Brokern (Wertpapierhändlern) getätigt werden. Ebenso werden hier Wertpapiere und andere finanzielle Instrumente und Kapitalgeschäfte abgewickelt, einschließlich der Zahlung von Gewinnen und Dividenden. Die berühmteste Börse ist die New York Stock Exchange in der Wall Street.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Una borsa &#232; una corporazione o organizzazione che fornisce la possibilit&#224; ad agenti e scambisti di scambiare azioni e altre security delle varie compagnie. Le borse servono anche per l'emissione e il riscatto delle security, cos&#236; come di altri strumenti finanziari ed eventi capitali, incluso il pagamento di entrate e dividendi. La più famosa al mondo &#232; la borsa di New York, che si trova a Wall Street. </Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La bolsa o mercado de valores es una corporaci&#243;n u organizaci&#243;n que proporciona instalaciones a los &quot;corredores&quot; y comerciantes para intercambiar acciones de empresas y otros t&#237;tulos. Las bolsas tambi&#233;n brindan facilidades para librar, expedir o reembolsar t&#237;tulos, as&#237; como instrumentos financieros apropiados para el pago de rentas y dividendos. La m&#225;s famosa es la que se encuentra en la calle Wall Street de Nueva York.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SCOTLAND_YARD</Tag>
		<English>Interpol</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Interpol</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Interpol</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Interpol</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>la Interpol</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SCOTLAND_YARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Interpol (or International Criminal Police Organization) was created in 1923 to assist international criminal police cooperation. Interpol, once merely the organization's telegraphic address, was officially incorporated as the organization's new name in 1956, prior to which it was known as the International Criminal Police Commission. Interpol is the world's third largest international organization, after the United Nations and FIFA; it currently has 186 member countries.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Interpol (abréviation de l'anglais "International Criminal Police Organization") fut créée en 1923 pour faciliter la coopération policière internationale. Interpol n'était au départ que l'adresse télégraphique de l'organisation. C'est en 1956 que ce nom devint officiellement celui de l'organisation, appelée jusque-là International Criminal Police Commission. Interpol est la troisième plus grande organisation internationale, derrière l'ONU et la FIFA. Elle compte actuellement 186 pays membres.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Interpol (früher offiziell "International Criminal Police Commission", zu Deutsch: Internationale kriminalpolizeiliche Organisation (IKPO)) wurde 1923 als Kommission zur gemeinschaftlichen internationalen Verbrechensbekämpfung gegründet. Das Wort "Interpol" war ursprünglich lediglich die telegrafische Adresse der Organisation, wurde jedoch 1956 als offizielle Bezeichnung übernommen. Interpol stellt nach den Vereinten Nationen und der FIFA mit gegenwärtig 186 Mitgliedsstaaten die drittgrößte internationale Organisation dar.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]L'Interpol (o International Criminal Police Organization, Organizzazione Internazionale di Polizia Criminale) &#232; stata creata nel 1923 per assistere nella cooperazione internazionale tra polizie criminali. Interpol, che una volta era semplicemente l'indirizzo telegrafico dell'organizzazione, &#232; stato ufficialmente incorporato nel nome dell'organizzazione nel 1956, mentre precedentemente era conosciuta come International Criminal Police Commission (Commissione Internazionale di Polizia Criminale). L'Interpol &#232; la terza organizzazione più grande al mondo, dopo le Nazioni Unite e la FIFA; attualmente consta di 186 paesi membri.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La Interpol (&quot;International Criminal Police Organization&quot; u &quot;Organizaci&#243;n Internacional de Polic&#237;a Criminal&quot; en castellano) fue fundada en 1923 para mejorar la cooperaci&#243;n internacional de la polic&#237;a criminal. El nombre &quot;Interpol&quot;, que entonces solo era la direcci&#243;n de tel&#233;grafo de la organizaci&#243;n, fue adoptado en 1956 como nuevo nombre oficial de la organizaci&#243;n, que dej&#243; de llamarse Comisi&#243;n Internacional de Polic&#237;a Criminal. Interpol es la tercera organizaci&#243;n internacional m&#225;s grande del mundo, despu&#233;s de las Naciones Unidas y la FIFA, y cuenta con 186 pa&#237;ses miembro.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SUMMER_PALACE</Tag>
		<English>Summer Palace</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Palais d'été</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Sommerresidenz</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Palazzo d'estate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>el Palacio de Verano</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SUMMER_PALACE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A palace is the home of a head of state or other high-ranking public figure. Many palaces are now put to other uses such as parliaments or museums. Heads of State, especially monarchs, usually spend some weeks each year in other palaces that are not their primary residence. Such palaces are often called Winter Palaces or Summer Palaces, depending on the season they are used. A few examples are the Russian Winter Palace in St. Petersburg, the Chinese Summer Palace in Beijing, and the Kucuksu Summer Palace in Istanbul.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un palais est un lieu où réside un chef d'Etat ou un personnage public important. Beaucoup de palais ont aujourd'hui été reconvertis en parlements ou en musées. Les chefs d'Etat, et principalement les monarques, passent généralement quelques semaines par an dans des palais secondaires. Ces palais sont souvent appelés palais d'hiver ou palais d'été, suivant la saison à laquelle ils sont occupés. On peut citer, par exemple, le palais d'hiver de Saint-Pétersbourg en Russie, le palais d'été de Beijing en Chine, et le palais d'été de Küçüksu à Istanbul.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Eine Residenz ist der Wohnsitz eines Staatsoberhaupts oder einer anderen hochrangigen Person des öffentlichen Lebens. Viele Residenzen dienen heute als Parlamentssitze oder Museen. Staatsoberh&#228;upter, insbesondere Monarchen, leben in der Regel einige Wochen im Jahr nicht in ihrem Hauptwohnsitz, sondern (je nach Jahreszeit) in ihren so genannten Winter- oder Sommerresidenzen. Beispiele hierfür sind der russische Winterpalast in St. Petersburg, der chinesische Sommerpalast in Peking und der Kücüksu-Sommerpalast in Istanbul.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Un palazzo &#232; la casa di un capo di stato o di un'altra importante figura pubblica. Molti palazzi ora sono adibiti a usi diversi, come parlamenti o musei. I capi di stato, specialmente i monarchi, passano qualche settimana ogni anno in palazzi che non sono la loro residenza primaria. Solitamente sono chiamati palazzo d'inverno o d'estate, a seconda della stagione in cui vengono usati. Un esempio sono il Palazzo d'Inverno a San Pietroburgo, il Palazzo d'Estate a Pechino e il Palazzo d'Estate Kucuksu a Istanbul.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Un palacio es el hogar del jefe de estado o de otro personaje público de alto rango. Hoy en d&#237;a, muchos palacios se usan para cosas diferentes, por ejemplo, como sedes del Parlamento o museos. Los cabezas de estado, especialmente los monarcas, sol&#237;an pasar algunas semanas del a&#241;o fuera de su residencia habitual, en otros palacios. Dichos edificios sol&#237;an recibir el nombre de palacios de invierno o de verano, en funci&#243;n de la estaci&#243;n en la que fueran utilizados. Algunos ejemplos son el Palacio de Invierno ruso de San Petersburgo, el Palacio de Verano chino de Pek&#237;n, y el Palacio de Kucuksu, de verano, en Estambul.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BROADWAY</Tag>
		<English>Wembley</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Stade de Wembley</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Wembley</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Wembley</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Wembley</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BROADWAY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Wembley Stadium is one of the world's most famous football stadiums, located in Wembley, London. In 2003, the original structure was demolished, to be replaced by a new one due to open in 2007. When complete, the new Wembley Stadium will be the largest roof-covered football stadium in Europe. First known as the Empire Stadium, the original stadium was built for the British Empire Exhibition of 1924. The first event held at the stadium was the FA Cup final on 28 April 1923 between Bolton Wanderers and West Ham United.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le stade de Wembley est l'un des stades de football les plus connus au monde. Il est situé dans le quartier de Wembley à Londres. En 2003, la structure originale fut détruite afin de laisser place à un nouveau stade dont l'inauguration est prévue pour 2007. Une fois achevé, le nouveau stade de Wembley sera le plus grand stade de football couvert d'Europe. D'abord connu sous le nom d'Empire Stadium, le premier stade fut construit pour l'exposition de l'Empire britannique de 1924. Le premier événement organisé dans ce stade fut la finale de la FA Cup du 28 avril 1923, qui opposa le Bolton Wanderers au West Ham United.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Wembley-Stadion in Wembley, einem Londoner Teil des Londoner Stadtbezirks Brent, zählt zu den berühmtesten Fußballstadien der Welt. Nach dem Abriss des alten Stadiongebäudes im Jahr 2003 wurde der Neubau im Jahr 2007 feierlich wiedereröffnet und repräsentiert nun das zweitgrößte Stadion Europas und das weltweit größte mit einem beweglichen Dach. Ursprünglich wurde das Wembley-Stadion als Empire Stadion für die British Empire Exhibition des Jahres 1924 gebaut. Die erste Veranstaltung in diesem Stadion war am 28. April 1923 das Football Association Challenge Cup (FA Cup)-Finale zwischen den Bolton Wanderers und West Ham United.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Lo stadio di Wembley &#232; uno dei più famosi stadi di calcio al mondo e si trova a Wembley, Londra. Nel 2003 la struttura originaria venne demolita per essere rimpiazzata da un'altra, aperta nel 2007. Lo stadio di Wembley (nuovo) &#232; il più grande stadio calcistico al coperto d'Europa. Inizialmente conosciuto come Empire Stadium, lo stadio originale venne costruito per l'esibizione del British Empire nel 1924. Il primo evento che si tenne allo stadio fu la finale di Coppa d'Inghilterra del 28 aprile 1923, tra i Bolton Wanderers e il West Ham United.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El estadio de Wembley es uno de los estadios de fútbol m&#225;s famosos y se encuentra en Wembley, Londres. En el a&#241;o 2003 se demoli&#243; la estructura original, que ha sido reemplazada por un estadio nuevo en el 2007. El Nuevo Estadio de Wembley es el estadio cubierto m&#225;s grande de Europa. El estadio original, que entonces llevaba el nombre de &quot;Empire Stadium&quot; o &quot;Estadio Imperial&quot;, se construy&#243; con motivo de la &quot;British Empire Exhibition&quot; de 1924. El primer evento celebrado en el estadio fue la final de la Copa FA, el 28 de abril de 1923, entre el Bolton Wanderers y el West Ham United.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_DRAMA</Tag>
		<English>Hit Football Event</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Match de football majeur</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Fu&#223;ballveranstaltungen</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Eventi calcistici</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Eventos importantes de fútbol</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BONUS_DRAMA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Football (also known as association football or soccer) is a team sport played between two teams, of 11 players each, and is widely considered to be the most popular sport in the world. The modern game was officiated in England following the formation of the Football Association, whose 1863 set of rules created the foundations for how the sport is played today. Football is governed internationally by the FIFA. The most prestigious international football competition is the World Cup, played every four years, which is also the most widely viewed and famous sporting event in the world, even more popular than the Summer Olympics. In many parts of the world football evokes great passions and plays an important role in the life of individual fans, local communities, and even nations.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le football est un sport collectif opposant deux équipes de onze joueurs chacune. Il est largement admis qu'il s'agit du sport le plus populaire au monde. Le jeu moderne a été créé en Angleterre après la formation de la Football Association, dont les règles de 1863 ont servi de base pour définir le sport tel qu'il se joue aujourd'hui. Le football est géré au niveau international par la FIFA. La compétition internationale de football la plus prestigieuse est la Coupe du Monde, organisée tous les quatre ans, qui est aussi l'événement sportif le plus célèbre et le plus regardé au monde. La Coupe du Monde de football est même plus populaire que les jeux olympiques d'été. Dans bien des régions du monde, le football suscite les passions et joue un rôle important dans la vie des fans, des communautés locales et même des nations.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Fu&#223;ball ist ein Ballsport, bei dem zwei Mannschaften mit je elf Spielern (einem Torh&#252;ter und zehn Feldspielern) gegeneinander antreten. Er gilt weithin als die beliebteste Sportart der Welt. Heute gilt England als das Mutterland des Fußballs, denn dort wurde 1863 in London die Football Association (FA) gegründet wurde, welche das umfangreiche Regelwerk aufstellte, das die Grundlage für die heutige Spielweise in diesem Sport bildet. International ist der Fußballsport im Weltverband FIFA organisiert. Das bedeutendste internationale Fußballturnier ist die Fußballweltmeisterschaft, die alle vier Jahre ausgetragen wird. Sie stellt die weltweit berühmteste und meist gesehene Sportveranstaltung überhaupt dar und ist sogar noch populärer als die Olympischen Sommerspiele. In vielen Teilen der Welt weckt der Fußballsport große Leidenschaft und spielt im Leben der einzelnen Fans, regionaler Gemeinschaften und auch Nationen eine bedeutende Rolle.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il calcio &#232; uno sport di squadra giocato fra due squadre, ognuna composta da 11 giocatori, ed &#232; considerato lo sport più popolare al mondo. Il gioco moderno nacque in Inghilterra in seguito alla formazione della Football Association, le cui regole del 1863 crearono le fondamenta dello sport conosciuto oggi. Il calcio &#232; governato a livello internazionale dalla FIFA. Il torneo internazionale più prestigioso &#232; la Coppa del Mondo: si gioca ogni quattro anni ed &#232; l'evento sportivo più conosciuto e visto a livello mondiale, ancora più popolare delle Olimpiadi. In molte parti del mondo il calcio alimenta grandi passioni e gioca un ruolo importante nella vita dei singoli fan, delle comunit&#224; e addirittura delle nazioni.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El fútbol, sin duda el deporte m&#225;s popular del mundo, se juega entre dos equipos de once jugadores cada uno. El juego moderno fue oficializado en Inglaterra con la fundaci&#243;n de la &quot;Football Association&quot;, o &quot;Asociaci&#243;n de Fútbol&quot;, cuyo conjunto de 1.863 normas supuso la base del deporte que se juega hoy en d&#237;a. La FIFA es la organizaci&#243;n que rige los destinos del fútbol a nivel internacional. La competici&#243;n de mayor prestigio es la Copa del Mundo, que se juega cada cuatro a&#241;os y genera m&#225;s expectaci&#243;n que ningún otro evento deportivo del mundo, incluyendo los Juegos Ol&#237;mpicos. En muchas partes del mundo el fútbol suscita grandes pasiones y juega un papel muy importante en las vidas de los aficionados, comunidades locales e incluso naciones.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ROCKNROLL</Tag>
		<English>Graceland</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Graceland</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Graceland</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Graceland</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Graceland</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHANNEL_TUNNEL</Tag>
		<English>Channel Tunnel</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Tunnel sous la Manche</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Eurotunnel</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Canale della Manica</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>el Eurotúnel</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHANNEL_TUNNEL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Channel Tunnel (French: le tunnel sous la Manche) is a 31 mile (50.5 km)-long rail tunnel beneath the English Channel at the Straits of Dover, connecting Folkestone, Kent in England to Coquelles near Calais in northern France. A long-standing and very expensive megaproject that saw several false starts, it was finally completed in 1994. It is the second-longest rail tunnel in the world, with the Seikan Tunnel in Japan being longer, but the undersea section of 24 miles (39 km) is the longest of its kind in the world.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le tunnel sous la Manche est un tunnel ferroviaire long de 49,7 km, qui effectue la liaison entre Coquelles (près de Calais) dans le Nord de la France et Folkestone dans le Kent, en Angleterre. Après avoir été plusieurs fois abandonné, ce projet colossal au budget faramineux fut finalement achevé en 1994. Le tunnel sous la Manche est le deuxième plus grand tunnel au monde, le premier étant le tunnel du Seikan au Japon. Sa section sous la mer (37,3 km) est toutefois la plus longue au monde.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Eurotunnel oder Kanaltunnel ist ein 50 km langer Eisenbahntunnel, der unterhalb des Ärmelkanals an der Meerenge von Dover verläuft. Er verbindet Folkeston in Kent (England) und Coquelle nahe Calais in Nordfrankreich. Das langwierige und äußerst kostspielige Mega-Bauprojekt, dem einige fehlgeschlagene Tunnelbauversuche vorangingen, wurde schließlich 1994 vollendet. Der Tunnel ist nach dem Seikan-Tunnel in Japan der zweitlängste Eisenbahntunnel der Welt, wobei der 37,9 Kilometer lange unterseeische Tunnelabschnitt bislang weltweit unübertroffen ist.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il canale della Manica (in francese: le tunnel sous la Manche) &#232; un tunnel lungo 50,5 km che passa sotto la manica all'altezza dello stretto di Dover e collega Folkestone, Kent in Inghilterra con Coquelles, vicino a Calais nella Francia settentrionale. Si tratta di un mega progetto che &#232; rimasto in ballo molto tempo e ha avuto molte false partenze, ed &#232; stato finalmente completato nel 1994. &#200; il secondo tunnel ferroviario più lungo al mondo: &#232; superato solo dal tunnel Seikan in Giappone, ma la sezione subacquea di 39 km &#232; la più lunga al mondo, nel suo genere.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El Eurotúnel es un túnel de cincuenta kil&#243;metros y medio que recorre el subsuelo del Canal de la Mancha y que conecta Folkestone, Kent, en Inglaterra, con Coquelles, cerca de Calais, en el norte de Francia. Se trata de un largo y caro proyecto que, tras varias salidas en falso, fue finalmente terminado en 1994. Es el segundo túnel para transporte ferroviario m&#225;s largo del mundo, despu&#233;s del Túnel Seikan japon&#233;s. Sin embargo, su secci&#243;n submarina, de 39 kil&#243;metros, es la m&#225;s larga del mundo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRADING_COMPANY</Tag>
		<English>Trading Company</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Compagnie marchande</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Handelsgesellschaft</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Compagnia commerciale</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>la Compa&#241;&#237;a de las Indias</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRADING_COMPANY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A trading company is an association formed by investors or shareholders for the purpose of trade, exploration and colonisation. Typically, these companies were formed from the sixteenth century onwards by groups of European investors to underwrite and profit from the exploration of Africa, India, the Caribbean and North America, usually under the patronage of one state, which issued the company's charter. Notable companies include British East India Company and Dutch Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Une compagnie marchande est une association formée par des investisseurs ou des actionnaires s'intéressant au commerce, à l'exploration et à la colonisation. Ces compagnies furent créées à partir du XVIe siècle, généralement par des investisseurs européens, pour financer l'exploration de l'Afrique, de l'Inde, des Caraïbes et de l'Amérique du Nord, et bien sûr en tirer profit. Elles étaient généralement sous le patronage d'un Etat, qui leur accordait une charte. Parmi les compagnies les plus connues, on peut citer la British East India Company (Compagnie anglaise des Indes orientales) et la Dutch Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie (Compagnie hollandaise des Indes orientales).</French>
		<German>[TAB]Eine Handelsgesellschaft ist eine von Investoren oder Aktionären gebildete Interessengemeinschaft zum Zwecke des Handels, der Ausbeutung und der Kolonialisierung. Derartige Gesellschaften wurden seit dem 16. Jahrhundert von europäischen Investoren gebildet, um sich den Anspruch auf die privilegierte Ausbeutung Afrikas, Indiens, Nordamerikas und des karibischen Raumes sowie die damit verbundenen Profite zu sichern, üblicherweise unter der Führung eines Staates, der den Freibrief für die Gesellschaft ausstellte. Bedeutende Gesellschaften dieser Art waren die Britische Ostindien-Kompanie und die Niederl&#228;ndische Ostindien-Kompanie.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Una compagnia commerciale &#232; un'associazione formata da investitori o azionisti con lo scopo di commerciare, esplorare e colonizzare. Queste compagnie nacquero a partire dal sedicesimo secolo per volont&#224; di investitori europei, che desideravano finanziare e approfittare dell'esplorazione di Africa, India, Caraibi e Nord America, solitamente con l'appoggio di uno stato, che emetteva l'atto costitutivo della societ&#224;. Tra le più famose ci sono la Compagnia delle Indie Orientali Britannica e la Compagnia Olandese delle Indie Orientali.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Una compa&#241;&#237;a de las Indias es una asociaci&#243;n de inversores o accionistas cuyos fines son promocionar el comercio, la exploraci&#243;n y la colonizaci&#243;n. Estas compa&#241;&#237;as se formaron a partir del siglo XVI por grupos de inversores europeos que quer&#237;an financiar la exploraci&#243;n de África, la India, el Caribe y el norte de Am&#233;rica, normalmente bajo la tutela de un estado, que emit&#237;a la carta real o los estatutos de la compa&#241;&#237;a. Algunas de las m&#225;s notables fueron la brit&#225;nica Compa&#241;&#237;a de las Indias Orientales y la Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie holandesa.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLYMPIC_PARK</Tag>
		<English>Olympic Park</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Parc olympique</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Olympiapark</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Parco olimpico</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>el Estadio Ol&#237;mpico</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLYMPIC_PARK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An Olympic Park is a venue set up when a country hosts the Olympic Games. A cauldron is always built within the park and it's the final destination of the torch relay ceremony. The final bearer of the torch runs towards the cauldron, usually placed at the top of a grand staircase, and then uses the torch to start the flame in the stadium. The cauldron and the pedestal it sits on are always the subject of unique and often dramatic design. These also tie in with how the cauldron is lit during the Opening Ceremony. In Barcelona in 1992, an archer shot a flaming arrow immediately over the cauldron to light it.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un parc olympique est un lieu créé lorsqu'un pays accueille les jeux olympiques. Une vasque est toujours construite à l'intérieur du parc ; elle est la destination finale de la cérémonie de relais de la flamme olympique. Le dernier porteur de la torche court vers la vasque, généralement placée en haut d'un grand escalier, puis utilise la torche pour allumer la flamme dans le stade. La vasque et le piédestal sur lequel elle est posée ont toujours une forme unique et spectaculaire, qui déterminera comment sera allumée la vasque durant la cérémonie d'ouverture. A Barcelone en 1992, un archer a allumé la vasque en tirant une flèche enflammée juste au-dessus.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Olympiapark ist ein Veranstaltungsort, der von dem Gastgeberland Olympischer Spiele errichtet wird. Im Innern des Parks ist stets eine große Schale untergebracht, welche als letzte Station für die Zeremonie des Olympischen Fackellaufs dient: Der Schlussläufer läuft auf diese Schale zu, die üblicherweise am oberen Ende einer großen Treppe platziert ist, und entzündet im Stadion das Olympische Feuer. Die Schale und das Podest, auf dem sie angebracht ist, sind stets in einem einzigartigen und häufig dramatischen Design entworfen, das thematisch die Art und Weise widerspiegelt, wie das Feuer während der Er&#246;ffnungsfeier entfacht wird - bei den Olympischen Spielen in Barcelona 1992 schoss ein Bogensch&#252;tze einen brennenden Pfeil direkt &#252;ber den Kessel, um ihn zu entz&#252;nden.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Un Parco olimpico &#232; un complesso architettonico creato da un paese quando deve ospitare le Olimpiadi e al cui interno viene sempre costruito un braciere: la destinazione della fiamma olimpica. L'ultimo tedoforo corre verso il braciere, solitamente posto in cima a una grande scalinata, e poi usa la torcia per accendere la fiamma nello stadio. Il braciere e il piedistallo su cui riposa sono sempre oggetto di design molto particolari. Ci&#242; &#232; anche legato al modo in cui il braciere viene acceso durante la cerimonia d'apertura. A Barcellona nel 1992, per esempio, un arciere scocc&#242; una freccia incendiaria sopra il braciere, per accenderlo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Un estadio ol&#237;mpico es el edificio principal de acogida al público de unos Juegos Ol&#237;mpicos. Siempre se construye un pebetero en el interior del mismo, que es el destino final de la ceremonia de entrega de la antorcha. El último portador de la antorcha debe correr hacia el pebetero, que suele encontrarse en la cima de unas escaleras, y usar la citada antorcha para encender la llama del estadio. El pebetero y el pedestal que lo soporta siempre son objeto de una ceremonia única y a menudo impresionante. El protagonismo de este evento tambi&#233;n reside en el modo de pasar la llama al pebetero durante la ceremonia de inauguraci&#243;n. En Barcelona en 1992, un arquero dispar&#243; una flecha en llamas que inmediatamente encendi&#243; la llama del pebetero.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT</Tag>
		<English>Wat Preah Pisnulok</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Vat Preah Pisnulok</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Wat Preah Pisnulok</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Wat Preah Pisnulok</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Wat Preah Pisnulok</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- added by Leoreth -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MONUMENT</Tag>
		<English>Pagan Temple</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Temple Paien</Text>	<!-- stupid internet translation -->
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Heidnischer Tempel</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Tempio Etnico</Text>	<!-- stupid internet translation -->
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Templo Pagano:Templos Paganos</Text>	<!-- stupid internet translation -->
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<!-- Confucianism -> Zoroastrianism rename by Leoreth -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ZOROASTRIAN_TEMPLE</Tag>	<!-- translations missing -->
		<English>Zoroastrian Temple</English>
		<French>
			<Text></Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Zoroastrischer Tempel</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text></Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>:</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ZOROASTRIAN_MONASTERY</Tag>	<!-- translations missing -->
		<English>Zoroastrian Monastery</English>
		<French>
			<Text></Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Zoroastrisches Kloster</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text></Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>:</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ZOROASTRIAN_CATHEDRAL</Tag>	<!-- translations missing -->
		<English>Zoroastrian Royal Fire</English>
		<French>
			<Text></Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Zoroastrisches Königsfeuer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text></Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>:</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ZOROASTRIAN_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>Adur Farnbag</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Adur Farnbag</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Adur Farnbag</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Adur Farnbag</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Adur Farnbag:Adur Farnbag</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORTHODOX_TEMPLE</Tag>
		<English>Orthodox Church</English>
		<German>Orthodoxe Kirche</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORTHODOX_CATHEDRAL</Tag>
		<English>Orthodox Cathedral</English>
		<German>Orthodoxe Kathedrale</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORTHODOX_MONASTERY</Tag>
		<English>Orthodox Monastery</English>
		<German>Orthodoxes Kloster</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ORTHODOX_SHRINE</Tag>
		<English>The Hagia Sophia</English>
		<German>Die Hagia Sophia</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TEMPLE_OF_SALOMON</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Temple of Solomon</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Temple of Solomon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Tempel von Salomon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Temple of Solomon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Temple of Solomon:Temple of Solomon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ISHTAR_GATE</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Ishtar Gate</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ishtar Gate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Ishtar-Tor</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Ishtar Gate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Ishtar Gate:Ishtar Gate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_THEODOSIAN_WALLS</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Theodosian Walls</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Theodosian Walls</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Theodosische Mauern</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Theodosian Walls</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Theodosian Walls:Theodosian Walls</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TERRACOTTA_ARMY</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Terracotta Army</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Terracotta Army</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Terracotta-Armee</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Terracotta Army</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Terracotta Army:Terracotta Army</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEZQUITA</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>La Mezquita</English>
		<French>
			<Text>La Mezquita</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>La Mezquita</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>La Mezquita</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>La Mezquita:La Mezquita</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DOME_ROCK</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Dome of the Rock</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Dome of the Rock</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Felsendom</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Dome of the Rock</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Dome of the Rock:Dome of the Rock</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Topkapi Palace</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Topkapi Palace</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Topkapi-Palast</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Topkapi Palace</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Topkapi Palace:Topkapi Palace</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BRANDENBURG_GATE</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Brandenburg Gate</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Brandenburg Gate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Brandenburger Tor</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Brandenburg Gate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Brandenburg Gate:Brandenburg Gate</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KREMLIN</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>St. Basil's Cathedral</English>
		<French>
			<Text>St. Basil's Cathedral</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Basilius-Kathedrale</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>St. Basil's Cathedral</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>St. Basil's Cathedral:St. Basil's Cathedral</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SAN_MARCO</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>San Marco Basilica</English>
		<French>
			<Text>San Marco Basilica</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>San Marco Basilica</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>San Marco Basilica</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>San Marco Basilica:San Marco Basilica</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WESTMINSTER</Tag> <!-- translation needed! -->
		<English>Westminster Palace</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Westminster Palace</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Palast von Westminster</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Westminster Palace</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Westminster Palace:Westminster Palace</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CERN</Tag>
		<English>CERN Research Complex</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CERN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CERN Forschungskomplex</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CERN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CERN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TEMPLE_OF_SALOMON_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Doubles the revenue limit of all your shrines</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Verdoppelt die Einnahmegrenze aller Ihrer Schreine</German>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_APOSTOLIC_PALACE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Relocates the Catholic holy city</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Verlegt die heilige Stadt des Katholizismus</German>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BOROBUDUR</Tag>
		<English>Borobudur</English>
		<German>Borobudur</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANGKOR_WAT_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Artists can also be hired using Priest slots.</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Künstler können auch mithilfe von Priesterstellen eingestellt werden.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KHAJURAHO</Tag>
		<English>Khajuraho</English>
		<German>Khajuraho</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELP_KHAJURAHO</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]State Religion buildings are constructed twice as fast</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Gebäude der Staatsreligion werden doppelt so schnell gebaut</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIMEJI_CASTLE</Tag>
		<English>Himeji Castle</English>
		<German>Die Burg von Himeji</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELP_HIMEJI_CASTLE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]New melee and archery units start with City Garrison I and Drill I[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Amount of [ICON_GOLD]looted doubled</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Neue Nahkampf- und Pfeil- und Bogeneinheiten starten mit Garnison I und Drill I[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Menge des geplünderten [ICON_GOLD]verdoppelt</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PORCELAIN_TOWER</Tag>
		<English>Porcelain Tower</English>
		<German>Porzellanturm</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELP_PORCELAIN_TOWER</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]All trade routes are counted as foreign and intercontinental</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]All Handelsrouten werden als ausländische und Überseerouten gewertet</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARMANDIR_SAHIB</Tag>
		<English>Harmandir Sahib</English>
		<German>Harmandir Sahib</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELP_HARMANDIR_SAHIB</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]All units built in cities with state religion receive +2 experience</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Alle Einheiten, die in Städten mit Staatsreligion ausgebildet werden, erhalten +2 Erfahrung</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH</Tag>
		<English>The Great Bath</English>
		<German>Das Große Bad</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HELP_GREAT_BATH</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Provides fresh water to the city[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]All newly founded cities receive one additional point of population</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Versorgt die Stadt mit Süßwasser[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Alle neu gegründeten Städte erhalten einen zusätzlichen Bevölkerungspunkt</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHINESE_EXAMINATION_HALL</Tag>
		<English>Taixue</English>
		<German>Taixue</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INDIAN_STEPWELL</Tag>
		<English>Stepwell</English>
		<German>Stufenbrunnen</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_THAI_HO_TRAI</Tag>
		<English>Ho Trai</English>
		<German>Ho Trai</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_JAPANESE_SHALE_PLANT</Tag>
		<English>Kaizen Plant</English>
		<German>Kaizen-Kraftwerk</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Can draft one extra unit per turn</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kann eine zusätzliche Einheit pro Runde rekrutieren</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BLUE_MOSQUE</Tag>
		<English>Blue Mosque</English>
		<German>Blaue Moschee</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RED_FORT</Tag>
		<English>The Red Fort</English>
		<German>Das Rote Fort</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STATUE_OF_ZEUS_EFFECT</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]No city resistance on conquest[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Increases military unit production speed by 25% in all cities with pagan temples</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kein Widerstand nach Stadteroberung[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Erhöht die Produktionsgeschwindigkeit militärischer Einheiten in allen Städten mit heidnischen Tempeln um 25%</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TERRACOTTA_ARMY_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Unlimited Experience from Barbarian Units[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Victories Against Barbarians Contribute to Great General Birth</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Unbegrenzte Erfahrung von barbarischen Einheiten[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Siege gegen Barbaren tragen zur Geburt großer Generäle bei</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAFALGAR_SQUARE</Tag>
		<English>Trafalgar Square</English>
		<German>Trafalgar Square</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAFALGAR_SQUARE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Requires a naval unit of level three or higher.</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Benötigt eine Marineeinheit der Stufe drei oder höher.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAFALGAR_SQUARE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Allows faster construction of ships, extra naval experience in this city.</English>
		<German>Erlaubt schnelleren Schiffsbau, extra Erfahrung für Schiffe in dieser Stadt.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EMPIRE_STATE</Tag>
		<English>The Empire State Building</English>
		<German>Das Empire State Building</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EMPIRE_STATE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Empire State Building is a 102-story landmark Art Deco skyscraper in New York City at the intersection of Fifth Avenue and West 34th Street. Its name is derived from the nickname for New York, The Empire State. It stood as the world's tallest building for more than 40 years, from its completion in 1931 until construction of the World Trade Center's North Tower was completed in 1972. Following the terrorist bombing and destruction of the World Trade Center in 2001, the Empire State Building again became the tallest building in New York City.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EMPIRE_STATE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The Empire State Building provides a gold bonus equal to the population of the city in which it's built.</English>
		<German>Das Empire State Building produziert Gold entsprechend der Bevölkerung in der Stadt, in der es errichtet wurde.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EMPIRE_STATE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Provides [ICON_GOLD] bonus equal to city's population.</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Produziert [ICON_GOLD] entsprechend der Bevölkerung seiner Stadt.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GRAND_CANAL</Tag>
		<English>The Grand Canal</English>
		<German>Kaiserkanal</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GRAND_CANAL_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Extra commerce on river tiles.</English>
		<German>Extra Kommerz an Flussfeldern.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FLOATING_GARDENS</Tag>
		<English>Floating Gardens</English>
		<German>Schwimmende Gärten</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FLOATING_GARDENS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>Extra food on river tiles.</English>
		<German>Extra Nahrung an Flussfeldern.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KGB</Tag>
		<English>Lubyanka</English>
		<German>Lubyanka</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KGB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Lubyanka is the popular name for the headquarters of the KGB and affiliated prison on Lubyanka Square in Moscow. It is a large building with a facade of yellow brick, designed by Alexander V. Ivanov in 1897 and augmented by Aleksey Shchusev in 1940-1947.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The Lubyanka was originally built in 1898 as the Neo-Baroque headquarters of the All-Russia Insurance Company, noted for its beautiful parquet floors and pale green walls. Belying its massiveness, the edifice avoids an impression of heroic scale: isolated Palladian and Baroque details, such as the minute pediments over the corner bays and the central loggia, are lost in an endlessly-repeating classicizing palace facade, where three bands of cornices emphasize the horizontal lines. A clock is centered in the uppermost band of the facade.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Following the Bolshevik Revolution, the structure was seized by the government for the headquarters of the secret police, then called the Cheka. In Soviet Russian jokes it was referred to as the tallest building in Moscow, since Siberia could be seen from its basement. Another joke referred to the building as "Adult's World" as compared to "Children's World," the name of the popular toy store across the street.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]During the Great Purge, the offices became increasingly cramped due to staff numbers. In 1940, the most famous Soviet architect, Shchusev, was commissioned to double its size by adding another storey and engulfing backstreet buildings. Shchusev's design accentuated Neo-Renaissance detailing, but only the left part of the facade was reconstructed under his direction in the 1940s, due to the war and other hindrances. This asymmetric facade survived intact until 1983, when the symmetry was restored at the urging of Yuri Andropov in accordance with Shchusev's plans.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Although the Soviet secret police changed its name many times, its headquarters remained in this building. Secret police chiefs from Lavrenty Beria to Yuri Andropov used the same office on the third floor, which looked down on the statue of Cheka founder Felix Dzerzhinsky. A prison at the ground floor of the building figures prominently in Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn's classic study of the Soviet police state, The Gulag Archipelago. Famous inmates held, tortured and interrogated there include Sidney Reilly, Raoul Wallenberg, János Esterházy and Father Walter Ciszek, S.J.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]After the dissolution of the KGB, the Lubyanka became the headquarters of the Border Guard Service of Russia, and houses the Lubyanka prison and one directorate of the Federal Security Service of the Russian Federation (FSB). In addition a museum of the KGB was opened to the public. On November 11, 1999 a fire broke out in the Lubyanka. Four FSB agents were injured, but damage was relatively mild. The fire was later traced to faulty wiring.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KGB_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Lubyanka[COLOR_REVERT] gives extra espionage from specialists.</English>
		<German>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Lubyanka[COLOR_REVERT] erzeugt zusätzliche Spionage durch Spezialisten.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STONEHENGE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Great prophets can create great works like great artists.</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Große Propheten können große Kunstwerke erstellen, genau wie große Künstler.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROJECT_PERSECUTION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Religious persecution is the systematic mistreatment of an individual or group of individuals as a response to their religious beliefs or affiliations or lack thereof.
The tendency of societies or groups within society to alienate or repress different subcultures is a recurrent theme in human history. Moreover, because a person's religion often determines to a significant extent his or her morality and personal identity, religious differences can be significant cultural factors.
Religious persecution may be triggered by religious bigotry (i.e. the denigration of practitioners' religions other than those of the oppressors) or by the State when it views a particular religious group as a threat to its interests or security. At a societal level, this dehumanization of a particular religious group may readily turn into violence or other forms of persecution. Indeed, in many countries, religious persecution has resulted in so much violence that it is considered a human rights problem.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BLUE_MOSQUE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Sultan Ahmed Mosque is a historical mosque in Istanbul, the largest city in Turkey and the capital of the Ottoman Empire from 1453 to 1923. The mosque is popularly known as the Blue Mosque for the blue tiles adorning the walls of its interior. It was built between 1609 and 1616, during the rule of Ahmed I. Like many other mosques, it also comprises a tomb of the founder, a madrasah and a hospice. [PARAGRAPH:1]The design of the Sultan Ahmed Mosque is the culmination of two centuries of both Ottoman mosque and Byzantine church development. It incorporates some Byzantine elements of the neighboring Hagia Sophia with traditional Islamic architecture and is considered to be the last great mosque of the classical period. The architect has ably synthesized the ideas of his master Sinan, aiming for overwhelming size, majesty and splendour.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BOROBUDUR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Borobudur is an 8th-century Mahayana Buddhist monument near Magelang, Central Java, Indonesia. The monument comprises six square platforms topped by three circular platforms, and is decorated with 2,672 relief panels and 504 Buddha statues. A main dome, located at the center of the top platform, is surrounded by 72 Buddha statues seated inside perforated stupa.[PARAGRAPH:2]The monument is both a shrine to the Lord Buddha and a place for Buddhist pilgrimage. The journey for pilgrims begins at the base of the monument and follows a path circumambulating the monument while ascending to the top through the three levels of Buddhist cosmology, namely Kamadhatu (the world of desire), Rupadhatu (the world of forms) and Arupadhatu (the world of formlessness). During the journey, the monument guides the pilgrims through a system of stairways and corridors with 1,460 narrative relief panels on the walls and the balustrades.[PARAGRAPH:2]Evidence suggests Borobudur was abandoned following the 14th-century decline of Buddhist and Hindu kingdoms in Java, and the Javanese conversion to Islam. Worldwide knowledge of its existence was sparked in 1814 by Sir Thomas Stamford Raffles, then the British ruler of Java, who was advised of its location by native Indonesians. Borobudur has since been preserved through several restorations. The largest restoration project was undertaken between 1975 and 1982 by the Indonesian government and UNESCO, following which the monument was listed as a UNESCO World Heritage Site. Borobudur is still used for pilgrimage; once a year Buddhists in Indonesia celebrate Vesak at the monument, and Borobudur is Indonesia's single most visited tourist attraction.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BRANDENBURG_GATE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Brandenburg Gate is a former city gate and one of the main symbols of Berlin and Germany. It is located west of the city center at the intersection of Unter den Linden and Ebertstra&#223;e, immediately west of the Pariser Platz. It is the only remaining gate of a series through which one formerly entered Berlin. One block to the north stands the Reichstag. The gate is the monumental entry to Unter den Linden, the renowned boulevard of linden trees which formerly led directly to the city palace of the Prussian monarchs. It was commissioned by King Frederick William II of Prussia as a sign of peace and built by Karl Gotthard Langhans from 1788 to 1791. The Brandenburg Gate was restored from 2000 to 2002 by the Stiftung Denkmalschutz Berlin (Berlin Monument Conservation Foundation). Today, it is considered one of Europe's most famous landmarks.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Das Brandenburger Tor in Berlin steht am Pariser Platz in der Dorotheenstadt im Ortsteil Mitte (Bezirk Mitte). Es wurde in den Jahren von 1788 bis 1791 auf Anweisung des preußischen Königs Friedrich Wilhelm II. von Carl Gotthard Langhans errichtet und ist das bekannteste Wahrzeichen der Stadt. Zugleich ist das Tor ein nationales Symbol, mit dem viele wichtige Ereignisse der Geschichte Berlins, Deutschlands, Europas und der Welt des 20. Jahrhunderts verbunden sind. Der Bau ist dem frühklassizistischen Stil zuzuordnen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Mit dem Bau der Zollmauer der Stadt Berlin wurde 1734 ein Vorgängerbau des heutigen Brandenburger Tores als Stadttor an der Straße nach Brandenburg an der Havel errichtet. Die Toranlage bestand aus Pylonen und beigeordneten Wachhäusern. Im Zuge des Ausbaus der Mauer und ihrer Tore ließ Friedrich Wilhelm II. ab 1788 das Brandenburger Tor neu gestalten, das dem Andenken an den Krieg des kurz zuvor verstorbenen Friedrich II. diente, von dessen Verdiensten auch etwas Glanz auf den Neffen und Nachfolger fallen sollte.[PARAGRAPH:2]Als Architekt wurde Carl Gotthard Langhans beauftragt. Er orientierte sich an dem "Stadttor von Athen", das er aus Stichen von Leroy, Stuart und Revett kannte, die aber die Propyläen der Athener Akropolis abgebildet hatten. Das Eingangstor zur Akropolis war im dorischen Stil des Parthenon gehalten, um eine optische Einheit zu bilden. Das Tor hatte eine breite Mittelöffnung und zwei schmale Seiteneingänge für Fußgänger. Im rechten Winkel dazu standen zwei Seitenflügel. Nach Langhans Planung sollten entsprechend beim Berliner Tor durch den breiten Mittelgang die königlichen Kutschen, daneben die sonstigen Gespanne fahren und außen die Fußgänger gehen. In den Seitenflügeln sollten die Wache und die Akziseeinnehmer untergebracht werden. 1788 wurde das alte Tor abgerissen, eine große Baugrube ausgehoben und fundamentiert. 1789 wurde der Neubau begonnen. Die Baukosten lagen bei 111.000 Talern. Am 6. August 1791 wurde das noch nicht ganz fertige Tor geöffnet.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die 1793 von Johann Gottfried Schadow gefertigte Quadriga auf dem Brandenburger Tor stellte ursprünglich nach der wohl überwiegend vertretenen Auffassung eine geflügelte Friedensbringerin dar. Das Brandenburger Tor erhielt den Namen Friedenstor, diesen Namen zeigte auch eine Inschrift aus Bronzelettern am Tor. Diese Sinngebung interpretiert auch der bildliche Schmuck. Die Entwürfe für die Reliefs wurden vorwiegend von dem Maler und Akademiedirektor Christian Bernhard Rode angefertigt. Schadow hat die Entwürfe überarbeitet und die Steinmetze bei der Ausführung beaufsichtigt. Die Göttin in der Quadriga wird durch das Relief auf der Attika der Stadtseite als Friedensbringerin erklärt. Das Attikarelief steht unter dem Thema "Der Zug der Friedensgöttin". Im Zentrum des Reliefs über dem Mittelgang stehen Sinnbilder auf Frieden und Freundschaft. Die Friedensgöttin Eirene steht auf der äußersten Kante eines Triumphwagens. Mit der Rechten stützt sie sich auf den mit einer Lorbeergirlande geschmückten Rand des Wagens. In der einen Hand hält sie einen Palmenzweig, in der anderen einen Lorbeerkranz. Ihr Wagen wird von vier Eroten gezogen. Weiter rechts auf dem Attikarelief kann man Nike mit Flügeln und Tropaion erkennen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Direkt über diesem Relief steht die Quadriga Schadows. Deren göttliche Wagenlenkerin ist Nike und Eirene in einer Person. Nach einer abweichenden Auffassung soll es sich von Anfang an um eine "Siegesgöttin" gehandelt haben, unter anderem weil davon bereits im Vertrag zur Anfertigung der Figurengruppe vom 22. Juli 1789 die Rede gewesen sei. Schadow hatte ursprünglich für die Wagenlenkerin keine Trophäe entworfen. Ihm schwebte mehr die griechische Eirene als Friedensgöttin vor, als die römische Siegesgöttin Viktoria. 1793 verlangte dann aber ein Akademiebeschluss eine Kopie der Siegestrophäe der Nike rechts auf dem Attikarelief auch für die Wagenlenkerin der Quadriga. Bei der Bevölkerung fand sie keinen Zuspruch. Aufgrund heftiger Kritik besserte Schadow noch ein weiteres Mal nach. Das Tropaion wurde nun durch eine Lanze mit einem Lorbeerkranz und einem römischen Adler ersetzt. Außerdem erhielt die knapp bekleidete Wagenlenkerin nun ein bis auf den Boden reichendes Gewand.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DOME_ROCK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Dome of the Rock is located at the visual center of an ancient man-made platform known as the Temple Mount, which Muslims refer to as the "Noble Sanctuary". The platform, greatly enlarged under the rule of Herod the Great, is the site of the Second Jewish Temple which was destroyed during the Roman Siege of Jerusalem in 70 CE. In 637 CE, Jerusalem was conquered by the Rashidun Caliphate army during the Islamic invasion of the Byzantine Empire.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Dome of the Rock was erected between 685 and 691 CE. The names of the two engineers in charge of the project are given as: Yazid Ibn Salam from Jerusalem and Raja Ibn Haywah from Baysan. Umayyad Caliph Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan who initiated construction of the Dome, hoped that it would "house the Muslims from cold and heat" and intended the building to serve as a shrine for pilgrims and not as a mosque for public worship. Historians contend that the Caliph wished to create a structure which would compete with the existing buildings of other religions in the city. al-Maqdisi writes that he "Sought to build for the Muslims a masjid that should be unique and a wonder to the world. And in like manner, is it not evident that Caliph Abd al-Malik, seeing the greatness of the martyrium of the Church of the Holy Sepulchre and its magnificence was moved lest it should dazzle the minds of Muslims and hence erected above the Rock the dome which is now seen there."[PARAGRAPH:2]During the Crusades the Dome of the Rock was given to the Augustinians, who turned it into a church, and the Al-Aqsa Mosque became the royal palace of Baldwin I of Jerusalem in 1104. The Knights Templar, who believed the Dome of the Rock was the site of the Temple of Solomon, set up their headquarters in the Al-Aqsa Mosque adjacent to the Dome for much of the 12th century. The "Templum Domini," as they called it, was featured on the official seals of the Order's Grand Masters, and it became the architectural model for Templar churches across Europe.[PARAGRAPH:2]Jerusalem was recaptured by Saladin on Friday, 2 October 1187 and the Haram was reconsecrated as a Muslim sanctuary. The cross on top of the Dome of the Rock was replaced by a golden crescent and a wooden screen was placed around the rock below. Salah al-Din's nephew al-Malik al-Mu'azzam Isa (615-24/1218-27) carried out other restorations within the Haram and added the porch to the Aqsa mosque.[PARAGRAPH:2]Large-scale renovation was undertaken during the reign of Mahmud II in 1817. Adjacent to the Dome of the Rock, the Ottomans built the free-standing Dome of the Prophet in 1620.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Dome of the Rock was badly shaken during an earthquake in Palestine on Monday, 11 July 1927 rendering useless many of the repairs that had taken place over previous years.[PARAGRAPH:2]Under Jordanian rule of Jerusalem, Jews were forbidden from entering the Old City. Israel took control of the Dome of the Rock during its victory in the Six-Day War in 1967. A few hours after the Israeli flag was hoisted over the Dome of the Rock in 1967, at the conclusion of the Six-Day War, Israelis lowered it on the orders of General Moshe Dayan, and invested the Muslim Waqf (religious trust) with the authority to manage the Temple Mount-Haram al-Sharif in order to "keep the peace".[PARAGRAPH:2]The Dome of the Rock, being among a complex of buildings on the Temple Mount, (the other principal building being the Al-Aqsa Mosque) is one of the holiest sites in Islam, following Mecca, Medina, and, for shia Muslims, the Imam Ali Mosque. Its significance stems from the religious beliefs regarding the rock at its heart. According to Islamic tradition, the rock is the spot from where Muhammad ascended to Heaven accompanied by the angel Gabriel.[PARAGRAPH:2]The stone over which the Muslim shrine, the Dome of Rock, was built is the holiest site in Judaism. Jews have traditionally regarded the location of the stone as the holiest spot on Earth, the site of the Holy of Holies during the Temple Period. In former times, some Jewish scholars thought that the location of the Holy of Holies was not known for certain. Today this is a minority opinion.[PARAGRAPH:2]Just as Muslims pray towards the Kaaba at Mecca, the holiest site in Islam, Jews pray towards the site of the ancient Holy of Holies, the Foundation Stone, the holiest site in Judaism.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Christianity it is believed that during the time of the Byzantine Empire, nearby the spot where the Dome was later constructed was where Constantine's mother built a small church, calling it the Church of St. Cyrus and St. John, later on enlarged and called the Church of the Holy Wisdom. On the walls of the Dome of the Rock is an inscription in a mosaic frieze that includes the following words:[PARAGRAPH:2]"Bless your envoy and your servant Jesus son of Mary and peace upon him on the day of birth and on the day of death and on the day he is raised up again. It is a word of truth in which they doubt. It is not for God to take a son. Glory be to him when he decrees a thing he only says be, and it is."</English>
		<German>Der Felsendom ist das wohl bekannteste Wahrzeichen Jerusalems und eines der Hauptheiligtümer des Islam. Er befindet sich auf dem Tempelberg im südöstlichen Teil der Altstadt von Jerusalem. Der Felsendom ist der älteste islamische Sakralbau und stellt ein Meisterwerk der islamischen Baukunst des frühen Umayyadenstils dar, in welchem die Übernahme des frühchristlich-byzantinischen Zentralbautyps zum Ausdruck kommt.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Kuppelbau wurde über dem Felsen (Sachra) errichtet, auf welchem Abraham der biblischen Erzählung nach seinen Sohn Isaak zu opfern bereit war und wo die Himmelfahrt Mohammeds stattgefunden haben soll. Er ist ursprünglich - und auch heute - nicht als Moschee, sondern als ein Schrein beziehungsweise eine Kuppel verstanden worden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Erbauung des Felsendoms wird in der neueren Forschung dem Kalifen ?Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan (regierte 685-705) sowie dessen Sohn und Nachfolger al-Walid ibn ?Abd al-Malik (reg. 705-715), der auch den Bau der al-Aqsa-Moschee weitergeführt haben soll, zugeschrieben. Die Bauinschrift in archaischem kufischen Duktus, die über dem Kranzgesims an der Kuppel erhalten ist, dokumentiert nicht nur den Namen des Erbauers, sondern auch die ursprüngliche Bezeichnung der Anlage, die man lediglich als Kuppel (Qubba) verstanden hat; der hier in Klammern stehende Namensteil ist vom Abbasidenkalifen Al-Ma?mun getilgt und durch seinen eigenen Namen ersetzt worden.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HIMEJI_CASTLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Himeji Castle is a hilltop Japanese castle complex located in Himeji in Hyogo Prefecture. The castle is regarded as the finest surviving example of prototypical Japanese castle architecture, comprising a network of 83 buildings with advanced defensive systems from the feudal period. The castle is frequently known as Hakurojou or Shirasagijou ("White Heron Castle") because of its brilliant white exterior and supposed resemblance to a bird taking flight.[PARAGRAPH:2]Himeji Castle dates to 1333, when Akamatsu Norimura built a fort on top of Himeyama hill. The fort was dismantled and rebuilt as Himeyama Castle in 1346, and then remodeled into Himeji Castle two centuries later. Himeji Castle was then significantly remodeled in 1581 by Toyotomi Hideyoshi, who added a three-story castle keep. In 1600, Tokugawa Ieyasu awarded the castle to Ikeda Terumasa for his help in the Battle of Sekigahara, and Ikeda completely rebuilt the castle from 1601 to 1609, expanding it into a large castle complex. Several buildings were later added to the castle complex by Honda Tadamasa from 1617 to 1618. For over 400 years, Himeji Castle has remained intact, even throughout the extensive bombing of Himeji in World War II, and natural disasters such as the 1995 Great Hanshin earthquake.[NEWLINE][TAB]Himeji Castle is the largest and most visited castle in Japan, and it was registered in 1993 as one of the first UNESCO World Heritage Sites in the country. The area within the middle moat of the castle complex is a designated Special Historic Site and five structures of the castle are also designated National Treasures. Along with Matsumoto Castle and Kumamoto Castle, Himeji Castle is considered one of Japan's three premier castles. In order to preserve the castle buildings, it is currently undergoing restoration work that is expected to continue for several years.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEZQUITA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Mezquita (Spanish for "mosque") of Córdoba or Cordova is a Roman Catholic cathedral originally built as a mosque in the Andalusian city of Córdoba, Spain. It is regarded as perhaps the most accomplished monument of the Umayyad dynasty of Córdoba. After the Spanish Reconquista, it was turned into a church, with a Gothic cathedral inserted into the center of the large Moorish building. Today the entire building is used to house the Cathedral of the diocese of Córdoba in Spain.[PARAGRAPH:2]The building was begun in approximately 600 A.D. as the Christian Visigothic church of St. Vincent. The first Muslim Emir Abd ar-Rahman I bought the church and reworked it over two centuries to refashion it as a mosque, starting in 784 A.D. Additionally, Abd ar-Rahman I used the mosque (originally called Aljama Mosque) as an adjunct to his palace and named it to honor his wife. According to some authors the church of St. Vincent was demolished after it was bought from the local Christian community.[PARAGRAPH:2]Several explanations have been proposed to explain the mosque's unorthodox orientation. Some have suggested the mihrab faces south because the foundations of the mosque were taken from the old Roman and Visigoth constructions. Others contend that Abd ar-Rahman oriented the mihrab southward as if he were still in the Ummayyad capital of Damascus and not in exile.[PARAGRAPH:2]The mosque underwent numerous subsequent changes: Abd ar-Rahman III ordered a new minaret; Al-Hakam II, in 961, enlarged the building and enriched the mihrab. The last of the reforms was carried out by Al-Mansur Ibn Abi Aamir in 987.[PARAGRAPH:2]It was the most magnificent of the more than 1,000 mosques in the city and was at one time the second largest mosque in the Muslim world. It was connected to the Caliph's palace by a raised walk-way, mosques within the palaces being the tradition for the Islamic rulers of all times.[PARAGRAPH:2]The city in which it was built was subject to frequent invasion and each conquering wave added their own mark to the architecture. The building is most notable for its giant arches, with over 1,000 columns of jasper, onyx, marble, and granite. These were made from pieces of the Roman temple which had occupied the site previously, as well as other destroyed Roman buildings. The double arches, pictured above, were a new introduction to architecture, and helped support the tremendous weight of the higher ceilings. The double arches consist of a lower horseshoe arch and an upper semi-circular arch. The Mezquita also features richly gilded prayer niches. A centrally located honey-combed dome has beautiful blue tiles decorated with stars. The mihrab is a masterpiece of architectural art, with geometric and flowing designs of plants. The Mezquita reached its current dimensions in 987 A.D. with the completion of the outer naves and orange tree courtyard.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1236, Córdoba was recaptured from the Muslim army by King Ferdinand III of Castile and the mosque was reconsecrated as a Christian church. Alfonso X oversaw the construction of the Villaviciosa Chapel and the Royal Chapel within the mosque. The kings who followed added further Christian features: Enrique II rebuilt the chapel in the 14th century.[PARAGRAPH:2]The most significant alteration was building a Renaissance cathedral nave in the middle of the structure. It was constructed by permission of Charles V, king of united Spain. Its reversion to a Christian church (officially the Cathedral of the Assumption of the Virgin) may have helped to preserve it when the Spanish Inquisition was most active.[PARAGRAPH:2]Artisans and architects continued to add to the existing structure until the late 18th century.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Die Mezquita-Catedral von Córdoba ist seit der Reconquista der Stadt deren römisch-katholische Kathedrale. Ihre architektonische Weltgeltung besitzt sie aber als ehemalige Hauptmoschee - al-Dschami? al-kabir / Dschami? Qur?uba - aus der Epoche des maurischen Spaniens. Als Kirche heißt sie Mariä-Empfängnis-Kathedrale. Mezquita ist die spanische Form des arabischen Wortes ?Masgid und entspricht dem ebenfalls gleichbedeutenden deutschen Wort Moschee. Der berühmte Betsaal ist durch Hufeisenbögen in Mittel- und Querschiffe aufgeteilt. Er wurde durch die Emire und Kalifen von Córdoba in mehreren Bauabschnitten immer wieder erweitert. Die Kathedrale von der Aufnahme Unserer Lieben Frau gehört mit ca. 23.000 m² zu den größten ehemaligen Moscheebauten weltweit.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Ort, an dem sich die Kathedrale befindet, diente schon zu Zeiten des Römischen Reiches der Religionsausübung. Es befand sich dort ein römischer Tempel, danach eine westgotische Kathedrale für Sankt Vincent von Saragossa.[PARAGRAPH:2]Mit dem Bau der Moschee wurde 784 unter der Aufsicht von Abd ar-Rahman I., dem ersten umayyadischen Emir von Córdoba, begonnen. In den zwei folgenden Jahrhunderten wurde sie erweitert. Abd ar-Rahman III. gab ein neues Minarett in Auftrag, Al-Hakam II. erweiterte das Gebäude und stattete den Mihrab mit neuen Elementen aus. Die im Betsaal aufstehenden Säulen sind Spolien; die heute vorhandenen Bogenformen zur Hervorhebung einzelner Betsaalbereiche sind erst in der Bauphase unter Al-Hakam II. verwendet worden. Die letzten Erweiterungen wurden durch den Wesir Al-Mansur Ibn Abi Aamir 987 vorgenommen. Die Mezquita war die prächtigste der Moscheen der Stadt. Córdoba wurde in den folgenden Jahrhunderten häufig erobert, und auf jede Eroberung folgten Veränderungen der Architektur.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PORCELAIN_TOWER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Porcelain Tower (or Porcelain Pagoda) is a historical site located on the south bank of the Yangtze in Nanjing, China. It was a pagoda constructed in the 15th century during the Ming Dynasty, but was mostly destroyed in the 19th century during the course of the Taiping Rebellion. There is purportedly a movement underway to reconstruct the tower. As of 2010, reconstruction of the tower and temple grounds went underway. The projected completion date of the first phase of reconstruction is 2014.[PARAGRAPH:2]The original blocks of the Nanjing Tower's arched door, now pieced back together and on display at the Nanjing Museum [NEWLINE][TAB]The Porcelain Tower of Nanjing was designed during reign of the Yongle Emperor (r. 1402-1424) shortly before its construction, in the early 15th century. It was first discovered by the Western world when European travelers like Johan Nieuhof visited it, sometimes listing it as one of the Seven Wonders of the World. After this exposure to the outside world, the tower was seen as a national treasure to both locals and other cultures around the world.[NEWLINE][TAB]In 1801, the tower was struck by lightning and the top three stories were knocked off, but it was soon restored. The 1843 book The Closing Events of the Campaign in China by Granville Gower Loch contains a detailed description of the tower as it existed in the early 1840s. In the 1850s, the area surrounding the tower erupted in civil war as the Taiping Rebellion reached Nanjing and the Taiping Rebels took over the city. They smashed the Buddhist images and destroyed the inner staircase to deny the Qing enemy an observation platform. American sailors reached the city in May 1854 and visited the hollowed tower. In 1856, the Taiping destroyed the tower in order to prevent a hostile faction from using it to observe and shell the city. After this point, the tower's remnants were forgotten and it lay dormant until a recent surge to try to rebuild the landmark.[PARAGRAPH:2]The original blocks of the Nanjing Tower's arched door, now pieced back together and on display at the Nanjing Museum [NEWLINE][TAB]The tower was octagonal with a base of about 97 feet (30 m) in diameter. When it was built, the tower was one of the largest buildings in China, rising up to a height of 260 feet (79 m) with nine stories and a staircase in the middle of the pagoda, which spiraled upwards for 184 steps. The top of the roof was marked by a golden pineapple. There were originally plans to add more stories, according to an American missionary who in 1852 visited Nanjing. There are only a few Chinese pagodas that surpass its height, such as the still existent 275-foot-tall (84 m) 11th-century Liaodi Pagoda in Hebei or the no longer existent 330-foot-tall (100 m) 7th-century wooden pagoda of Chang'an.[NEWLINE][TAB]The tower was built with white porcelain bricks that were said to reflect the sun's rays during the day, and at night as many as 140 lamps were hung from the building to illuminate the tower. Glazes and stoneware were worked into the porcelain and created a mixture of green, yellow, brown and white designs on the sides of the tower, including animals, flowers and landscapes. The tower was also decorated with numerous Buddhist images.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SAN_MARCO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]San Marco Basilica, the cathedral church of Venice, is the most famous of the city's churches and one of the best known examples of Byzantine architecture. It lies on Piazza San Marco adjacent and connected to the Doge's Palace. Originally it was the "chapel" of the Venetian rulers, and not the city's cathedral. Since 1807 it has been the seat of the Patriarch of Venice, archbishop of the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Venice. For its opulent design, gilded Byzantine mosaics, and its status as a symbol of Venetian wealth and power, from the 11th century on the building was known by the nickname Chiesa d'Oro (Church of gold).[PARAGRAPH:2]The first San Marco's was a temporary building in the Doge's Palace, constructed in 828, when Venetian merchants stole the supposed relics of San Marco the Evangelist from Alexandria. This was replaced by a new church on its present site in 832; from the same century dates the first San Marco's Campanile (bell tower). The new church was burned in a rebellion in 976, rebuilt in 978 and again to form the basis of the present basilica since 1063. The basilica was consecrated in 1094, the same year in which the body of San Marco was supposedly rediscovered in a pillar by Vitale Faliero, doge at the time. The building also incorporates a low tower (now housing San Marco's Treasure), believed by some to have been part of the original Doge's Palace. Within the first half of the 13th century the narthex and the new façade were constructed, most of the mosaics were completed and the domes were covered with higher wooden, lead-covered domes in order to blend in with the Gothic architecture of the redesigned Doge's Palace.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Der Markusdom (italienisch Basilica di San Marco) in Venedig war bis 1797 das zentrale Staatsheiligtum der Republik Venedig und ist seit 1807 die Kathedrale des Patriarchen von Venedig. Er befindet sich am Markusplatz im Stadtsechstel San Marco.[PARAGRAPH:2]Bis zum Untergang der Republik war es erklärte Absicht der venezianischen Regierung durch die Jahrhunderte hindurch, den Sitz des Bischofs möglichst weit entfernt vom Zentrum der Macht zu wissen. San Marco dagegen war die Palastkapelle des Dogen, später Staatskirche Venedigs. Sie wurde erbaut als würdige Ruhestätte für die Gebeine des Evangelisten Markus, des Stadtheiligen Venedigs, der den heiligen Theodor als Stadtpatron ablöste. Der Bischofspalast und der Bischofssitz des Patriarchen von Venedig befanden sich bis zur Säkularisierung in dem abgelegenen Distrikt von San Pietro di Castello.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die erste dem heiligen Markus geweihte Kirche wurde 828 gestiftet und in den Jahren 829 bis 832 anstelle einer Hauskapelle des Dogenpalastes erbaut, um die aus Alexandria durch eine List venezianischer Kaufleute entführten Gebeine des Evangelisten Markus aufzunehmen. 976 fielen Kirche, Dogenpalast und 200 Häuser einer Feuersbrunst zu Opfer. Im selben Jahr begann der Doge Pietro I. Orseolo mit dem Wiederaufbau, der nach mehrmaligen Unterbrechungen erst 1094 beendet war. Die (angeblichen) Gebeine des Hl. Markus wurden durch ein (angebliches) Wunder am 25. Juni 1094 "wiedergefunden". Dieser Tag wurde zum Feiertag Inventio Sancti Marci.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TERRACOTTA_ARMY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Terracotta Army is a collection of terracotta sculptures depicting the armies of Qin Shi Huang, the first Emperor of China. It is a form of funerary art buried with the emperor in 210-209 BC and whose purpose was to help guard his empire in his afterlife.[NEWLINE][TAB]The figures, dating from 3rd century BC, were discovered in 1974 by some local farmers in Lintong District, Xi'an, Shaanxi province, near the Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor.[NEWLINE][TAB]The figures vary in height, according to their roles, with the tallest being the generals. The figures include warriors, chariots, horses, officials, acrobats, strongmen and musicians. Current estimates are that in the three pits containing the Terracotta Army there were over 8,000 soldiers, 130 chariots with 520 horses and 150 cavalry horses, the majority of which are still buried in the pits.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Terracotta Army was discovered in the spring of 1974 to the east of Xi'an in Shaanxi Province by a group of farmers when they were digging a water well 1.5 miles (2.4 km) north of Mount Li (Lishan), a region riddled with underground springs and watercourses. For centuries, there were reports of pieces of terracotta figures and fragments of the Qin necropolis - roofing tiles, bricks, and chunks of masonry - having been occasionally dug up in the area. This most recent discovery prompted archaeologists to investigate, and they unearthed the largest pottery figurine group ever found in China. In 195 B.C., Liu Bang - the first emperor of the dynasty that followed the Qin - had ordered that 'twenty households' should move to the site of the mausoleum of the First Emperor of Qin (Shi Huangdi, "Shi Huangdi" means the first emperor) to watch over the tomb. To this day, twenty villages sit in the immediate vicinity of the mausoleum, one of them the hamlet where those who made the discovery lived.[PARAGRAPH:2]In addition to the warriors, an entire man-made necropolis for the emperor has also been found. Qin Shi Huangdi's necropolis complex was constructed as a microcosm of his imperial palace or compound. It consists of several offices, halls, stables and other structures placed around the tomb mound which is surrounded by two solidly built rammed earth walls with gateway entrances. Up to 5 meters (16 feet) of reddish, sandy soil had accumulated over the site in the centuries following its construction, but archaeologists found evidence of earlier disturbances at the site. During the digs at Mount Li, archaeologists found several graves dating from the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, where diggers had apparently struck terracotta fragments which were then discarded as worthless back into the back-filled soil.[NEWLINE][TAB]According to historian Sima Qian (145-90 BC), work on this mausoleum began in 246 BC soon after Emperor Qin ascended the throne (then aged 13), and the full construction later involved 700,000 workers. Geographer Li Daoyuan, six centuries after the death of the First Emperor, recorded in Shui Jing Zhu that Mount Li was a favoured location due to its auspicious geology: "... famed for its jade mines, its northen side was rich in gold, and its southern side rich in beautiful jade; the First Emperor, envious of its fine reputation, therefore chose to be buried there". Sima Qian, in his most famous work, Shiji, completed a century after the mausoleum completion, wrote that the First Emperor was buried with palaces, towers, officials, valuable artefacts and wonderful objects. According to this account, there were 100 rivers simulated with flowing mercury, and above them the ceiling was decorated with heavenly bodies below which were the features of the land. Some translations of this passage refer to "models" or "imitations," those words however weren't used in the original text.[PARAGRAPH:2]Recent scientific work at the site has found high levels of mercury in the soil of the tomb mound, giving some credence to Sima Qian 's account of the emperor's tomb. The tomb mound is located at the foot of Mount Li as an earthen pyramid, and the tomb of Shi Huangdi appears to be a hermetically sealed space that is as big as a football pitch and located underneath the pyramid. The tomb remains unopened, one possible reason may be concerns about the preservation of valuable artifacts once the tomb is opened. For example, the painted surface of the terracotta army began to flake and fade once they have been excavated. Later historical accounts suggested that the tomb had been looted by Xiang Yu, a contender for the throne, five years after the death of the emperor, however there are indications that the tomb may not have been plundered.[NEWLINE][TAB]Only a portion of the site is presently excavated, and photos and video recordings are prohibited in some viewing areas. Only a few foreign dignitaries, such as Queen Elizabeth II, have been permitted to walk through the pits to observe the army at close quarters.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GRAND_CANAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Grand Canal in China, also known as the Beijing-Hangzhou Grand Canal is the longest canal or artificial river in the world. Starting at Beijing, it passes through Tianjin and the provinces of Hebei, Shandong, Jiangsu and Zhejiang to the city of Hangzhou. The oldest parts of the canal date back to the 5th century BC, although the various sections were finally combined during the Sui Dynasty (581-618 CE).[NEWLINE][TAB]The total length of the Grand Canal is 1,776 km (1,103 miles). Its greatest height is reached in the mountains of Shandong, at a summit of 42 m (138 ft). Ships in Chinese canals did not have trouble reaching higher elevations after the pound lock was invented in the 10th century, during the Song Dynasty (960-1279), by the government official and engineer Qiao Weiyo. The canal's size and grandeur won it the admiration of many throughout history, including the Japanese monk Ennin (794-864), the Persian historian Rashid al-Din (1247-1318), the Korean official Choe Bu (1454-1504) and the Italian missionary Matteo Ricci (1552-1610).[NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, periodic flooding of the adjacent Yellow River threatened the safety and functioning of the canal. During wartime the high dikes of the Yellow River were sometimes deliberately broken in order to flood advancing enemy troops. This caused disaster and prolonged economic hardships. Despite temporary periods of desolation and disuse, the Grand Canal furthered an indigenous and growing economic market in China's urban centers through all the ages since the Sui period.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RED_FORT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Red Fort, or Lal Qila, is a 17th century fort complex constructed by the Mughal emperor Shah Jahan in the walled city of Old Delhi (in present day Delhi, India). Shah Jahan moved his capital here from Agra in a move designed to bring prestige to his reign, and to provide ample opportunity to apply his ambitious building schemes and interests. It served as the capital of the Mughals until 1857, when Mughal emperor Bahadur Shah Zafar was exiled by the British Indian  government. [PARAGRAPH:1]Shah Jahan started construction of the massive fort in 1638 and work was completed in 1648. The Red Fort was originally referred to as "Qila-i-Mubarak" (the blessed fort), because it was the residence of the royal family. The layout of the Red Fort was organised to retain and integrate this site with the Salimgarh Fort. The fortress palace was an important focal point of the medieval city of Shahjahanabad. The planning and aesthetics of the Red Fort represent the zenith of Mughal creativity which prevailed during the reign of Emperor Shah Jahan.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_THEODOSIAN_WALLS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The original walls of Constantinople were built in the 8th century BC when Byzantium was founded by Greek colonists from Megara. At the time the city consisted of an acropolis and little more. The colony was relatively unimportant by the Roman period, but Septimius Severus built a new set of walls during his reign, bringing more land into the city. When Constantine moved the capital of the empire to Byzantium, which he renamed Constantinople, he greatly expanded the walls of the city, incorporating even more territory.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 412 the Roman emperor Theodosius II surrounded Constantinople with a wall that stretched 6.5 kilometers between the Sea of Marmara and the Golden Horn. Although named after Theodosius, they were actually constructed under the direction of Anthemius, Praetorian prefect of the Eastern Empire.[PARAGRAPH:2]The walls were built of stone and brick in two lines of defense which adjoined a ditch 20 meters wide and 10 meters deep. The inner wall had was 5 meters thick and 12 meters high. It was strengthened with 96 unapproachable towers 18-20 meters tall. The thickness of the external wall was 2 meters, and its height was 8.5 meters. The wall contained the Belgrad, Silivrikapi, Mevlevihane, Topkapi, Edirnekapi, Egrikapi and Yedikule gates. Yedikule Gate was also known as the "Porta Aurea" or "Golden Gate", and was the most magnificent, consisting of three archways. As the state entrance into the capital, the Golden Gate was architecturally splendid, and was built of large square blocks of polished marble fitted together without cement, and flanked by two great towers of the same material. Upon the gates were placed sculpted elephants.[PARAGRAPH:2]The inner walls had massive square or hexagonal towers. The southern end of the walls, at the Sea of Marmara, was the location of the Marble Tower. There were ten gates, the four major ones being the Golden Gate at the southern end, the Selymbria Gate leading to the Forum of Constantine and Hagia Sophia, the Adrianople Gate connecting Constantinople's Mese (the main street) with the city of Adrianople and the Via Egnatia, and the Blachernae Gate in the north.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 439 the first sea walls were built. In 447 the wall was damaged by an earthquake, but was quickly restored in time to stop Attila's army. In the northwestern corner of the city, in the suburb of Blachernae, the Theodosian walls were relatively weaker, but were expanded by Leo I. The northern coast of the city, along the Golden Horn, also had a separate set of walls.[PARAGRAPH:2]These walls were almost inpenetrable, saving the city during sieges from the Bulgars, Arabs, and Rus', among others. The first attackers to break through the walls were the knights of the Fourth Crusade, who managed to scale the lower sea walls and also break the Wall of Leo in the northwestern Blachernae section of the city.[PARAGRAPH:2]The second and final time the walls were breached was during the Siege of Constantinople in 1453, by the Ottomans; however, they did not break through by force, but entered through the Kerkoporta Gate, which happened to be open, apparently accidentally but possibly through treachery. A large plaque today marks the spot where the Ottomans entered. Mehmed had the walls repaired in short order among other massive public works projects. Within a few years, due to the renewed importance of the city as the new Ottoman capital, the population started to soar again.[PARAGRAPH:2]Under the Ottomans, the Golden Gate, known to them as Yedikule ("the Seven Towers"), was used as a prison. Many parts of the walls are still standing today and are a testament to the extraordinary longevity of the empire. They have been damaged by recent earthquakes, but many sections have also been restored. The wall runs through the suburbs of modern Istanbul, with a belt of parkland flanking their course. The walls are pierced at intervals by modern roads leading westwards out of the city.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Die Theodosianische Mauer ist eine Anfang des 5. Jahrhunderts unter Kaiser Theodosius II. und dem Präfekten Anthemius errichtete, etwa 19-20 Kilometer lange Befestigungsanlage (Land- und Seemauern) zum Schutz von Konstantinopel, dem heutigen Istanbul.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Theodosianische Mauer wird von einigen Historikern als eine der erfolgreichsten und bestdurchdachten Befestigungsanlagen in der Geschichte der Kriegstechnik angesehen. Viele der einschneidensten Ereignisse in der Geschichte der Stadt stehen eng mit diesem außergewöhnlichen Bauwerk in Zusammenhang. Der Bau des Wallsystems wurde notwendig, um der Bedrohung durch die Hunnen zu begegnen und der rasch expandierenden Stadt zusätzlichen Raum zu verschaffen. Trotz zunehmenden Verfalles und dem Aufkommen der Feuerwaffen, waren die Befestigungen bei entschlossener Verteidigung auch noch in der Mitte des 15. Jahrhunderts nur schwer zu überwinden. Die Komplexität der Verteidigungsanlagen trug wesentlich zum langen Bestehen des Byzantinischen Reiches bei.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TOPKAPI_PALACE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Topkapi Palace is a palace in Istanbul, Turkey, which was the official and primary residence in the city of the Ottoman Sultans, from 1465 to 1853. The palace was a setting for state occasions and royal entertainments and is a major tourist attraction today. The name directly translates as "Cannongate Palace", from the palace being named after a nearby, now lost gate.[PARAGRAPH:2]The initial construction started in 1459, ordered by Sultan Mehmed II, the conqueror of Byzantine Constantinople. The palace is a complex made up of four main courtyards and many smaller buildings. At the height of its existence as a royal residence, the palace was home to as many as 4,000 people, formerly covering a larger area with a long shoreline. The complex has been expanded over the centuries, with many renovations such as after the 1509 earthquake and 1665 fire.[PARAGRAPH:2]Topkapi Palace gradually lost its importance at the end of the 17th century, as the Sultans preferred to spend more time in their new palaces along the Bosporus. In 1853, Sultan Abd&#252;l Mecid I decided to move the court to the newly built Dolmabah&#231;e Palace, the first European-style palace in the city. Some functions, such as the imperial treasury, the library, mosque and mint, were retained though.[PARAGRAPH:2]After the end of the Ottoman Empire in 1921, Topkapi Palace was transformed by government decree on April 3, 1924 into a museum of the imperial era. The Topkapi Palace Museum is under the administration of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism. The palace complex has hundreds of rooms and chambers, but only the most important are accessible to the public today. The complex is guarded by officials of the ministry as well as armed guards of the Turkish military. The palace is full of examples of Ottoman architecture and also contains large collections of porcelain, robes, weapons, shields, armor, Ottoman miniatures, Islamic calligraphic manuscripts and murals, as well as a display of Ottoman treasure and jewelry.[PARAGRAPH:2]Topkapi Palace is among those monuments belonging to the "Historic Areas of Istanbul", which became a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1985, and is described in Criterion iv as "the best example(s) of ensembles of palaces of the Ottoman period."</English>
		<German>[TAB]Der Topkapi-Palast (im Deutschen auch Topkapi-Serail, wörtlich "Kanonentor-Palast") in Istanbul war jahrhundertelang der Wohn- und Regierungssitz der Sultane sowie das Verwaltungszentrum des Osmanischen Reiches.[PARAGRAPH:2]Mit dem Bau wurde kurz nach der Eroberung Konstantinopels (1453) durch Sultan Mehmed II. begonnen. Zunächst ordnete er die Errichtung des Palastes auf dem heutigen Beyazitplatz (Beyazit Meydani) an, entschied sich dann aber für die heute Sarayburnu genannte Landspitze zwischen Goldenem Horn und Marmarameer. Dabei wurden Teile des byzantinischen Mangana-Palastes überbaut. Ihr heutiges Aussehen erhielt die Anlage durch umfangreiche Renovierungen und Erweiterungen bis zum Anfang des 18. Jahrhunderts. Seit Mehmed II. residierten alle osmanischen Herrscher im Topkapi-Palast, bis Sultan Abdülmecid I. im Jahre 1856 das neue Dolmabahçe Sarayi auf der anderen Seite des Goldenen Horns am Ufer des Bosporus bezog. Beide Paläste sind heute Museen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Palast besteht nicht aus einem einzelnen, sondern getreu der türkischen Tradition aus mehreren Gebäuden in einem großen Garten. Mit einer Fläche von über 69 Hektar und bis zu 5000 Bewohnern war der Palast eine eigene Stadt. Man nannte ihn anfangs Saray-i Cedîd-i Âmire oder Yeni Saray /,Neuer Palast', bevor sich im 18. Jahrhundert der Name Topkapi Sarayi durchsetzte, der sich von der palasteigenen Kanonengießerei ableitete.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Palast ist in vier Höfe unterteilt, die jeweils durch eigene Tore erreicht werden. Mit seiner Lage auf einer Landspitze bietet er eine beispiellose Panoramasicht auf Istanbul, den Bosporus und das Goldene Horn.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FLOATING_GARDENS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Floating Garden is a method of ancient Mesoamerican agriculture which used small, rectangle-shaped areas of fertile arable land to grow crops on the shallow lake beds in the Valley of Mexico.  Often referred to as "floating gardens," Floating Gardens were artificial islands that usually measured roughly 30 × 2.5 m (98 × 8.2 ft), although they were sometimes longer. They were created by staking out the shallow lake bed and then fencing in the rectangle with wattle. The fenced-off area was then layered with mud, lake sediment, and decaying vegetation, eventually bringing it above the level of the lake. Often trees were planted at the corners to secure the Floating Garden. Floating Gardens were separated by channels wide enough for a canoe to pass.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ISHTAR_GATE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Ishtar Gate was the eighth gate to the inner city of Babylon. It was constructed in about 575 BC by order of King Nebuchadnezzar II on the north side of the city.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dedicated to the Babylonian goddess Ishtar, the gate was constructed of blue glazed tiles with alternating rows of bas-relief sirrush (dragons) and aurochs.[PARAGRAPH:2]The roof and doors of the gate were of cedar, according to the dedication plaque. Through the gate ran the Processional Way, which was lined with walls covered in lions on glazed bricks (about 120 of them).[PARAGRAPH:2]Statues of the deities were paraded through the gate and down the Processional Way each year during the New Year's celebration.[PARAGRAPH:2]Originally the gate, being part of the Walls of Babylon, was considered one of the Seven Wonders of the world until, in the 6th century AD, it was replaced by the Lighthouse of Alexandria.[PARAGRAPH:2]A reconstruction of the Ishtar Gate and Processional Way was built at the Pergamon Museum in Berlin out of material excavated by Robert Koldewey and finished in the 1930s. It includes the inscription plaque. It stands 47 feet high and 100 feet wide (14 meters by 30 meters). The excavation ran from 1902-1914, and, during that time, 45 feet of the foundation of the gate was uncovered.[PARAGRAPH:2]The gate was in fact a double gate. The part that is shown in the Pergamon Museum today is only the smaller, frontal part, while the larger, back part was considered too large to fit into the constraints of the structure of the museum. It is in storage.[PARAGRAPH:2]Parts of the gate and lions from the Processional Way are in various other museums around the world. Only three museums acquired dragons, while lions went to several museums. The Istanbul Archaeology Museum has lions, dragons, and bulls. The Detroit Institute of Arts houses a dragon. The Röhsska Museum in Gothenburg, Sweden, has one dragon and one lion; the Louvre, the State Museum of Egyptian Art in Munich, the Royal Ontario Museum in Toronto, the University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology in Philadelphia, the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York, the Oriental Institute in Chicago, the Rhode Island School of Design Museum, the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston, and the Yale University Art Gallery in New Haven, Connecticut, each have lions.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ZOROASTRIAN_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Apart from (relatively) minor fire temples, three were said to derive directly from Ahura Mazda, thus making them the most important in Zoroastrian tradition. These were the "Great Fires" or "Royal Fires" of Adur Burzen-Mihr, Adur Farnbag, and Adur Gushnasp. The legends of the great fires are probably of antiquity, for by the 3rd century CE, miracles were said to happen at the sites and the fires were popularly associated with other legends such as those of the folktale heroes Fereydun, Jamshid and Rustam.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Bundahishn, a Zoroastrian view of creation finished in the 11th or 12th century CE, states that the Great Fires had existed since creation and had been brought forth on the back of the ox Srishok to propagate the faith, dispel doubt, and to protect all humankind. Other texts observe that the Great Fires were also vehicles of propaganda and symbols of imperial sovereignty.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Farnbag fire (translated as 'the fire Glory-Given' by Darmesteter) was considered the most venerated of the three because it was seen as the earthly representative of the Atar Spenishta, 'Holiest Fire' of Yasna 17.11 and described in a Zend commentary on that verse as the "the one burning in Paradise in the presence of Ohrmazd."</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAFALGAR_SQUARE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Trafalgar Square is a public space and tourist attraction in central London, England, United Kingdom built around the area formerly known as Charing Cross. It is in the borough of the City of Westminster. At its centre is Nelson's Column, which is guarded by four lion statues at its base. There are a number of statues and sculptures in the square, with one plinth displaying changing pieces of contemporary art. The square is also used for political demonstrations and community gatherings, such as the celebration of New Year's Eve.[PARAGRAPH:1]The name commemorates the Battle of Trafalgar (1805), a British naval victory of the Napoleonic Wars over France. The original name was to have been "King William the Fourth's Square", but George Ledwell Taylor suggested the name "Trafalgar Square".[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 1820s, George IV engaged the architect John Nash to redevelop the area. Nash cleared the square as part of his Charing Cross Improvement Scheme. The present architecture of the square is due to Sir Charles Barry and was completed in 1845.[PARAGRAPH:1]Trafalgar Square is owned by the Queen in Right of the Crown, and managed by the Greater London Authority, while Westminster City Council owns the roads around the square, including the pedestrianised area of the North Terrace.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CERN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The European Organization for Nuclear Research (French: Organisation européenne pour la recherche nucléaire), known as CERN or Cern is an international organization whose purpose is to operate the world's largest particle physics laboratory, in the northwest suburbs of Geneva on the Franco-Swiss border. Established in 1954, the organization has 20 European member states.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term CERN is also used to refer to the laboratory, which employs just under 2,400 full-time employees, 1,500 part-time employees, and hosts some 10,000 visiting scientists and engineers, representing 608 universities and research facilities and 113 nationalities.[PARAGRAPH:1]CERN's main function is to provide the particle accelerators and other infrastructure needed for high-energy physics research. Numerous experiments have been constructed at CERN by international collaborations to make use of them. It is also the birthplace of the World Wide Web. The main site at Meyrin also has a large computer centre containing very powerful data-processing facilities primarily for experimental data analysis and, because of the need to make them available to researchers elsewhere, has historically been a major wide area networking hub.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARMANDIR_SAHIB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Harmandir Sahib, also referred to as the Golden Temple, is a prominent Sikh Gurdwara located in the city of Amritsar, Punjab, India. Construction of the Gurdwara was begun by Guru Ram Das ji, the fourth Sikh Guru, and completed by his successor, Guru Arjan Dev ji. In 1604, Guru Arjan Dev ji completed the Adi Granth, the holy scripture of Sikhism, and installed it in the Gurdwara. In 1634, Guru Hargobind left Amritsar for the Shivalik Hills and for the remainder of the seventeenth century the city and Gurdwara was in the hands of forces hostile to the Sikh Gurus. During the eighteenth century, Sri Harmandir Sahib was the site of frequent fighting between the Sikhs on one side and either Mughal or Afghan forces on the other side and the Gurdwara occasionally suffered damage. In the early nineteenth century, Maharaja Ranjit Singh secured the Punjab region from outside attack and covered the upper floors of the Gurdwara with gold, which gives it its distinctive appearance and English name of "Golden Temple".[PARAGRAPH:1]The present day Golden Temple was rebuilt in 1764 by Maharaja Jassa Singh Ahluwalia (1718-1783) with the help of other Misl Sikh chieftains.The gold plating of all the domes of Sri Darbar Sahib was done by Maharaja Jassa Singh Ahluwalia's descendents. Between 1802-1830 Ranjit Singh did the sewa of adding gold plating and marble to the Gurdwara, while the interior was decorated with fresco work and gemstones.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KHAJURAHO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Khajuraho Group of Monuments in Khajuraho, a town in the Indian state of Madhya Pradesh, located in Chhatarpur District, about 620 kilometres (385 mi) southeast of New Delhi, is one of the most popular tourist destinations in India. Khajuraho has the largest group of medieval Hindu and Jain temples, famous for their erotic sculptures.
The name Khajuraho, ancient "Kharjuravahaka", is derived from the Sanskrit words kharjura = date palm and vahaka = "one who carries". In the 19th century, British engineer T.S. Burt arrived in the area, followed by General Alexander Cunningham. Cunningham put Khajuraho on the world map when he explored the site on behalf of the Archaeological Survey of India and described what he found in glowing terms. The Khajuraho Group of Monuments has been listed as a UNESCO World Heritage Site, and is considered to be one of the "seven wonders" of India.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WESTMINSTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Palace of Westminster is the meeting place of the House of Commons and the House of Lords, the two houses of the Parliament of the United Kingdom. Commonly known as the Houses of Parliament after its tenants, the Palace lies on the Middlesex bank of the River Thames in the City of Westminster, in central London. Its name, which derives from the neighbouring Westminster Abbey, may refer to either of two structures: the Old Palace, a medieval building complex that was destroyed by fire in 1834, and its replacement New Palace that stands today. For ceremonial purposes, the palace retains its original style and status as a royal residence.[PARAGRAPH:1]The first royal palace was built on the site in the eleventh century, and Westminster was the primary London residence of the Kings of England until a fire destroyed much of the complex in 1512. After that, it served as the home of Parliament, which had been meeting there since the thirteenth century, and the seat of the Royal Courts of Justice, based in and around Westminster Hall. In 1834, an even greater fire ravaged the heavily rebuilt Houses of Parliament, and the only structures of significance to survive were Westminster Hall, the Cloisters of St Stephen's, the Chapel of St Mary Undercroft and the Jewel Tower.[PARAGRAPH:1]The subsequent competition for the reconstruction of the Palace was won by architect Charles Barry and his design for a building in the Perpendicular Gothic style. The remains of the Old Palace (with the exception of the detached Jewel Tower) were incorporated in its much larger replacement, which contains over 1,100 rooms organised symmetrically around two series of courtyards. Part of the New Palace's area of 3.24 hectares (8 acres) was reclaimed from the Thames, which is the setting of its principal façade, the 266-metre (873 ft) river front. Barry was assisted by Augustus W. N. Pugin, a leading authority on Gothic architecture and style, who provided designs for the decoration and furnishings of the Palace. Construction started in 1840 and lasted for thirty years, suffering great delays and cost overruns, as well as the death of both leading architects; works for the interior decoration continued intermittently well into the twentieth century. Major conservation work has been carried out since, due to the effects of London's air pollution, and extensive repairs took place after the Second World War, including the reconstruction of the Commons Chamber following its bombing in 1941.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Palace is one of the centres of political life in the United Kingdom; "Westminster" has become a metonym for the UK Parliament, and the Westminster system of government has taken its name after it. The Elizabeth Tower, in particular, which is often referred to by the name of its main bell, "Big Ben", is an iconic landmark of London and the United Kingdom in general, one of the most popular tourist attractions in the city and an emblem of parliamentary democracy. The Palace of Westminster has been a Grade I listed building since 1970 and part of a UNESCO World Heritage Site since 1987.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STONEHENGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Great Sphinx of Giza, commonly referred to as the Sphinx, is a limestone statue of a reclining or couchant sphinx (a mythical creature with a lion's body and a human head) that stands on the Giza Plateau on the west bank of the Nile in Giza, Egypt.[PARAGRAPH:1]It is the largest monolith statue in the world, standing 73.5 metres (241 ft) long, 19.3 metres (63 ft) wide, and 20.22 m (66.34 ft) high. It is the oldest known monumental sculpture, and is commonly believed to have been built by ancient Egyptians of the Old Kingdom during the reign of the pharaoh Khafra (c. 25582532 BC).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FORBIDDEN_PALACE_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Civic Upkeep Reduced by 33%</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Staatsformen-Unterhalt um 33% reduziert</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_EIFFEL_TOWER_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Golden Ages Consume at most Three Great People</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Goldene Zeitalter verbrauchen höchstens drei große Persönlichkeiten</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PYRAMID_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Hurry Unhappiness Does Not Increase with the Amount of Sacrificed Population</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Die Unzufriedenheit durch Sklaverei steigt nicht mit der Anzahl der geopferten Bevölkerung</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_WALL_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Reduced Enemy Movement Speed Within the Walls.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Barbarian Units Take Damage within the Walls</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Geringere Bewegung feindlicher Einheiten innerhalb der Mauern.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Barbarische Einheiten nehmen Schaden innerhalb der Mauern</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEZQUITA_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Builder Receives a Great Person</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Erbauer erhält eine große Persönlichkeit</German>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>