<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_AGRARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Agrarianism has two common meanings. The first meaning refers to a social philosophy or political philosophy which values rural society as superior to urban society, the independent farmer as superior to the paid worker, and sees farming as a way of life that can shape the ideal social values. It stresses the superiority of a simpler rural life as opposed to the complexity of city life, with its banks and factories. The American Thomas Jefferson was a representative agrarian who built Jeffersonian Democracy around the notion that farmers are "the most valuable citizens" and the truest republicans.[PARAGRAPH:1]The philosophical roots of agrarianism include European and Chinese philosophers. The Chinese School of Agrarianism was a philosophy that advocated peasant utopian communalism and egalitarianism. This influenced European intellectuals like François Quesnay, an avid Confucianist and advocate of China's agrarian policies, forming the French agrarian philosophy of Physiocracy. The Physiocrats, along with the ideas of John Locke and the Romantic Era, formed the basis of modern European and American agrarianism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Secondly, the term "agrarianism" means political proposals for land redistribution, specifically the distribution of land from the rich to the poor or landless. This terminology is common in many countries, and originated from the "Lex Sempronia Agraria" or "agrarian laws" of Rome in 133 BC, imposed by Tiberius Gracchus, that seized the lands of the rich and distributed them to the poor.This definition of agrarianism is commonly known as "agrarian reform".[PARAGRAPH:1]In societies influenced by Confucianism, the farmer was considered an esteemed productive member of society, whereas merchants who made money were looked down upon. In eighteenth- and nineteenth-century England, the word identified any land reform movement that sought to redistribute cultivated lands equally. Today, the word has largely shed this radical political meaning. Instead, agrarianism points to a collection of political, philosophical, and literary ideas that together tend to describe farm life in ideal terms.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ANIMISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Animism (from Latin anima "soul, life") is a set of beliefs based on the existence of non-human "spiritual beings" or similar kinds of embodied principles.[PARAGRAPH:1]Animism encompasses the beliefs that there is no separation between the spiritual and physical (or material) world, and souls or spirits exist, not only in humans, but also in all other animals, plants, rocks, geographic features such as mountains or rivers, or other entities of the natural environment. Animism may further attribute souls to abstract concepts such as words, true names, or metaphors in mythology. Examples of Animism can be found in forms of Shinto, Serer, Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, Pantheism, Paganism, and Neopaganism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Throughout European history, philosophers such as Aristotle and Thomas Aquinas, among others, contemplated the possibility that souls exist in animals, plants, and people; however, the currently accepted definition of animism was only developed in the 19th century by Sir Edward Tylor, who created it as "one of anthropology's earliest concepts, if not the first".[PARAGRAPH:1]According to the anthropologist Tim Ingold, animism shares similarities to totemism but differs in its focus on individual spirit beings which help to perpetuate life, whereas totemism more typically holds that there is a primary source, such as the land itself or the ancestors, who provide the basis to life. Certain indigenous religious groups such as the Australian Aborigines are more typically totemic, whereas others like the Inuit are more typically animistic in their worldview.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_AUTOCRACY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>An autocracy is a system of government in which a supreme political power is concentrated in the hands of one person, whose decisions are subject to neither external legal restraints nor regularized mechanisms of popular control (except perhaps for the implicit threat of coup d'état or mass insurrection).[PARAGRAPH:1]Autocracy is any form of government in which one person is the supreme power within the state. It is derived from the Greek "auto" ("self") and "kratos" ("rule"), and may be translated as "one who rules by himself". It is distinct from oligarchy ("rule by the few") and democracy ("rule by the people"). Like "despot", "tyrant", "strongman" and "dictator", "autocrat" has become a loaded word with a negative value judgment in contemporary English usage.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term autokrator is employed in antiquity to translate the Latin imperator into Greek. It was the primary word used by grecophones to the Roman Emperor during the later Roman Empire through the seventh century CE and continued to be used in the Byzantine period, although it lost favor to Sebastos ("augustus") and Basileus (obscure: prob. "chieftain;" later "king") as synonyms for "emperor". This use remains current in the modern Greek language, where the term is used for anyone holding the title "emperor," regardless of the actual power of the monarch.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CAPITALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Capitalism is an economic system that is based on private ownership of the means of production and the creation of goods or services for profit. Competitive markets, wage labor, capital accumulation, voluntary exchange, and personal finance are also considered capitalistic. Competitive markets, capital accumulation, voluntary exchange, and personal finance may be parts of capitalism, however in practice there are never pure capitalist economies. Often, other non-capitalist systems such as market socialism and worker cooperatives retain aspects of capitalism. There are multiple variants of capitalism, including laissez-faire and state capitalism. Capitalism is considered to have been applied in a variety of historical cases, varying in time, geography, politics, and culture. There is general agreement that capitalism became dominant in the Western world following the demise of feudalism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Economists, political economists and historians have taken different perspectives on the analysis of capitalism. Economists usually emphasize the degree to which government does not have control over markets (laissez faire), as well as the importance of property rights. Most political economists emphasize private property as well, in addition to power relations, wage labor, class, and the uniqueness of capitalism as a historical formation. The extent to which different markets are free, as well as the rules defining private property, is a matter of politics and policy. Many states have what are termed mixed economies, referring to the varying degree of planned and market-driven elements in a state's economic system. A number of political ideologies have emerged in support of various types of capitalism, the most prominent being economic liberalism.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term capitalism gradually spread throughout the Western world in the 19th and 20th centuries largely through the writings of Karl Marx. However, it is the default economic system and it has its roots tracing back to the beginning of recorded history.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CITY_STATES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A city-state is an independent or autonomous entity whose territory consists of a city which is not administered as a part of another local government. A city-state can also be defined as a central city and its surrounding villages, which together follow the same law, have one form of government, and share languages, religious beliefs, and ways of life. Today, only three independent, sovereign city-states exist: Monaco, Singapore, and the Vatican City.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EGALITARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Egalitarianism (from French égal, meaning "equal") is a trend of thought that favors equality among living entities. Egalitarian doctrines maintain that all humans are equal in fundamental worth or social status, according to The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. The Cultural theory of risk holds egalitarianism as defined by (1) a negative attitude towards rules and principles, and (2) a positive attitude towards group decision-making, with fatalism termed as its opposite. According to the Merriam-Webster Dictionary, the term has two distinct definitions in modern English. It is defined either as a political doctrine that all people should be treated as equals and have the same political, economic, social, and civil rights or as a social philosophy advocating the removal of economic inequalities among people or the decentralization of power. Some sources define egalitarianism as the point of view that equality reflects the natural state of humanity.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_IMPERIALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Kings often challenged the legitimacy of their neighbours to rule certain plots of land. Wars of conquest were common in Europe during the Middle Ages. But under the feudal system, conquest inevitably meant the destruction of the old government as the losing barons were punished. Some states managed to overcome this problem and created great empires.[PARAGRAPH:2]Successful imperialism required leaders to rapidly export systems of law and commerce to their non-national territories, so that anarchy would not prevail. It often took a long time for new subjects to overcome their loyalty to the old king and nation, and instead embrace the winner of war, so patience was a leading virtue of an asiprant emperor.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PANTHEON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>A pantheon (literally "a temple of all gods", "of or common to all gods") is a set of all the gods of a particular polytheistic religion or mythology.[PARAGRAPH:1]Max Weber's 1922 opus, Economy and Society, discusses the link between a pantheon of gods and the development of monotheism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Pantheon can also refer to a temple or sacred building explicitly dedicated to "all deities", avoiding the difficulty of giving an exhaustive list. The most known such structure is the Pantheon of Rome, built in the year 27 BC. The building was dedicated to "all gods" as a gesture embracing the religious syncretism in the increasingly multicultural Roman Empire, with subjects worshipping gods from many cultures and traditions. The building was later renovated for use as a Christian church in 609 under Pope Boniface IV.[PARAGRAPH:1]Since the 16th century "pantheon" also refers in a secular sense to the set of a society's exalted persons. For example "Mick Jagger was exalted into the pantheon of rock megastars".</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_REPUBLIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In a republic, the head of state is not a monarch and there are no legal privileges for the nobility. The exact form of government can vary widely, from absolute despotism to direct democracy, but the most important difference between a republic and any form of monarchy is the much-diminished role of family and lineage in government.[PARAGRAPH:2]Before the French Revolution, a republic in Europe was an aberration. The state enjoyed none of the external security provided by royal family ties. Internally, the succession was decided to some extent by merit, even if this often meant merely that the man with the best ability to take power would do so.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SCHOLASTICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Scholasticism is a method of critical thought which dominated teaching by the academics (scholastics, or schoolmen) of medieval universities in Europe from about 1100–1500, and a program of employing that method in articulating and defending orthodoxy in an increasingly pluralistic context. It originated as an outgrowth of, and a departure from, Christian monastic schools.[PARAGRAPH:1]Not so much a philosophy or a theology as a method of learning, scholasticism places a strong emphasis on dialectical reasoning to extend knowledge by inference, and to resolve contradictions. Scholastic thought is also known for rigorous conceptual analysis and the careful drawing of distinctions. In the classroom and in writing, it often takes the form of explicit disputation: a topic drawn from the tradition is broached in the form of a question, opponents' responses are given, a counterproposal is argued and opponent's arguments rebutted. Because of its emphasis on rigorous dialectical method, scholasticism was eventually applied to many other fields of study.
As a program, scholasticism began as an attempt at harmonization on the part of medieval Christian thinkers: to harmonize the various authorities of their own tradition, and to reconcile Christian theology with classical and late antiquity philosophy, especially that of Aristotle but also of Neoplatonism.[PARAGRAPH:1]The main figures of scholasticism historically are Anselm of Canterbury, Peter Abelard, Alexander of Hales, Albertus Magnus, Duns Scotus, William of Ockham, Bonaventure and Thomas Aquinas. Thomas Aquinas's masterwork, the Summa Theologica, is often seen as the highest fruit of Scholasticism. Important work in the scholastic tradition has been carried on, however, well past Aquinas' time, for instance by Francisco Suárez and Molina, and also among Lutheran and Reformed thinkers.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SECULARISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Secularism is the principle of separation between government institutions and the persons mandated to represent the State from religious institutions and religious dignitaries. In one sense, secularism may assert the right to be free from religious rule and teachings, and the right to freedom from governmental imposition of religion upon the people within a state that is neutral on matters of belief. (See also separation of church and state and Laïcité.) In another sense, it refers to the view that human activities and decisions, especially political ones, should be unbiased by religious influence. Some scholars are now arguing that the very idea of secularism will change.[PARAGRAPH:1]Secularism draws its intellectual roots from Greek and Roman philosophers such as Marcus Aurelius and Epicurus; medieval Muslim polymaths such as Ibn Rushd; Enlightenment thinkers such as Denis Diderot, Voltaire, Baruch Spinoza, John Locke, James Madison, Thomas Jefferson, and Thomas Paine; and more recent freethinkers, agnostics, and atheists such as Robert Ingersoll and Bertrand Russell.[PARAGRAPH:1]The purposes and arguments in support of secularism vary widely. In European laicism, it has been argued that secularism is a movement toward modernization, and away from traditional religious values (also known as secularization). This type of secularism, on a social or philosophical level, has often occurred while maintaining an official state church or other state support of religion. In the United States, some argue that state secularism has served to a greater extent to protect religion and the religious from governmental interference, while secularism on a social level is less prevalent. Within countries as well, differing political movements support secularism for varying reasons.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SELF_SUFFICIENCY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Self-sufficiency is the state of not requiring any aid, support, or interaction, for survival; it is therefore a type of personal or collective autonomy. On a national scale, a totally self-sufficient economy that does not trade with the outside world is called an autarky.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term self-sufficiency is usually applied to varieties of sustainable living in which nothing is consumed outside of what is produced by the self-sufficient individuals. Examples of attempts at self-sufficiency in North America include simple living, homesteading, off-the-grid, survivalism, DIY ethic and the back-to-the-land movement.[PARAGRAPH:1]Practices that enable or aid self-sufficiency include autonomous building, permaculture, sustainable agriculture, and renewable energy.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term is also applied to limited forms of self-sufficiency, for example growing one's own food or becoming economically independent of state subsidies.[PARAGRAPH:1]The entire population of the world was, at one time, self sufficient. They made their own clothing, tools, weapons, boats, huts, and food. They used gathering, hunting, herding and farming to find/hunt/grow their own food. As the human population of he world grew, the wild food supply dwindled. People began to rely on herding and farming more; reling less upon gathering and hunting. In modern times, automated food production on farms makes food. The vast populations now depend on a fewer farmers to make their food for them. Many in developed nations now depend on job salaries to buy food, clothes, and shelter, rather than making these things from raw materials found in the environment. But in a few places in the world, native societies continue to be self sufficient, never having given up their traditional ways of food gathering and food making. Because these native peoples have no jobs and make no salaries, they are often listed as unemployed.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_TOTALITARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Totalitarianism (or totalitarian rule) is a political system where the state recognizes no limits to its authority and strives to regulate every aspect of public and private life wherever feasible. Totalitarian regimes stay in political power through an all-encompassing propaganda campaign, which is disseminated through the state-controlled mass media, a single party that is often marked by political repression, personality cultism, control over the economy, regulation and restriction of speech, mass surveillance, and widespread use of terror. It is not synonymous with dictatorship, as authoritarian regimes also exhibit dictatorial features, but do not create an all-controlling, all-politicised society. Furthermore, non-dictatorial governments and societies are sometimes denounced as having totalitarian features, including democratic socialism, capitalism and liberal democracy.[PARAGRAPH:1]The concept of totalitarianism was first developed in a positive sense in the 1920s by the Italian fascists. The concept became prominent in Western anti-communist political discourse during the Cold War era in order to highlight perceived similarities between Nazi Germany and other fascist regimes on the one hand, and Soviet communism on the other.[PARAGRAPH:1]Aside from fascist and Stalinist movements that are totalitarian, there have been other movements that are totalitarian. The leader of the historic Spanish reactionary conservative movement called the Spanish Confederation of the Autonomous Right declared his intention to "give Spain a true unity, a new spirit, a totalitarian polity..." and went on to say "Democracy is not an end but a means to the conquest of the new state. When the time comes, either parliament submits or we will eliminate it." Baathist Iraq was distinctly ultra-nationalist and totalitarian, and has been dubbed by historian Stanley G. Payne as "the closest" reproduction of the Third Reich. Several revolutionary fundamentalist regimes have been pointed out as totalitarian, including post-revolutionary Iran.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_URBANIZATION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Urbanisation, urbanization or urban drift is the physical growth of urban areas as a result of rural migration and even suburban concentration into cities, particularly the very largest ones. The United Nations projected that half of the world's population would live in urban areas at the end of 2008.[PARAGRAPH:1]It closely linked to modernization, industrialization, and the sociological process of rationalization. Urbanization can describe a specific condition at a set time, i.e. the proportion of total population or area in cities or towns, or the term can describe the increase of this proportion over time. So the term urbanization can represent the level of urban relative to overall population, or it can represent the rate at which the urban proportion is increasing.[PARAGRAPH:1]Urbanization is not merely a modern phenomenon, but a rapid and historic transformation of human social roots on a global scale, whereby predominantly village culture is being rapidly replaced by predominantly urban culture. The last major change in settlement patterns was the accumulation of hunter-gatherers into villages many thousand years ago. Village culture is characterized by common bloodlines, intimate relationships, and communal behavior whereas urban culture is characterized by distant bloodlines, unfamiliar relations, and competitive behavior. This unprecedented movement of people is forecast to continue and intensify in the next few decades, mushrooming cities to sizes incomprehensible only a century ago. Indeed, today, in Asia the urban agglomerations of Dhaka, Karachi, Mumbai, Delhi, Manila, Seoul and Beijing are each already home to over 20 million people, while the Pearl River Delta, Shanghai-Suzhou, Jakarta-Bandung and Tokyo are forecast to approach or exceed 40 million people each within the coming decade.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_LIMITED_UNIT_HAPPINESS</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad per Military Unit Stationed in a City up to a Maximum of %D3</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad par unit&#233; militaire en garnison dans une ville</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad pro in einer Stadt stationierter Milit&#228;reinheit bis zu einem Maximum von %D3</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad per le unit&#224; militari stazionate in citt&#224;</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit %F2_HappyOrSad por cada unidad militar destacada en la ciudad</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EGALITARIANISM_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Unable to Use Slaves[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_UNHAPPY] Penalty for Slaves in Civs without [LINK=literal]Egalitarianism[\LINK]</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>