<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_CHRISTIANITY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Catholicism is one of the three major divisions (Catholicism, Orthodoxy, and Protestantism) within Christianity. Catholicism and Orthodoxy got officially separated after many years of debates and arguments in the Great Schism in 1054[PARAGRAPH:2]Catholicism is a broad term for the body of the Catholic faith, its theologies and doctrines, its liturgical, ethical, spiritual, and behavioral characteristics, as well as a religious people as a whole.[PARAGRAPH:2]For many the term usually refers to Christians and churches belonging to the Roman Catholic Church in full communion with the Holy See. For others it refers to the churches of the first millennium, including, besides the Roman Catholic Church, the Eastern Orthodox Church, the Oriental Orthodox Church, and the Assyrian Church of the East. And for others again it refers to "adhering to the catholic faith as it has been inherited from the earliest Christians ... seeking to restore the faith and order of the primitive church", as claimed by the Anglican Communion and the Reformation and post-Reformation churches.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Catholic claim of continuity is based on, among other factors, Apostolic succession, especially in conjunction with adherence to the Nicene Creed. In the sense of indicating historical continuity of faith and practice, the term "catholicism" is at times employed to mark a contrast to Protestantism, which tends to look solely to the Bible as interpreted on the principles of the 16th-century Protestant Reformation as its ultimate standard.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le catholicisme est une confession du christianisme représentée par l'Église catholique et ses institutions. Les dogmes et les préceptes du catholicisme se fondent sur l'Ancien et le Nouveau Testament. En tant que religion chrétienne, elle se fonde sur la vie et les enseignements de la vie de Jésus-Christ ou Jésus de Nazareth. C'est donc une église eucharistique qui croit en la présence de Jésus-Christ lors de la sainte communion. L'élaboration de cette Église repose sur l'enseignement des Pcres de l'Église et sur les différents conciles scuméniques tels que le concile de Trente (1545-1563), le concile Vatican I (1870) et le concile Vatican II (1962-1965). Pour les catholiques, tant l'écriture que la tradition doivent etre enseignées et vénérées.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'Église catholique se caractérise par la reconnaissance de l'autorité du pape, éveque de Rome et successeur de saint Pierre. Cette branche du christianisme regroupe l'Église catholique occidentale de rite latin et les Églises catholiques orientales.</French>
		<German>{TAB]Katholizismus bezeichnet soziologisch weniger die offizielle Lehre der Römisch-katholischen Kirche sondern das tatsächliche Denken, Empfinden und Handeln katholischer Bevölkerungsteile besonders dort, wo sie die Mehrheit bilden und milieuprägend wirken.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Europa prägt der Katholizismus die Zivilisation vor allem in Ländern, in denen der Protestantismus schwach war, etwa in Italien, Spanien, Portugal und Frankreich, oder im Zuge der Gegenreformation zurückgedrängt wurde. Im deutschsprachigen Raum ist er v.a. im Westen und Süden Deutschlands anzutreffen, aber auch in Österreich. In Irland und Polen steht die nationale Identität dem Katholizismus besonders nahe, da sich dort jeweils eine nationale Opposition auf den überlieferten Katholizismus stützte. Eine große Rolle spielt der Katholizismus darüber hinaus in Lateinamerika.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Begriff bedeutet ursprünglich allumfassend, universell und leitet sich vom Griechischen ab. In diesem Sinne wird er etwa von Aristoteles oder Polybios, aber auch von frühen christlichen Schriftstellern verwendet; so spricht etwa Justin der Märtyrer von der "katholischen Auferstehung". Diese Bedeutung hat sich in der Bezeichnung Katholische Briefe für einige neutestamentliche Bücher erhalten. Die Wortverbindung "Katholische Kirche" wurde erstmals von Ignatius von Antiochien um das Jahr 110 verwendet, um diese von Kleingruppen abzugrenzen.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_ORTHODOXY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Orthodoxy is one of the three major divisions (Catholicism, Orthodoxy, and Protestantism) within Christianity. Catholicism and Orthodoxy got officially separated after many years of debates and arguments in the Great Schism in 1054[PARAGRAPH:2]In classical Christian usage, the term orthodox refers to a set of doctrines which gained prominence in the 4th century AD. The Roman Emperor Constantine I initiated a series of ecumenical councils to try to standardize what was by then, not a necessarily homogeneous religion in terms of theology. The most significant of these early debates was that between the Homoousian doctrine of Athanasius and Eustathius (Trinitarianism) and the Heteroousian doctrine of Arius and Eusebius (Arianism).[PARAGRAPH:2]The Homoousian doctrine gradually won out in the Roman Church and came to be referred to as orthodoxy in most Christian contexts, since this became the viewpoint of the majority (although, of course, many non-Trinitarian Christians still object to this terminology). Following the Great Schism, both the Western and Eastern churches continued to consider themselves uniquely orthodox and catholic. Over time the Western church gradually identified itself more with the "Catholic" label and Westerners gradually associated the "Orthodox" label more with the Eastern church (in some other languages the "Catholic" label is not necessarily identified with the Western church). In addition to the Eastern Orthodox Church, there also exists a separate Oriental Orthodox communion, as well as other smaller communions that are commonly associated with the "Orthodox" label.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Eastern Orthodox Church uses the original form of the Nicene Creed created at the First Council of Constantinople in 381, in contrast to the Roman Catholic church, which uses the Nicene creed with the addition of the phrase 'and the Son' (see Filioque clause). This change is one of many causes for the Great Schism formalized in 1054 by simultaneous proclamations of "Anathema" from the leadership of the Orthodox Churches in the East and the Bishop of Rome (Pope) in the West. This emphasis on the use of the original "creed" is shared today by all Eastern Orthodox Christians.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Orthodox Church is composed of several self-governing ecclesial bodies, each geographically and nationally distinct but theologically unified. Each self-governing (or autocephalous) body, often but not always encompassing a nation, is shepherded by a synod of bishops whose duty, among other things, is to preserve and teach the Apostolic and patristic traditions and related church practices. As in the Roman Catholic Church, Anglican Church, Assyrian Church of the East, Oriental Orthodoxy and some other churches, Orthodox bishops trace their lineage back to the Apostles through the process of Apostolic Succession.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'orthodoxie ou christianisme orthodoxe descend en droite ligne des premicres communautés chrétiennes fondées par les apôtres de Jésus dans les provinces orientales de l'Empire romain et comptant quelque 350 millions de fidcles. Elle est organisée en de nombreuses Églises territoriales (et non nationales) qui forment ensemble l'« Église orthodoxe » ou « Communion orthodoxe » fidcle r la théologie des sept conciles du premier millénaire chrétien et au droit canon qui en découle. Jusqu'au schisme de 1054, les Églises d'Occident (Église catholique comprise) furent elles aussi orthodoxes, c'est-r-dire conformes r la théologie et au droit canon des sept conciles du premier millénaire.[PARAGRAPH:2]Les Églises fidcles aux sept conciles, donc orthodoxes, sont présentes dans l'antique zone de culture grecque, c'est-r-dire dans la zone orientale du bassin de la Méditerranée, Palestine, Liban, Égypte, Turquie, Irak, Syrie, Éthiopie, Arménie, Soudan, voir (Portail:Chrétiens d'Orient) . Ces Églises sont aussi concentrées dans les zones de peuplement slave (Russie, Ukraine, Biélorussie, Bulgarie, Serbie, Monténégro, Macédoine) ainsi qu'en Géorgie, en Roumanie et bien sur en Grcce. Elles sont réparties dans le monde entier au travers de la diaspora des communautés d'origine et par le biais de convertis. Ce groupe d'Églises (ou plutôt : ces Églises en inter-communion) partage une compréhension, un enseignement et des offices suivant le rite de l'Empire romain d'orient 1et se considcrent comme faisant partie d'une seule et meme Église. La Bible et la Liturgie sont lues dans les langues nationales actuelles ou anciennes (araméen, arménien classique, grec ancien, vieux-slave).</French>
		<German>[TAB]Orthodoxie bezeichnet allgemein eine Interpretation einer Lehre, die sich stark an die ursprüngliche Interpretation hält. Anhänger einer Orthodoxie sehen darin eine notwendige Selbstbehauptung des Denkens gegen Beliebigkeit und Willkür; die jeweiligen Kritiker wenden ein, dass eine orthodoxe Interpretation sich flexiblen Weiterentwicklungen und Anpassungen an veränderte religiöse, politische und kulturelle Verhältnisse verweigert.[PARAGRAPH:2]Im Christentum ist "Orthodoxie" ursprünglich der Begriff für das Festhalten an der trinitätstheologischen Entscheidung des 1. Konzils von Nicaea (325) ("homooúsios tô patrí" "mit dem Vater wesenseins") in Abgrenzung von den Arianern. Sodann wird damit das Bekenntnis zum christologischen Dogma des Konzils von Chalkedon (451) bezeichnet. Erst in nachreformatorischer Zeit ist damit das Beharren auf bestimmten traditionellen Lehrmeinungen, Ideologien oder Handlungsweisen gemeint, im Gegensatz zu Erneuerungsbewegungen.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_JUDAISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Protestantism is one of the three major divisions (Catholicism, Orthodoxy, and Protestantism) within Christianity. It is a movement that began in northern Europe in the early 16th century as a reaction against medieval Roman Catholic doctrines and practices.[PARAGRAPH:2]The doctrines of the various Protestant denominations and non-denominations vary, but most non-denominational doctrines include justification by grace through faith and not through works, known as Sola Fide, the priesthood of all believers, and the Bible as the ultimate authority in matters of faith and order, known as Sola Scriptura, which is Latin for 'by scripture alone'.[PARAGRAPH:2]In the 16th century the followers of Martin Luther established the evangelical churches of Germany and Scandinavia. Reformed churches in Switzerland were established by John Calvin and more radical reformers such as Huldrych Zwingli. Thomas Cranmer reformed the Church of England and later John Knox established a more radical Calvinist communion in the Church of Scotland.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le protestantisme ou le christianisme protestant regroupe l'ensemble des courants religieux chrétiens sortis du catholicisme qui ont pris naissance en Europe lors de la Réforme sous l'impulsion de théologiens tels que Martin Luther, Jean Calvin, Jan Hus, Ulrich Zwingli et bien d'autres.[PARAGRAPH:2]On compte vingt-six unions d'églises au sein de la seule fédération protestante de France.1 Le terme protestant est utilisé pour la premicre fois en 1529, quand les seigneurs et les villes qui suivaient la doctrine de Martin Luther se sont déclarés contre les décisions prises par la dicte impériale r Spire r majorité catholique.[PARAGRAPH:2]Les protestants français, d'abord appelés « luthériens » au début par leurs adversaires, seront ensuite nommés par dérision « huguenots », puis « religionnaires ». Il s'agit de l'abréviation de « ceux de la Religion prétendue réformée », appellation officielle du protestantisme dans les actes royaux.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Mit dem ursprünglich politischen Begriff Protestanten werden im engeren Sinne die Angehörigen der christlichen Konfessionen bezeichnet, die, ausgehend von Deutschland und der Schweiz, vor allem in Mittel- und Nordeuropa durch die Reformation des 16. Jahrhunderts entstanden sind.[PARAGRAPH:2]Allgemeiner werden auch nachreformatorisch entstandene Konfessionsrichtungen als protestantisch bezeichnet, die gleiche oder ähnliche Grundsätze wie die reformatorischen Kirchen vertreten und sich deshalb von der römisch-katholischen Kirche distanzierten. In diesem Sinne wird beispielsweise die Anglikanische Kirche zum Protestantismus gezählt. Nach der Unabhängigkeitserklärung nannten sich die amerikanischen Anglikaner Protestant Episcopal Church in the United States of America. Auch die evangelischen Freikirchen gehören zum Protestantismus und sehen sich ebenso als "Erben der Reformation". Dazu zählen in Deutschland zum Beispiel die Baptisten, die Methodisten, die Mennoniten, die Siebenten-Tags-Adventisten und die Pfingstler. Presbyterianer, Kongregationalisten und eine Anzahl anderer Kirchen vor allem in den Vereinigten Staaten gehören zur reformierten Kirchengemeinschaft. Die Quäker entstanden ebenfalls im Umkreis der englischen Reformation.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die deutschen protestantischen (bevorzugter Name: evangelischen) Landeskirchen haben sich in der Evangelischen Kirche in Deutschland (EKD) organisiert. Die protestantischen Freikirchen sind in der Vereinigung Evangelischer Freikirchen zusammengefasst. Durch Auswanderung und Mission entstanden in vielen Ländern der Erde größere oder kleinere protestantische Kirchen (Weltprotestantismus). Besonders stark wachsen sie in China und Lateinamerika. Die meisten lutherischen Kirchen sind im Lutherischen Weltbund zusammengeschlossen, die reformierten Kirchen in der Weltgemeinschaft Reformierter Kirchen. Auch die evangelischen Freikirchen kennen entsprechende internationale Zusammenschlüsse. Die große Mehrzahl der protestantischen Kirchen sind Mitglieder des Ökumenischen Rates der Kirchen. Protestanten bilden die Bevölkerungsmehrheit in Skandinavien, Großbritannien, den Vereinigten Staaten, Kanada, Australien und Neuseeland. In Deutschland, den Niederlanden und der Schweiz leben etwa gleich viele evangelische wie katholische Christen.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_ZOROASTRIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Zoroastrianism or Mazdaism is known as one of the world's oldest monotheistic religions. It was once the official religion of Sassanid Persia and played an important role in Achaemenid times.  The prophet Zarathushtra, commonly known in the West as Zoroaster, lived in Persia no earlier than 1700 BCE and no later than 600 BCE, although Plato believed that Zoroaster lived some 6000 years previous to himself. Zoroastrianism is uniquely important in the history of religion because of its formative links to both Western Abrahamic and Eastern Dharmic religious traditions.  Zoroaster's writings suggest a metaphysical dualism, but devotional monotheism, requiring adherence to Ahura Mazda. Many modern scholars believe that Zoroastrianism had a large influence on Judaism, Mithraism, Manichaeism, and Christianity because of Persia's connections to the Roman Empire and because of its earlier control over Israel under rulers such as Cyrus II the Great, Darius the Great and Xerxes I.  [PARAGRAPH:2]When the Sassanid dynasty came into power in Iran in 228 CE, they aggressively promoted their Zoroastrian religion. During periods when the Sassanids captured provinces held by the Romans, they often built fire temples there. During periods of Sassanid suzernity over Armenia, the Persians made attempts to promote the religion there as well.  By the 6th century, Zoroastrianism had spread to northern China via the Silk Road, gaining official status in a number of Chinese states. Zoroastrian temples still remained in Kaifeng and Zhenjiang as late as the 1130s, but by the 13th century the religion had faded from prominence in China.  [PARAGRAPH:2]In the 7th century, the Sassanid dynasty was conquered by Muslim Arabs. Zoroastrianism, which was once dominant in a region stretching from Anatolia to Persian Gulf and Central Asia, did not have a powerful foreign champion as Christianity did in the Byzantine Empire, and so steadily lost influence and adherents in Iran under Muslim rule.  Iranian Zoroastrians fled to India in large numbers, where they were offered refuge on condition that they abstain from missionary activities and marry only in their community. Although these strictures are centuries old, Parsis of the 21st century still do not accept converts and are endogamous.   Zoroastrians in Iran are still persecuted by that nation's theocratic rulers, but even today one can find Zoroastrian communities living and practicing their faith there, such as in the province of Yazd, Kerman and Tehran</English>
		<French>[TAB]Zoroastrianisme ou Mazdaisme est connu comme l'une des plus ancienne religion monotheiste du monde. Ce fut la religion officiel de Sassanid des Perses et elle joua un role important a son &#233;poque. Le prophete Zarathushtra, plus connu comme Zoroaster, vecu en Perse entre 1700 av-jc et 600 av-jc (fourchette estim&#233; pendant laquelle il a du naitre) et aurait vecu 6000 ans avant Platon.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Zoroastrismus bzw. Zarathustrismus (auch: Mazdaismus oder Parsismus) ist eine um 1800 v. Chr.-700 v. Chr. vermutlich in Baktrien entstandene, monotheistische bzw. (zumindest in ihren frühen Ausprägungen) dualistische Religion, mit etwa 120.000-150.000 Anhängern, die ursprünglich im iranischen Raum verbreitet war. Die Anhänger des Zoroastrismus werden Zoroastrier oder Zarathustrier genannt, die Anhängerschaft im heutigen Indien bezeichnet man auch als Parsen.
Der Begründer des Zarathustrismus war Zarathustra (griech. Zoroaster), über dessen Datierung in der Forschung bis heute Uneinigkeit herrscht. Im Zentrum des auf ihn zurückgeführten Glaubens, der aber auf ältere iranische Kulte zurück geht, steht der Schöpfergott Ahura Mazda (daher manchmal auch "Mazdaismus"). Er wird begleitet von unsterblichen Heiligen (Amesha Spenta) sowie von seinem Widersacher, dem bösen Dämon Anramainyu( Angro-Maina) (Ahriman).
Obwohl die Zoroastrier mehrere Gottheiten (z. B. Anahita oder Mithra) kennen, ist die Religion grundsätzlich vom Dualismus zwischen Ahura Mazda und Ahriman geprägt: "Und im Anbeginn waren diese beiden Geister, die Zwillinge, die nach ihrem eigenen Worte das Gute und das Böse im Denken, Reden und Tun heißen. Zwischen ihnen haben die Guthandelnden richtig gewählt." In der Spätantike war unter den Sassaniden die zurvanistische Variante des Zoroastrismus weit verbreitet, in der der gute und der böse Geist als die Kinder der "unendlichen Zeit" (Zurvan/Zervan) galten.
Der Zoroastrismus ist eine Schriftreligion und basiert auf der heiligen Schrift Avesta. Gottesbilder sind dem Zoroastrismus fremd. Er kennt allerdings Feuertempel.</German>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>