<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Soren Johnson (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- Game Text Objects -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_THAILAND_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Thais</English>
		<German>Die Thais</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_THAILAND_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Thailand</English>
		<German>Thailand</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_THAILAND_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Thai</English>
		<German>Thai</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MUGHALS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Mughals</English>
		<German>Die Moguln</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MUGHALS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mughals</English>
		<German>Moguln</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MUGHALS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Mughal</English>
		<German>Mogul</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDONESIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Indonesians</English>
		<French>The Indonesians</French>
		<German>Die Indonesier</German>
		<Italian>The Indonesians</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Indonesians</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDONESIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Indonesia</English>
		<French>Indonesia</French>
		<German>Indonesien</German>
		<Italian>Indonesia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Indonesia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDONESIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Indonesian</English>
		<French>Indonesian</French>
		<German>Indonesisch</German>
		<Italian>Indonesian</Italian>
		<Spanish>Indonesian</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_INDONESIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Indonesian archipelago was reached by the Modern Man in 45.000 BC. A migration from Southeast asia around 2000 BC brought many new techniques, and in the 8th century BC, the Indonesian people mastered bronze casting, wet-field rice cultivation, megalithik practises and much more. This allowed villages, towns and small kingdoms to flourish by the 1st century AD. With the introduction of Buddhism and Hinduism came great monuments, and both the Saleindra and Medang kingdoms built large Hindu and Buddhist stupas commonly called Candis, including the large Borobudut and Prambanan. In the 7th century however, this small kingdom society were soon to come to an end with the rise of Sri Vijaya.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]Sri Vijaya was a Malay kingdom formed on the island of Sumatra that flourished on its trade and naval power. While not a state in modern sense, it was rather a confederacy form of society centered on the royal heartland and trading centre of Palembang. Especially the trade trought the Starit of Malacca gained the country financial advantages, and by the end of the 7th century Sri Vijaya controlled numerous trade cities along both sides of the strait. Controlling both the Malacca and Sunda straits, they lived on as a formidable economy and naval power well into the 13th century, and their reign saw the height of the Buddhist influence in Indonesia.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]The decline of Sri Vijaya in the 13th century left many of the Islands with regional kingdoms, and when the kingdom of Singhasari emerged on Java, Kublai Khan sent emmisaries to demand tribute. The Majapahit kingdom, an original ally of Singhasari and also based on Java, allied with the mongols and defeated the Singhasari, but then turned against them and forced the mongol forces to withdraw in confusion. This marked the beginning of the second large Indonesian empire, the Majapahit. Majapahit reached its peak under Hayam Wuruk and his prime minister and commander Gajah Mada, and just a few years after Gajah Madas death, Hayam Wuruk conquered Palembang and ended Sri Vijaya rule in Indonesia. Although the Majapahit rulers extended their power over other islands and destroyed neighbouring kingdoms, their focus seems to have been on controlling and gaining a larger share of the commercial trade that passed through the archipelago. About the time Majapahit was founded, Muslim traders and proselytisers  began entering the area.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]After Majahapits peak in the 14th century, Majapahit power began to decline and was unable to control the rising power of the Sultanate of Malacca. With an increased percantage of the population converting to Islam, the islands saw mostly muslim rule for the next centuries, with numerous different sultanates controlling the Islands.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]In the 16th century, sucsessful european invasions put the Sultanates to an end, with the Portuguese, Spanish, Dutch and British seeking to dominate the Spice trade from India and the 'Spice Islands' of Indonesia. In the early 16 century, the Portuguese manged to control the trade, but in 1602 the Dutch parliament awarded the Dutch East-India Company with a monoploy on all trade and colonial activities in Indonesia at a time before the company controlled any territory in there. In the early 20th century, the monopoly was compleated and the boundaries of modern Indonesia was created. It was also in this period that the first Indoneasian national movement started, basing their idea of one Indonesian nation on Sri Vijaya and Majapahit.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]During World War II, Japan extended their Pacific empire to far away lands, including Indonesia. With the Dutch losing control of the archipelago, Indonesia decleared independance 2 days after Japans defeat and the and of the war. This marked the beginning if modern day Indonesia, and the first president, Sukarno, was elected. He introduced a form of democracy he called the 'Old Order', claiming that western democracy would not work in Indonesia. Although his methods worked in the beginning, he relied more and more on support from the Indonesian communist party, the PKI, which was the largest communist party outside of China and Soviet. With the party gaining more and more power, the militarya and the islamic groups, the other two major powers in Indonesia, got worried, and with the army did everything they could to weaken Sukarno. In March 1967, Sukarno were forced to abdicate and the Provisional People's Consultative Assembly named the army general Suharto as Acting President.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]Suharto brought many changes with him during his "New Order", which he named his goverment to differ it from Sukartos "Old Order", and early in his reign he invaded Papua after negotiations with the Dutch about the territory faied. The invasion was however easily repelled, and Suharto then gave them the "Act of Free Choice". After learning the Papuan representaions Indonesia, they were threatened and bribed to vote in Indonesias favor, and the transfer were confirmed by a UN General Assembly meeting. During his period he also transmigrated peole from the overpopluated areas to the more underpopulated islands, stating that this was for the good of the economy and industry and to give the poor a chance and he annexed the earlier Portuguese region East-Timor. During his reign Indonesia also became of OPEC, short for Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, due to large amounts of oil found in the area, something that helped Indonesias wealth, even when corruption was pretty usual during his reign.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]Within a few years, however, many of its original allies had become indifferent or averse to the New Order, which comprised a military faction supported by a narrow civilian group. Among much of the pro-democracy movement which forced Suharto to resign in the Indonesian 1998 Revolution and then gained power, the term "New Order" has come to be used pejoratively.[PARAGRAPH:2:1]Indonesia today is a country with much history. It granted independence to East-Timor in 2002, and its economy is growing. In 2004 a massive earthquake and tsunami devasted parts of Northern Sumatra, particulary the Aceh region. The same year Susilo Bambang won the first direct presidental election, and he was re-elected in 2009 to a second term. This shows that Indoneasia is on its way into a stable and democratic country, and the possiblity for them raising again as a power in Southeast Asia is still there.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<French>INSERT</French>
		<German>INSERT</German>
		<Italian>INSERT</Italian>
		<Spanish>INSERT</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<!-- Leaders -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HAYAM_WURUK</Tag>
		<English>Hayam Wuruk</English>
		<French>Hayam Wuruk</French>
		<German>Hayam Wuruk</German>
		<Italian>Hayam Wuruk</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hayam Wuruk</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HAYAM_WURUK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Hayam Wuruk[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Majapahit[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1334 to 1389 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Born as the fourth monarch of Majapahit, he is credited as a bright, talendted, handsome and exceptional in the courtly martial arts. He was educeted with the purpose of being the next Majapahit king and his reign marked the peak of Majapahit glory.[PARAGRAPH:1]When Rajapatni, Hayams grandmother, died in 1350, Tribhuwana, Hayams mum and queen of Majapahit, had to descend from the throne because she ruled Majapahit under Rajapatni's auspices, and she must relinquish her throne to her son. He inherited the throne at an age of 16, at the same time as his Prime Minister, Gajah Mada, was at the height of his career. With the help of Gajah Mada, Hayam extended his rule all trough the Indonesian archipelago.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1357, Hayam was to marry the princess of the Sunda kingdom. The reasons of this royal engagement was probably a political one, to foster alliance between Majapahit and the Sundanese Kingdom. However in the Bubat incident, the Sunda royal family and their guards was involved in skirmish with Majapahit troops. The planned royal wedding ended in disaster with the death of the princess and the whole of Sunda royal party. The court officials blamed Gajah Mada, because it was his intention to demand submission from Sunda Kingdom that ended in bloodshed.[PARAGRAPH:1]Several years later, Hayam wed his cousin, Sori, and they had a daughter who later married to a relative, Wikramawardhana, who then became the Crown Prince. However Hayam also had a son, Wirabhumi, with the royal concubine, and after Hayams death in 1389, Wirabhumi tried to seize the throne from Wikramawardhana. Although Wikramawardhana crushed the rebellion in the end, is severly weakeden Majapahit and this can be seen as the start of its decline.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<French>INSERT</French>
		<German>INSERT</German>
		<Italian>INSERT</Italian>
		<Spanish>INSERT</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SUHARTO</Tag>
		<English>Suharto</English>
		<French>Suharto</French>
		<German>Suharto</German>
		<Italian>Suharto</Italian>
		<Spanish>Suharto</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SUHARTO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Haji Mohammed Suharto[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Indonesia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1921 - 2008 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Haji Mohammad Soeharto, more commonly referred to as simply Soeharto (General Suharto in the English-speaking world), is a former Indonesian military and political leader. He served as a military officer in the Indonesian National Revolution, but is better known as the long-reigning second President of Indonesia, holding the office from 1967 to 1998.[PARAGRAPH:1]Suharto seized power from his predecessor, the first president of Indonesia Sukarno, through a mixture of force and political maneuvering against the backdrop of foreign and domestic unrest. Over the three decades of his "New Order" regime, Suharto constructed a strong central government along militarist lines. An ability to maintain stability and an avowedly anti-Communist stance won him the economic and diplomatic patronage of several Western governments in the era of the Cold War. For almost all of his three-decade rule, Indonesia experienced rapid industrialization and economic growth.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Suharto regime had won the favour of Western governments and institutions, however, in 1990's, its increasingly authoritarian and corrupt practices became a source of much discontent. After the 1990s brought end of the Cold War, Western concern over communism waned, and Suharto's human rights record came under greater international scrutiny. In 1991, the murder of East Timorese civilians in a Dili cemetery, also known as the "Santa Cruz Massacre", caused American attention to focus on its military relations with the Suharto regime and the question of Indonesia's occupation of East Timor. In 1992,this attention resulted in the Congress of the United States passing limitations on IMET assistance to the Indonesian military, over the objections of President George H.W. Bush. In 1993, under President Bill Clinton, the U.S. delegation to the UN Human Rights Commission helped pass a resolution expressing deep concern over Indonesian human rights violations in East Timor. The Indonesian invasion and occupation of East Timor has been called the worst instance of genocide (relative to population) since the Holocaust.[PARAGRAPH:1]His almost unquestioned authority over Indonesian affairs slipped dramatically when the Asian financial crisis lowered Indonesians' standard of living and fractured his support among the nation's military, political and civil society institutions. After internal unrest and diplomatic isolation sapped his support in the mid-to-late 1990s, Suharto was forced to resign from the presidency in May 1998.[PARAGRAPH:1]After serving as the public face of Indonesia for over 30 years, Suharto then lived his post-presidential years in virtual seclusion. His legacy remains hotly debated and contested both in Indonesia and in foreign-policy debates in the West. Since his resignation, Suharto retired to a family compound in Central Jakarta, making few public appearances. Efforts to prosecute Suharto have mostly centered around alleged mismanagement of funds, and their force has been blunted due to health concerns. In january 2008, Suharto was taken to the Pertamina hospital, Jakarta, with complications arising from a weak heart, swelling of limbs and stomach, and partial renal failure. He died there at 27th of January at 1:10 pm.</English>
		<French>INSERT</French>
		<German>INSERT</German>
		<Italian>INSERT</Italian>
		<Spanish>INSERT</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DHARMASETU</Tag>
		<English>Dharmasetu</English>
		<French>Dharmasetu</French>
		<German>Dharmasetu</German>
		<Italian>Dharmasetu</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dharmasetu</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DHARMASETU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Dharmasetu[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Maharaja of Sri Vijaya[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 8th century AD [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB][PARAGRAPH:1]Dharmasetu was an 8th century Maharaja (high king) of Sri Vijaya. While we know little about him, he is commonly referred to as one of, if not the, greatest of the Sri Vijaya monarchs.[PARAGRAPH:1]During Dharmasetus reign, trade gradually started to relocate to cities in Indochina and away from the Sri Vijaya heartland. He solved this problem by sending raids over there and for a while Indrapura was actually controlled from Palembang (the Sri Vijaya capital). He also successfully incorporated Pan Pan, a kingdom located in the north of the Malay Peninsula into Srivijayan sphere of influence before 775 AD. A stele in Thailand also states that he constructed three sanctuaries dedicated to Bodhisattvas Padmapani, Vajrapani and Buddha in Ligor.[PARAGRAPH:1]He is also noted as head of the Saleindra, and this is the first instance of relationship known existed between Srivijaya and the Sailendra. Yet, he was the son of Jayanasa of Srivijaya and a princess from Tarumanagara. Dewi Tara, the daughter of Dharmasetu later married a member of the Sailendra family by the name of Samaratunga whom later would assumed throne of Srivijaya around 792. The relationship between Srivijaya and the Sailendra became intimately close afterwards.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
		<French>INSERT</French>
		<German>INSERT</German>
		<Italian>INSERT</Italian>
		<Spanish>INSERT</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<!-- UU and UB -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INDONESIAN_CANDI</Tag>
		<English>Candi</English>
		<French>Candi</French>
		<German>Candi</German>
		<Italian>Candi</Italian>
		<Spanish>Candi</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INDONESIAN_CANDI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Candis were Hindu and Buddhist temples built in Indonesia mostly between the 8th and 15th century AD. The term "candi" itself derived from Candika, one of the manifestation of the goddess Durga as the goddess of death. This suggested in ancient Indonesia the "candi" has mortuary function as well as attributed with the afterlife. The association of the name "candi", candika or durga with Hindu-Buddhist temples is unknown in India and other of Indonesia's Southeast Asian neighbours such as Cambodia, Thailand, or Burma. The historians suggested that temples of ancient Java also used to store the ashes of cremated deceased kings or royalties. This is also in-line with buddhist concept of stupa  as the structure to store buddhist relicts including the ashes and remnants of holy buddhist priest or the buddhist king, the patron of buddhism. The statue of god stored inside the garbhagriha (main chamber) of the temple often modelled after the deceased king and considered as deified self of the king portrayed as Vishnu or Shiva. The example is the statue of king Airlangga from Belahan temple portrayed as Vishnu riding Garuda.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some of the more famous Candis are Borobudur, a Mahayana Buddhist monument in Central Java and the large Prambanan, dedicated to the Hindu god Trimurti, both built in the 9th century.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Candis were Hindu and Buddhist temples built in Indonesia mostly between the 8th and 15th century AD. The term "candi" itself derived from Candika, one of the manifestation of the goddess Durga as the goddess of death. This suggested in ancient Indonesia the "candi" has mortuary function as well as attributed with the afterlife. The association of the name "candi", candika or durga with Hindu-Buddhist temples is unknown in India and other of Indonesia's Southeast Asian neighbours such as Cambodia, Thailand, or Burma. The historians suggested that temples of ancient Java also used to store the ashes of cremated deceased kings or royalties. This is also in-line with buddhist concept of stupa  as the structure to store buddhist relicts including the ashes and remnants of holy buddhist priest or the buddhist king, the patron of buddhism. The statue of god stored inside the garbhagriha (main chamber) of the temple often modelled after the deceased king and considered as deified self of the king portrayed as Vishnu or Shiva. The example is the statue of king Airlangga from Belahan temple portrayed as Vishnu riding Garuda.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some of the more famous Candis are Borobudur, a Mahayana Buddhist monument in Central Java and the large Prambanan, dedicated to the Hindu god Trimurti, both built in the 9th century.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Candis were Hindu and Buddhist temples built in Indonesia mostly between the 8th and 15th century AD. The term "candi" itself derived from Candika, one of the manifestation of the goddess Durga as the goddess of death. This suggested in ancient Indonesia the "candi" has mortuary function as well as attributed with the afterlife. The association of the name "candi", candika or durga with Hindu-Buddhist temples is unknown in India and other of Indonesia's Southeast Asian neighbours such as Cambodia, Thailand, or Burma. The historians suggested that temples of ancient Java also used to store the ashes of cremated deceased kings or royalties. This is also in-line with buddhist concept of stupa  as the structure to store buddhist relicts including the ashes and remnants of holy buddhist priest or the buddhist king, the patron of buddhism. The statue of god stored inside the garbhagriha (main chamber) of the temple often modelled after the deceased king and considered as deified self of the king portrayed as Vishnu or Shiva. The example is the statue of king Airlangga from Belahan temple portrayed as Vishnu riding Garuda.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some of the more famous Candis are Borobudur, a Mahayana Buddhist monument in Central Java and the large Prambanan, dedicated to the Hindu god Trimurti, both built in the 9th century.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Candis were Hindu and Buddhist temples built in Indonesia mostly between the 8th and 15th century AD. The term "candi" itself derived from Candika, one of the manifestation of the goddess Durga as the goddess of death. This suggested in ancient Indonesia the "candi" has mortuary function as well as attributed with the afterlife. The association of the name "candi", candika or durga with Hindu-Buddhist temples is unknown in India and other of Indonesia's Southeast Asian neighbours such as Cambodia, Thailand, or Burma. The historians suggested that temples of ancient Java also used to store the ashes of cremated deceased kings or royalties. This is also in-line with buddhist concept of stupa  as the structure to store buddhist relicts including the ashes and remnants of holy buddhist priest or the buddhist king, the patron of buddhism. The statue of god stored inside the garbhagriha (main chamber) of the temple often modelled after the deceased king and considered as deified self of the king portrayed as Vishnu or Shiva. The example is the statue of king Airlangga from Belahan temple portrayed as Vishnu riding Garuda.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some of the more famous Candis are Borobudur, a Mahayana Buddhist monument in Central Java and the large Prambanan, dedicated to the Hindu god Trimurti, both built in the 9th century.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Candis were Hindu and Buddhist temples built in Indonesia mostly between the 8th and 15th century AD. The term "candi" itself derived from Candika, one of the manifestation of the goddess Durga as the goddess of death. This suggested in ancient Indonesia the "candi" has mortuary function as well as attributed with the afterlife. The association of the name "candi", candika or durga with Hindu-Buddhist temples is unknown in India and other of Indonesia's Southeast Asian neighbours such as Cambodia, Thailand, or Burma. The historians suggested that temples of ancient Java also used to store the ashes of cremated deceased kings or royalties. This is also in-line with buddhist concept of stupa  as the structure to store buddhist relicts including the ashes and remnants of holy buddhist priest or the buddhist king, the patron of buddhism. The statue of god stored inside the garbhagriha (main chamber) of the temple often modelled after the deceased king and considered as deified self of the king portrayed as Vishnu or Shiva. The example is the statue of king Airlangga from Belahan temple portrayed as Vishnu riding Garuda.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some of the more famous Candis are Borobudur, a Mahayana Buddhist monument in Central Java and the large Prambanan, dedicated to the Hindu god Trimurti, both built in the 9th century.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INDONESIAN_CANDI_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Candi[COLOR_REVERT], which replaces the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Theatre[COLOR_REVERT], provides the Indonesians with +1 happiness as well as giving them a reliable culture-boost.</English>
		<French>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Candi[COLOR_REVERT], which replaces the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Theatre[COLOR_REVERT], provides the Indonesians with +1 happiness as well as giving them a reliable culture-boost.</French>
		<German>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Candi[COLOR_REVERT], which replaces the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Theatre[COLOR_REVERT], provides the Indonesians with +1 happiness as well as giving them a reliable culture-boost.</German>
		<Italian>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Candi[COLOR_REVERT], which replaces the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Theatre[COLOR_REVERT], provides the Indonesians with +1 happiness as well as giving them a reliable culture-boost.</Italian>
		<Spanish>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Candi[COLOR_REVERT], which replaces the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Theatre[COLOR_REVERT], provides the Indonesians with +1 happiness as well as giving them a reliable culture-boost.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_INDONESIAN_ORANG_LAUT</Tag>
		<English>Orang Laut</English>
		<French>Orang Laut</French>
		<German>Orang Laut</German>
		<Italian>Orang Laut</Italian>
		<Spanish>Orang Laut</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_IRAN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Iranians</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Les Perses</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Perser:Die Perser:den Persern</Text>
			<Gender>Male:Male:Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1:1:1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>I Persiani</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Los Persas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KONGO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Kingdom of Kongo was a former state in western Central Africa, founded in the 14th century. In the 15th century the kingdom stretched from the Congo River in the north to the Loje River in the south and from the Atlantic Ocean in the west to beyond the Kwango River in the east. Several smaller autonomous states to the south and east paid tribute to it. Kongo was ruled by the manikongo, or king, and was divided into six provinces, each administered by a governor appointed by the manikongo.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1482, Diogo Cão, a Portuguese explorer, visited the kingdom, and the reigning manikongo, Nzinga Nkuwu, was favorably impressed with Portuguese culture. In 1491, Portuguese missionaries, soldiers, and artisans were welcomed at Mbanza-Kongo, the capital of the kingdom. The missionaries soon gained converts, including Nzinga Nkuwu (who took the name João I), and the soldiers helped the manikongo defeat an internal rebellion.[PARAGRAPH:1]The next manikongo, Afonso I (reigned 1505–43), was raised as a Christian and attempted to convert the kingdom to Christianity and European ways. However, the Portuguese residents in Kongo were primarily interested in increasing their private fortunes (especially through capturing Africans and selling them into slavery), and, despite the attempts of King Manuel I of Portugal to channel the efforts of his subjects into constructive projects, the continued rapaciousness of the Portuguese played a major part in weakening the kingdom and reducing the hold of the capital over the provinces.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the death of Afonso, Kongo declined rapidly and suffered major civil wars. The Portuguese shifted their interest southward to the kingdom of Ndongo and helped Ndongo defeat Kongo in 1556. However, in 1569 the Portuguese aided Kongo by helping to repel an invasion from the east by a Lunda ethnic group. The slave trade, which undermined the social structure of Kongo, continued to weaken the authority of the manikongo.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1641, Manikongo Garcia II allied himself with the Dutch in an attempt to control Portuguese slave traders, but in 1665 a Portuguese force decisively defeated the army of Kongo and from that time onward the manikongo was little more than a vassal of Portugal. The kingdom disintegrated into a number of small states, all controlled to varying degrees by the Portuguese. The area of Kongo was incorporated mostly into Portuguese Angola and partly into the Kongo Free State (under control of Belgium). Today the territory is made up by Northern Angola, the western part of the Democratic Republic of Congo (Congo-Kinshasa, former Zaire) and southern Republic of the Congo (Congo-Brazzaville).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HARAPPANS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The earliest traces of civilization in the Indian subcontinent can be found along the Indus River. The first excavations of this Indus Valley Civilization, or Harappan Civilization, were conducted in 1921 in the ancient cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro. Both of these sites show examples of a highly sophisticated civilization that first developed some 4,500 - 5,000 years ago. The Indus Valley people were most likely Dravidians, who may have been pushed down into southern India when the Aryans, with their more advanced military technology, commenced their migrations to India around 2,000 BC. Though the Indus Valley script has yet to be deciphered, the numerous seals, statuary, potter, and cities of the Indus Valley have enabled scholars to construct a realistic account of the Indus Valley Civilization. [PARAGRAPH: 1] A centralized state and extensive town planning is suggested by the layout of the great cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro. The same kind of burnt brick appears to have been used in many cities that were hundreds of miles apart. The weights and measures show a substantial regularity. The Indus Valley people domesticated animals and harvested various crops, such as cotton, sesame, peas, and barley. They may also have been seafaring people, as Indus Valley seals have been found in places such as Sumer. However, the Indus Valley Civilization appears to have been extensively urban, challenging the former idea of India as an agricultural civilization. The Indus Valley people had a merchant class that, as data suggests, engaged in widespread trading. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Neither Harappa nor Mohenjo-Daro show any evidence of fire altars, and as a result one can reasonably surmise that the various rituals around the fire which are important in Hinduism were brought in by the Aryans. The Indus Valley people do not appear to have been in ownership of horses, as Harappan seals and terracotta do not show any evidence of horses. Other than the excavated ruins of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro, these seals provide the most detailed hints on the personality and culture of the Indus Valley people. Bulls and elephants do appear on the seals, yet the horned bulls still cannot be associated with Shiva's bull in Hinduism. The revered cow of Hinduism also does not appear on the Harappan seals. The women portrayed on the seals wear elaborate clothing in heavy jewelry. This suggests that the Indus Valley people were sophisticated people with cultured tastes in an advanced artistic feeling. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The Indus Valley civilization raises many unresolved questions. Why did this civilization, considering its sophistication, not spread beyond the Indus Valley? The area where the Indus Valley Civilization developed is arid, and one can surmise that urban development took place along a river that flowed through a virtual desert. There are also question about the disappearance of the Indus Valley cities. In the Rig Veda there is mention of a Vedic war god, Indra, destroying some forts and citadels, which could have included Harappa and other Indus Valley cities. However, most of the evidence concerning the cities' disappearance is based on the arrival of the Aryans in India.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les plus anciennes traces de civilisation dans le sous-continent indien se trouvent le long du fleuve Indus. Les premières fouilles de cette civilisation de la vallée de l'Indus, ou Harappan Civilization, ont été réalisées en 1921 dans les anciennes cités d'Harappa et Mohenjo-Daro. Ces deux sites montrent des exemples d'une civilisation hautement sophistiqués que d'abord développé quelques 4500 - il ya 5000 ans. La vallée de l'Indus personnes étaient plus susceptibles Dravidians, qui peut avoir été déplacée vers le bas dans le sud de l'Inde lorsque les Aryens, avec leurs technologies militaires les plus avancés, ont commencé leur migration vers l'Inde autour de 2000 av. Bien que la vallée de l'Indus script doit encore être déchiffrés, les nombreux phoques, statuaire, potier, et les villes de la vallée de l'Indus ont permis aux chercheurs de construire un réaliste compte de la civilisation de l'Indus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Un État centralisé, et une vaste urbanisme, est suggérée par la présentation des grandes villes d'Harappa et Mohenjo-Daro. Le même type de brique brûlée semble avoir été utilisée dans plusieurs villes qui ont des centaines de kilomètres de distance. Les poids et les mesures montrent une régularité. La vallée de l'Indus personnes animaux domestiqués et récolté diverses cultures telles que le coton, le sésame, les pois, et de l'orge. Ils peuvent aussi avoir été marin peuple, comme la vallée de l'Indus phoques ont été retrouvés dans des endroits comme Sumer. Cependant, la civilisation de l'Indus semble avoir été largement urbaine, contestant l'idée ancienne de l'Inde en tant que civilisation agricole. La vallée de l'Indus gens avaient une classe de marchands qui, comme le suggèrent les données, engagés dans la négociation généralisée. [PARAGRAPH 1] Ni Harappa ni Mohenjo-Daro montrent aucun signe d'incendie autels, et en conséquence, on peut raisonnablement supposer que les différents rituels autour du feu qui sont importants dans l'hindouisme ont été amenés par les Aryens. La vallée de l'Indus les gens ne semblent pas avoir été en possession de chevaux, les phoques et les Harappan terre ne montrent aucun signe de chevaux. Autres que les vestiges exhumés de Harappa et Mohenjo-Daro, ces sceaux fournir les indications plus détaillées sur la personnalité et la culture de la vallée de l'Indus. Taureaux et les éléphants apparaissent sur les phoques, mais les taureaux à cornes ne peuvent toujours pas être associé à Shiva, le taureau dans l'hindouisme. La vache révérés de l'hindouisme également n'apparaît pas sur le Harappan phoques. Les femmes dépeintes sur les sceaux élaborer porter des vêtements lourds bijoux. Cela donne à penser que la vallée de l'Indus personnes ont été perfectionnées personnes ayant cultivé des goûts à un stade avancé sentiment artistique. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La vallée de l'Indus civilisation soulève de nombreuses questions non résolues. Pourquoi est-ce que cette civilisation, compte tenu de sa sophistication, pas propagé au-delà de la vallée de l'Indus? La zone où la civilisation de l'Indus est aride développés, et l'on peut supposer que le développement urbain a eu lieu le long d'une rivière qui a coulé à travers un désert virtuel. Il ya aussi des question à propos de la disparition de la vallée de l'Indus villes. Dans le Rig Veda, il est fait mention d'un dieu de la guerre védiques, Indra, détruisant certains des forts et citadelles, ce qui pourrait avoir inclus Harappa et d'autres villes de la vallée de l'Indus. Cependant, la plupart des preuves concernant les villes "disparition est basée sur l'arrivée des Aryens en Inde.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die frühesten Spuren von Zivilisation auf dem indischen Subkontinent finden sich entlang des Flusses Indus. Die ersten Ausgrabungen dieser Indus Valley Civilization, oder Harappan Civilization, wurden in 1921 in den antiken Städten und Harappa Mohenjo-Daro. Beide Websites zeigen Beispiele einer hochentwickelten Zivilisation, die erst einige entwickelte zwischen 4500 und 5000 Jahre alt. Die Indus-Tal waren die meisten Menschen wahrscheinlich Dravidians, wer kann sie gedrückt wurden in Südindien, wenn die Arier, mit ihren militärischen Technik weiter fortgeschritten, begann ihre Migration nach Indien um 2000 v. Chr.. Obwohl der Indus-Tal-Skript muss noch entschlüsselt werden, die zahlreichen Dichtungen, Statuen, Töpfer, und die Städte der Indus-Tal Wissenschaftler haben es ermöglicht, den Bau eines realistischen Konto des Indus Valley Civilization. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Eine zentrale Staat, Stadt und umfassende Planung, wird vorgeschlagen, durch das Layout der großen Städte und der Harappa Mohenjo-Daro. Die gleiche Art von gebrannten Ziegeln offenbar wurden in vielen Städten, die Hunderte von Kilometern auseinander. Die Maße und Gewichte zeigen eine deutliche Regelmäßigkeit. Die Indus-Tal Menschen domestizierte Tiere und geerntet verschiedenen Kulturen wie Baumwolle, Sesam, Erbsen und Gerste. Sie können auch Menschen wurden Seefahrt, wie Indus Valley Dichtungen wurden in Orten wie Sumer. Allerdings ist die Indus Valley Civilization offenbar wurden ausgiebig Stadtentwicklung, der ehemalige herausfordernde Idee von Indien als landwirtschaftliches Zivilisation. Die Indus-Tal Menschen hatten ein Händler Klasse, die, wie Daten vermuten lässt, die sich im Handel weit verbreitet. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Weder noch Harappa Mohenjo-Daro zeigen irgendwelche Anzeichen von Feuer-Altäre, und als Ergebnis kann man vernünftigerweise davon aus, dass die verschiedenen Rituale rund um das Feuer, die wichtig sind im Hinduismus wurden von den Ariern. Die Indus-Tal Menschen nicht erscheinen, haben im Besitz von Pferden, wie Harappan Dichtungen und Terrakotta zeigen keine Anzeichen für Pferde. Andere als die ausgegrabenen Ruinen der Harappa-und Mohenjo-Daro, diese Siegel bieten die meisten detaillierte Hinweise auf die Persönlichkeit und die Kultur des Indus-Tal Menschen. Bulls und Elefanten bis auf die Dichtungen, die noch horned Bullen kann es immer noch nicht in Verbindung gebracht werden mit Shiva's Stier im Hinduismus. Die Kuh verehrt der Hinduismus auch nicht in der Harappan Dichtungen. Die Frauen porträtiert die Dichtungen auf Verschleiß aufwändige Kleidung in der Schwerindustrie Schmuck. Dies lässt den Schluss zu, dass die Indus-Tal waren anspruchsvoll kultivierten Menschen mit Geschmack in einem fortgeschrittenen künstlerischen Gefühl. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die Indus-Tal Zivilisation wirft viele ungelöste Fragen. Warum ist diese Zivilisation, in Anbetracht ihrer Komplexität, nicht ausserhalb der Indus-Tal? Der Bereich, in dem die Indus Valley Civilization entwickelt, ist trocken, und man kann vermuten, daß auf die städtische Entwicklung fand an einem Fluss entlang, floss durch einen virtuellen Wüste. Es gibt auch Fragen über das Verschwinden der Indus-Tal Städten. In der Rig Veda erwähnt, es ist ein Krieg vedischen Gott Indra, zerstören einige Festungen und Burgen, das hätte auch Harappa Indus Valley und anderen Städten. Allerdings sind die meisten der Nachweise über die Städte 'Verschwinden stützt sich auf die Ankunft der Arier in Indien.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Le prime tracce di civiltà del subcontinente indiano si trovano lungo il fiume Indus. I primi scavi di questa Civiltà della valle dell'Indo, o Harappan Civilization, sono state effettuate nel 1921 e l'antica città di Harappa e Mohenjo-Daro. Entrambi questi siti mostrano alcuni esempi di una civiltà altamente sofisticato che prima sviluppato alcuni 4500 - 5000 anni fa. La gente della valle sono stati Dravidians più probabile, che potrebbe essere stato spinto verso il basso in India meridionale quando il ariani, con le loro più avanzata tecnologia militare, ha iniziato le loro migrazioni in India intorno al 2000 aC. Anche se il Indus Valley script deve ancora essere decifrata, i numerosi sigilli, statuaria, vasaio, e le città della valle di Indus studiosi hanno permesso di costruire una realistica conto della Civiltà della valle dell'Indo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Una stato centralizzato, ampie e urbanistica, è suggerita dal layout della grande città di Harappa e Mohenjo-Daro. Lo stesso tipo di bruciato mattone sembra essere stata utilizzata in molte città che sono state centinaia di miglia di distanza. I pesi e le misure mostrano una sostanziale regolarità. La gente della valle animali addomesticati e raccolte varie colture, come il cotone, sesamo, piselli, e orzo. Essi possono anche essere stati navigatori, come Indus Valley sigilli sono stati trovati in luoghi come Sumeri. Tuttavia, la Civiltà della valle dell'Indo sembra essere stata ampiamente urbano, sfidando l'ex India idea di come la civiltà agricola. La gente della valle era un mercante di classe che, come suggerisce dati, impegnati nella diffusione commerciale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Né Harappa Mohenjo-Daro, né mostrare alcuna prova del fuoco altari, e, di conseguenza, si può ragionevolmente supporre che i vari rituali intorno al fuoco, che sono importanti e Induismo sono stati portati dagli ariani. La gente della Valle non sembrano essere stati in possesso di cavalli, come Harappan sigilli di terracotta e non mostrano alcun segno di cavalli. Diversa da quella scavata e rovine di Harappa Mohenjo-Daro, questi sigilli fornire suggerimenti più dettagliati sulla personalità e della cultura del popolo della valle. Tori e gli elefanti fare apparire sulla sigilli, ma i cornuti tori ancora non può essere associato con il toro di Shiva e Induismo. La mucca di venerata anche l'Induismo non viene visualizzato in Harappan sigilli. Le donne ritratte sulla sigilli elaborare indossare indumenti pesanti e gioielli. Questo suggerisce che la gente della valle sono stati colti con le persone sofisticato gusto in un avanzato sentimento artistico. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La civiltà della Valle solleva molte questioni irrisolte. Perché questa civiltà, considerando la sua raffinatezza, e non al di là della diffusione della Valle? La zona in cui la Civiltà della valle dell'Indo è sviluppato aride, e si può supporre che lo sviluppo urbano si è svolta lungo un fiume che fluiva attraverso un deserto virtuale. Ci sono anche questione circa la scomparsa del Indus Valley città. Nel Rig Veda si parla di una guerra dio vedica, Indra, distruggendo alcune fortezze e cittadelle, che potrebbe avere incluso Harappa e di altre città della Valle. Tuttavia, la maggior parte degli elementi di prova concernenti la citta 'si basa sulla scomparsa l'arrivo degli ariani in India.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los primeros rastros de civilización en el subcontinente indio se pueden encontrar a lo largo del río Indus. Las primeras excavaciones de este valle de Indus la civilización, o la civilización Harappan, se llevaron a cabo en 1921 en las antiguas ciudades de Harapa y Mohenjo-Daro. Ambos de estos sitios muestran ejemplos de una civilización altamente sofisticada que desarrolló primero algunos 4500 - 5000 años atrás. El valle de Indus personas fueron Dravidianos más probable, que puede haber sido empujado hacia abajo en el sur de la India, cuando los arios, con su más avanzada tecnología militar, comenzó sus migraciones a la India, alrededor del año 2000 antes de Cristo. Aunque el valle de Indus script todavía tiene que ser descifrado, de las numerosas focas, estatuas, alfarero, y las ciudades del valle de Indus han permitido a los estudiosos de construir una consideración realista de la civilización del valle del Indo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Un estado centralizado, y una amplia planificación de la ciudad, ha sido propuesto por el trazado de las grandes ciudades de Harapa y Mohenjo-Daro. El mismo tipo de ladrillo quemado parece haber sido utilizadas en muchas ciudades que estaban a cientos de kilómetros de distancia. Los pesos y medidas muestran una importante regularidad. El valle de Indus personas y animales domesticados cosechado diversos cultivos, como el algodón, sésamo, guisantes, y la cebada. También pueden haber sido marinero pueblo, como Indus Valle de focas han sido encontradas en lugares como Sumer. Sin embargo, el valle de Indus la civilización parece haber sido ampliamente urbana, desafiando la antigua idea de la India como una civilización agrícola. El valle de Indus la gente tenía una clase mercantil que, según los datos sugiere, que participan en el comercio generalizado. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ni Harapa ni Mohenjo-Daro mostrar ninguna prueba de fuego altares, y como resultado se puede suponer razonablemente que los diversos rituales en torno al fuego que son importantes en el hinduismo son aportados por los arios. El valle de Indus la gente no parece haber sido en la propiedad de los caballos, como Harappan sellos de terracota y no muestran ninguna prueba de caballos. Aparte de la excavación ruinas de Harapa y Mohenjo-Daro, estos sellos proporcionan los más detallados consejos sobre la personalidad y la cultura del Indus Valle de la gente. Toros y elefantes hacer figurar en los sellos, sin embargo, el cornudo toros todavía no puede ser asociada con el toro de Shiva en el hinduismo. El venerado de la vaca también el hinduismo no aparece en la Harappan focas. La mujer retratada en la elaboración de sellos de desgaste en la ropa pesada joyería. Esto sugiere que el valle de Indus personas fueron sofisticados gustos de las personas con cultivos en avanzado sentimiento artístico. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El valle de Indus la civilización plantea muchas cuestiones no resueltas. ¿Por qué esta civilización, teniendo en cuenta su complejidad, no se extienda más allá del valle de Indus? El área en la que la civilización del valle del Indo se desarrolló áridas, y uno puede suponer que el desarrollo urbano se llevó a cabo a lo largo de un río que fluía a través de un desierto virtual. También hay preguntas sobre la desaparición de las ciudades del valle Indus. En el Rig Veda se habla de un dios védico guerra, Indra, la destrucción de algunos fuertes y ciudadelas, que podría haber incluido Harapa y otras ciudades del valle Indus. Sin embargo, la mayoría de las pruebas relativas a las ciudades' se basa en la desaparición de la llegada de los arios en la India.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Over the centuries the Yarlung Zangbo valley was the focus of ancient trade routes from India, China, and central Asia. Tibet emerged from an obscure history to flourish in the 7th cent. AD as an independent kingdom with its capital at Lhasa. Toward the end of the 12th century many Indian Buddhists, fleeing before the Muslim invasion, went to Tibet. In the 13th century Tibet fell under Mongol influence, which was to last until the 18th century. In 1270, Kublai Khan, emperor of China, was converted to Buddhism by the abbot of the Sakya lamasery. The abbot returned to Tibet to found the Sakya dynasty (1270-1340) and to become the first priest-king of Tibet. In 1720, the Ch'ing dynasty replaced Mongol rule in Tibet. China thereafter claimed suzerainty, often merely nominal.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the 18th century, British authorities in India attempted to establish relations with Lhasa, but Tibet maintained its traditional seclusion. Meanwhile, Ladakh, long part of Tibet, was lost to the rulers of Kashmir, and Sikkim was seized by Britain. In 1906, Britain recognized China's suzerainty over Tibet. However, the Tibetans were able to expel the Chinese from Tibet and reassert their independence (1912). After the death (1933) of the 13th Dalai Lama, Tibet gradually drifted back into the Chinese orbit. By a Tibetan-Chinese agreement (May, 1951), Tibet became a national autonomous region of China under the traditional rule of the Dalai Lama, but under the actual control of a Chinese Communist Commission.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Communist government introduced far-reaching land reforms and sharply curtailed the power of the monastic orders. Full-scale revolt broke out in March, 1959. The Chinese suppressed the rebellion, but the Dalai Lama managed to escape to India.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Chinese adopted brutal repressive measures, provoking charges from the Dalai Lama of genocide. Landholdings were seized, the lamaseries were virtually emptied, and thousands of monks were forced to find other work. In 1965 the Tibetan Autonomous Region was formally established. The Cultural Revolution, with its antireligious orientation, was disastrous for highly religious Tibet. Religious practices were banned and over 4,000 monasteries were destroyed. Though the ban was lifted in 1976 and some Buddhist temples have again been in operation since the early 1980s, Tibetans continue to complain of widespread discrimination by the Chinese. Several protests in Tibet in the late 1980s and early 1990s were violently suppressed by the Communist government and martial law was imposed in 1989. Demonstrations against Chinese rule have nevertheless continued. Moreover, in recent years other countries have increasingly raised the issue of human-rights violations in Tibet, and have pressured the Chinese government to moderate their stance in that region.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_THAILAND_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Thai city-states gradually became independent from the weakened Khmer Empire. It is said that Sukhothai was established as a sovereign, strong kingdom by Pho Khun Si Indrathit in 1238 AD. A political feature which "classic" Thai historians call "father governs children" existed at this time. Everybody could bring their problems to the king directly, as there was a bell in front of the palace for this purpose. The city briefly dominated the area under King Ramkhamhaeng, who established the Thai alphabet, but after his death in 1365, Sukothai fell into decline and became subject to another emerging Thai state: the Ayutthaya Kingdom in the lower Chao Phraya area.[PARAGRAPH:2]Another Thai state that coexisted with Sukhothai was the northern state of Lanna, centred in Chiang Mai. King Phya Mangrai was its founder. This city-state emerged in the same period as Sukhothai. Evidently Lanna became closely allied with Sukhothai. After the Ayutthaya kingdom had emerged and expanded its influence from the Chao Phraya valley, Sukhothai was finally subdued. Fierce battles between Lanna and Ayutthaya also constantly took place and Chiang Mai was eventually subjugated, becoming Ayutthaya's 'vassal'.[PARAGRAPH:2]Lanna's independent history ended in 1558, when it finally fell to the Burmese; thereafter it was dominated by Burma until the late 18th century. Local leaders then rose up against the Burmese with the help of the rising Thai kingdom of Thonburi of king Taksin. The 'Northern City-States' then became vassals of the lower Thai kingdoms of Thonburi and Bangkok. In the early 20th century they were annexed and became part of modern Siam, the country now called Thailand.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]There can be little doubt that, had they been able to overcome their internal divisions, the Poles would have been a dominant power in the Middle Ages. The first institution that can be called a Polish kingdom or nation arose in around 980 AD, when a tribal leader named Mieszko united three major tribes in eastern Europe and converted to Catholicism. The concept of a dynasty had not yet caught on in that part of Europe, though, so successions were often extremely violent and chaotic. After Mieszko's rule, the fortunes of the Polish nation-state depended entirely on the ruthlessness and strength of will of its leader. Some of Mieszko's successors were strong and able to impose their wills on the fractious principalities and tribes of Poland and Pomerania, and thereby defend effectively against foreign, usually German or Bohemian, invasion. Others were not.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1226 AD, just over two hundred years after Boleslaw II successfully reunited the Polish kingdom, Poland was deeply divided once again. Baltic tribes menaced the north and the German state of Brandenburg sought greater land and influence in the west. The Polish king, Conrad of Mazovia, decided to import an army to fight off both of these threats in exchange for an indefinite homeland in Poland. The army was the Teutonic Knights. They accepted Conrad's offer and, after arriving in northern Poland, waged several bloody campaigns of conquest against the German and Baltic occupiers. To Conrad's surprise, though, the Knights then decided that they would rather have their own country rather than a dependent homeland inside someone else's kingdom. Conrad had saved the Polish kingdom from outside invasion, only to be invaded from within.[PARAGRAPH:2]Future Polish kings then had to deal not just with Germans, Bohemians and Lithuanians, but the restless and aggressive Teutonic Knights. As if that were not enough, in 1241 a major Mongol invasion force arrived in Silesia (southeastern Poland). The Poles were able to defeat the Mongols, but at huge cost. Vast lands were laid waste and thousands of soldiers perished. In 1330 tensions between the Teutonic Knights and Poland erupted into open war, and after many political and military stalemates, the Polish king Casimir III was able to expand and recover from the Mongol attack and the endless conflicts with Poland's neighbors. But despite holding firm, Casimir had to settle for survival rather than prosperity.[PARAGRAPH:2]The golden age of Poland came at the end of the Middle Ages, when alliance with Lithuania led to a combined assault on the Teutonic Knights that culminated in the fated battle of Grunwald in 1410. The Knights were able to fight off one contingent of the allied force, but were crushed by the other. The Knights were not totally defeated, but they would never again exert their will upon Poland as forcefully as they had in the preceding two centuries. Casimir IV, perhaps the greatest Polish king, was able to capitalize on this success to unite the Polish succession lines with those of Hungary and Bohemia, creating, albeit briefly, an eastern European super-state that dominated the region culturally and militarily for two generations.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Es kann wenig Zweifel geben, dass, wenn sie fähig gewesen wären, ihre inneren Spaltungen zu überwinden, die Polen eine dominierende Macht im Mittelalter gewesen wären. Die erste Institution, die ein polnisches Königreich oder eine polnische Nation genannt werden kann, entstand ungefähr 980 n. Chr., als ein Stammesführer, Mieszko, drei größere Stämme in Osteuropa vereinigte und zum Katholizismus konvertierte. Obwohl das Konzept einer Dynastie hatte in diesem Teil Europas noch nicht Anklang gefunden, waren Thronfolgen häufig äußerst brutal und chaotisch. Nach der Herrschaft Mieszkos hing das Geschick des polnischen Nationalstaats völlig von der Grausamkeit und Willenskraft seines Führers ab. Einige der Nachfolger Mieszkos waren stark und fähig, ihre Willen den widerspenstigen Fürstentümern und Stämmen Polens und Pommerns aufzuerlegen, und sich dabei effektiv gegen ausländische, gewöhnlich deutsche oder böhmische, Invasionen zu verteidigen. Andere waren es nicht.[PARAGRAPH:2]1226 n. Chr., nur zweihundert Jahre nachdem Boleslaw II. das polnische Königreich erfolgreich wiedervereinigt hatte, wurde Polen wieder tief geteilt. Baltische Stämme bedrohte den Norden und der deutsche Staat Brandenburg suchte größeres Land und Einfluss im Westen. Der polnische König Konrad I. von Masowien entschied sich dafür, eine Armee anzuheuern, um beide dieser Drohungen im Austausch für ein unbestimmtes Heimatland in Polen zu bekämpfen. Diese Armee waren die teutonischen Ritter. Sie akzeptierten das Angebot von Konrad und nachdem sie im nördlichen Polen angekommen waren, führten sie mehrere blutige Kampagnen der Eroberung gegen die deutschen und baltischen Besatzer. Zur Überraschung Konrads aber entschieden sich die Ritter dann dafür, dass sie lieber ihr eigenes Land und nicht ein abhängiges Heimatland innerhalb eines Königreichs eines anderen haben wollten. Konrad hatte das polnische Königreich vor äußeren Invasionen geschützt, um nun von innen angegriffen zu werden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Zukünftige polnische Könige mussten sich dann nicht nur mit Deutschen, Böhmen und Litauern, sondern auch den ruhelosen und aggressiven teutonischen Rittern befassen. Als ob das nicht genug war, kam 1241 eine große mongolische Invasionsarmee in Silesia (südöstliches Polen) an. Die Polen waren im Stande, die Mongolen zu besiegen, jedoch mit immensem Aufwand. Riesengroße Länder wurden verwüstet und Tausende von Soldaten kamen um. 1330 mündeten die Spannungen zwischen den teutonischen Rittern und Polen in offenen Krieg aus, und nach vielen politischen und militärischen Patts war der polnische König Kasimir III. im Stande, zu expandieren und sich vom mongolischen Angriff und den endlosen Konflikten mit Polens Nachbarn zu erholen. Aber obwohl er standhaft blieb, musste sich Kasimir eher mit dem Überleben, als mit Wohlstand abfinden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Das Goldene Zeitalter Polens kam am Ende des Mittelalters, als das Bündnis mit Litauen zu einem vereinigten Angriff gegen die teutonischen Ritter führte, der 1410 in der vom Schicksal bestimmten Schlacht bei Tannenberg kulminierte. Die Ritter waren im Stande, ein Kontingent der verbündeten Streitmacht zu bekämpfen, wurden aber durch den anderen zerschlagen. Die Ritter wurden nicht völlig besiegt, würden aber nie wieder ihren Willen auf Polen so kräftig ausüben, wie sie es in den vorangegangenen zwei Jahrhunderten getan hatten. Kasimir IV., der vielleicht größte polnische König, konnte aus diesem Erfolg Kapital schlagen, um die polnischen Erbfolge-Linien mit den Ungarns und Böhmens zu vereinigen. Er schuf, wenngleich nur für kurze Zeit, einen osteuropäischen Superstaat, der das Gebiet kulturell und militärisch für zwei Generationen beherrschte.</German>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La creación de una nación polaca es frecuentemente identificada con la adopción del cristianismo por su monarca Miecislao I en el 966, cuando su territorio era similar al de la Polonia moderna. El Reino de Polonia fue formado en 1025, y en 1569 cimentó una larga asociación con el Gran Ducado de Lituania al firmar la Unión de Lublin, mediante la cual se erigió la Mancomunidad Polaco-Lituana. La Mancomunidad colapsó en 1795, y el territorio polaco fue repartido entre Rusia, Prusia y Austria.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MUGHALS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Mughal Empire was an Indian-Islamic imperial power that ruled a large portion of the Indian subcontinent which began in 1526, invaded and ruled most of South Asia by the late 17th and early 18th centuries by forming alliance with Indian Maharaja, and ended in the mid-19th century. The Mughal Emperors were descendants of the Timurids, and at the height of their power around 1700, they controlled most of the Indian Subcontinent — extending from Bengal in the east to Balochistan in the west, Kashmir in the north to the Kaveri basin in the south. Its population at that time has been estimated as between 110 and 130 million, over a territory of over 4 million sq.km (1.5 million square miles).[PARAGRAPH:1]The "classic period" of the Empire started in 1556 with the accession of Jalaluddin Mohammad Akbar, better known as Akbar the Great. It ended with the death of Emperor Aurangzeb in 1707, although the Empire continued for another 150 years. During this period, the Empire was marked by a highly centralized administration connecting the different regions. All the significant monuments of the Mughals, their most visible legacy, date to this period which was characterised by the expansion of Persian cultural influence in the Indian subcontinent, with brilliant literary, artistic and architectural results.[PARAGRAPH:1]Following 1725 the empire declined rapidly, weakened by wars of succession, agrarian crises fueling local revolts, the growth of religious intolerance, the rise of the Maratha, Durrani, and Sikh empires and finally British colonialism. The last king, Bahadur Zafar Shah II, whose rule was restricted to the city of Delhi, was imprisoned and exiled by the British after the Indian Rebellion of 1857.[PARAGRAPH:1]The name Mughal is derived from the original homelands of the Timurids, the Central Asian steppes once conquered by Genghis Khan and hence known as Moghulistan, "Land of Mongols". Although early Mughals spoke the Chagatai language and maintained Turko-Mongol practices, they were essentially Persianized. They transferred the Persian literature and culture to India, thus forming the base for the Indo-Persian culture.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MOORS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The term Moors has referred to several historic and modern populations of Berber, Black African and Arab descent from Northern Africa, who came to conquer, occupy and rule the Iberian Peninsula for nearly 800 years.[citation needed] At that time they were Muslim, although earlier the people had followed other religions. They called the territory Al Andalus, comprising most of what is now Spain and Portugal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Moors are not a distinct or self-defined people. Medieval and early modern Europeans applied the name primarily to Berbers, but also at various times to Arabs, Muslim Iberians and West Africans from Mali and Niger who had been absorbed into the Almoravid dynasty. Mainstream scholars observed in 1911 that "The term 'Moors' has no real ethnological value."[PARAGRAPH:1]The Andalusian Moors of the late Medieval era inhabited the Iberian Peninsula after the Moorish conquests of the Rashidun and Umayyad Caliphates, and the final Umayyad conquest of Hispania. The Moors' rule stretched at times as far as modern-day Mauritania, West African countries, and the Senegal River. Earlier, the Classical Romans interacted with (and later conquered) parts of Mauretania, a state that covered northern portions of modern Morocco and much of north western and central Algeria during the classical period. The people of the region were noted in Classical literature as the Mauri.[PARAGRAPH:1]The term Mauri, or variations, was later used by European traders and explorers of the 16th to 18th centuries to designate ethnic Berber and Arab groups speaking the Hassaniya Arabic dialect.[citation needed] Today such groups inhabit Mauritania and parts of Algeria, western Sahara, Morocco, Niger and Mali. Speakers of European languages have historically designated a number of associated ethnic groups as "Moors". In modern Iberia, the term is applied to people of Moroccan ethnicity living in Europe. "Moor" is sometimes colloquially applied to any person from North Africa. Some people to whom it is applied consider the term pejorative and racist.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TAMILS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Tamil people, are an ethnic group native to Tamil Nadu, India and the north-eastern region of Sri Lanka. Historic and post 15th century emigrant communities are also found across the world, notably Malaysia, Singapore, Mauritius, South Africa, Australia, Canada, Réunion (France) and the UK. Since the early BCE, urbanization and mercantile activity along the western and eastern coast of what is today Kerala and Tamil Nadu led to the development of four large Tamil political states (Chera, Chola, Pandya and Pallavas) and a number of small petty states warring amongst themselves for dominance. Between the 3rd century BCE and the 3rd century CE Tamil people also produced native literature that came to be called Sangam literature. In centuries BCE religions such as Jainism, Buddhism, Saivism,Vaishnavism and was spread amongst the populace.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tamils were noted for their military, religious and mercantile activities beyond their native borders. Pandyas and Cholas were historically active in Sri Lanka. Pallava traders and religious leaders travelled to South East Asia and played an important role in the cultural Indianisation of the region. Locally developed scripts such as Grantha and Pallava script induced the development of many native scripts such as Khmer, Javanese and Thai.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tamil visual art is dominated by stylized Temple architecture in major centers and the productions of images of deities in stone and bronze. Chola bronzes, especially the Nataraja sculpture of the Chola period, have become notable as a symbol of Hinduism. Tamil performing arts are divided into popular and classical. Classical form is Bharatanatyam whereas the popular forms are known as Kuthus and performed in village temples and on street corners. Tamil cinema known as Kollywood is an important part of the Indian cinema industry. Music too is divided into classical Carnatic form and many popular genres. Although most Tamilians are Hindus, most practice what is considered to be folk Hinduism, venerating a plethora of village deities. A sizeable number are Christians and Muslims. A small Jain community survives from the classical period as well. Tamil cuisine is informed by varied vegetarian and non vegetarian items usually spiced with locally available spices. The music, the temple architecture and the stylized sculptures favored by the Tamil people as in their ancient nation are still being learnt and practiced. Thus, Tamilians have been referred to as the last surviving classical civilization on Earth.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>