<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_NEWCIV_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>A new civilization is being born</English>
		<French>Naissance d'une nouvelle civilisation</French>
		<German>Eine neue Zivilisation entsteht</German>
		<Italian>Nasce una nuova civilt&#224;</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ha nacido una nueva civilizaci&#243;n</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_NEWCIV_MESSAGE2</Tag>
		<English> empire?</English>
		<French> ?</French>
		<German> Reich übernehmen?</German>
		<Italian>?</Italian>
		<Spanish>  </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIPMESSAGE1</Tag>
		<English>The following cities:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</English>
		<French>Les villes suivantes :[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</French>
		<German>Die folgenden St&#228;dte:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</German>
		<Italian>Le seguenti citt&#224;:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>Las ciudades de[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIPMESSAGE2</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE]want to flip to a rising civilization. Our refusal may lead to a war and some of our troops may join it. Should we let them go?</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE]désirent rejoindre une civilisation émergente. Notre refus pourrait conduire à une guerre et certaines de nos troupes pourraient s'y joindre. Devons-nous les laisser y aller ?</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE]wollen sich einer aufstrebenden Zivilisation anschließen. Wenn wir es ihnen verweigern, hätte das einen Krieg zur Folge und einige unserer Truppen k&#246;nnten sich dem Feind anschließen. Sollen wir die St&#228;dte ziehen lassen?</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]vogliono passare a una nuova civilt&#224;. Il nostro rifiuto potrebbe portare alla guerra e alcune nostre truppe potrebbero unirsi a loro. Le lasciamo andare?</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE]quieren unirse a la incipiente civilizaci&#243;n. Una negativa por nuestra parte podr&#237;a provocar la guerra y parte de nuestras tropas podr&#237;an unirse a ella. ¿Debemos permitir que se unan?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_AGREED</Tag>
		<English>We agreed to the flip!</English>
		<French>Nous acceptons de céder la ville !</French>
		<German>Wir lassen sie ziehen!</German>
		<Italian>Siamo d'accordo sul passaggio!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Hemos accedido a la cesi&#243;n!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_REFUSED</Tag>
		<English>We refused the flip, this means war!</English>
		<French>Nous refusons de céder la ville, cela signifie la guerre !</French>
		<German>Wir lassen sie nicht ziehen. Das bedeutet Krieg!</German>
		<Italian>Abbiamo rifiutato il passaggio: ci&#242; significa guerra!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nos hemos negado a la cesi&#243;n, ¡esto significa la guerra!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_BETRAYAL</Tag>
		<English>Some of our forces are joining the enemy to help their war of liberation!</English>
		<French>Certaines de nos forces se joignent à l'ennemi pour les aider dans leur guerre de libération !</French>
		<German>Einige unserer Streitkr&#228;fte schlie&#223;en sich dem Feind an, um ihm bei seinem Befreiungskrieg zu helfen!</German>
		<Italian>Alcune delle nostre forze si uniscono al nemico per aiutarne la guerra di liberazione!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Algunas de nuestras unidades se han unido al enemigo para luchar en su guerra de liberaci&#243;n!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_BETRAYAL_NEW</Tag>
		<English>Some of our enemy's forces are joining us to help our war of liberation!</English>
		<French>Certaines des forces ennemies se joignent à nous pour nous aider dans notre guerre de libération !</French>
		<German>Einige feindliche Streitkr&#228;fte schlie&#223;en sich uns an, um uns bei unserem Befreiungskrieg zu helfen!</German>
		<Italian>Alcune forze del nemico si uniscono a noi per aiutarci nella guerra di liberazione!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Algunas de las unidades del enemigo se han unido a nosotros para apoyarnos en nuestra guerra de liberaci&#243;n!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISC_CIV_IS_BORN</Tag>
		<English>A new civilization is born: %s1_CityName</English>
		<French>Naissance d'une nouvelle civilisation : %s1_CityName</French>
		<German>Eine neue Zivilisation wurde geboren: %s1_CityName</German>
		<Italian>&#200; nata una nuova civilt&#224;: %s1_CityName</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ha nacido una nueva civilizaci&#243;n: %s1_CityName</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INDEPENDENCE1</Tag>
		<English/>
		<French/>
		<German/>
		<Italian>&#200; nata una nuova civilt&#224;: %s1_CityName</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ha nacido una nueva civilizaci&#243;n: %s1_CityName</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INDEPENDENCE2</Tag>
		<English>cities have declared independence from their foreign domination!</English>
		<French> ont déclaré leur indépendance par rapport à la domination étrangère !</French>
		<German>St&#228;dte haben ihre Unabh&#228;ngigkeit von der Fremdherrschaft erkl&#228;rt!</German>
		<Italian>citt&#224; hanno dichiarato la propria indipendenza dal dominio straniero!</Italian>
		<Spanish>ciudades han declarado su independencia del dominio extranjero.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_REBELLION_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>Independence!</English>
		<French>Indépendance !</French>
		<German>Unabh&#228;ngigkeit!</German>
		<Italian>Indipendenza!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Independencia!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_REBELLION_MESSAGE</Tag>
		<English>cities have declared their independence from us and expelled our garrisons. Shall we leave them free?</English>
		<French>ont déclaré leur indépendance et attaquent nos garnisons. Devons-nous les laisser libres ?</French>
		<German>St&#228;dte haben ihre Unabh&#228;ngigkeit von uns erkl&#228;rt und unsere Garnisonen vertrieben. Sollen wir sie gewähren lassen?</German>
		<Italian>citt&#224; hanno dichiarato la propria indipendenza, espellendo le nostre guarnigioni. Dobbiamo lasciarle libere?</Italian>
		<Spanish>ciudades han declarado su independencia de nosotros y han expulsado a nuestras guarniciones. ¿Debeos permitir su libertad?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>Exile!</English>
		<French>Exil !</French>
		<German>Exil!</German>
		<Italian>Esilio!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Al exilio!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TEXT1</Tag>
		<English>You have been captured by the</English>
		<French>Vous avez été capturé par les</French>
		<German>Ihr wurdet von den</German>
		<Italian>Sei stato catturato dai</Italian>
		<Spanish>El</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TEXT2</Tag>
		<English>and exiled to the unimportant lands of</English>
		<French>et exilé dans les terres inintéressantes de</French>
		<German>gefangen genommen und seid ins Exil geschickt worden - in das unbedeutende Land von</German>
		<Italian>ed esiliato nelle insignificanti terre di</Italian>
		<Spanish>os ha capturado y exiliado a las insignificantes tierras de</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TEXT3</Tag>
		<English>. You have a short period of time for retaking your capital and gain back your position.</English>
		<French>. Vous avez peu de temps pour reprendre votre capitale et récupérer votre situation.</French>
		<German>. Es bleibt Euch nur wenig Zeit, um Eure Hauptstadt zur&#252;ckzuerobern und Eure Position wiederzuerlangen.</German>
		<Italian>. Hai un breve periodo di tempo per riprendere la tua capitale e riguadagnare la tua posizione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>. Dispon&#233;is de un breve periodo de tiempo para recuperar vuestra capital y vuestra posici&#243;n.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ESCAPE_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>You have escaped!</English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes échappé !</French>
		<German>Ihr seid entkommen!</German>
		<Italian>Sei riuscito a fuggire!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Hab&#233;is escapado!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ESCAPE_TEXT1</Tag>
		<English>You have escaped and regained control of </English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes échappé et avez regagné le contrôle du territoire </French>
		<German>Ihr seid entkommen und habt die Kontrolle über das </German>
		<Italian>Sei riuscito a fuggire e a riguadagnare il controllo del territorio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hab&#233;is escapado y recuperado el control del territorio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ESCAPE_TEXT2</Tag>
		<English>territory. Now let's teach our enemies a lesson!</English>
		<French>. A présent, donnons une leçon à nos ennemis !</French>
		<German>Territorium wiedererlangt. Nun sollten wir unseren Feinden eine Lektion erteilen!</German>
		<Italian>. Ora diamo una bella lezione ai nostri nemici!</Italian>
		<Spanish>. ¡D&#233;mosles una lecci&#243;n a nuestros enemigos!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FIRST_CONTACT_NEWWORLD</Tag>
		<English>Conquerors from a far away continent are invading our lands searching for wealth!</English>
		<French>Des conquérants d'un continent lointain envahissent nos terres à la recherche de richesses !</French>
		<German>Eroberer von einem weit entfernten Kontinent fallen auf der Suche nach Reichtum in unser Land ein!</German>
		<Italian>I conquistatori provenienti da un continente lontano invadono le nostre terre in cerca di ricchezza!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Unos conquistadores de un continente lejano est&#225;n invadiendo nuestras tierras en busca de riquezas!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FIRST_CONTACT_OLDWORLD</Tag>
		<English>A group of our own adventurers has arrived in the new world searching for wealth!</English>
		<French>Un groupe de nos aventuriers est arrivé dans le nouveau monde à la recherche de richesses !</French>
		<German>Eine Gruppe Eurer eigenen Abenteurer ist auf der Suche nach Reichtum in der Neuen Welt angekommen!</German>
		<Italian>Un gruppo di nostri avventurieri &#232; arrivato nel nuovo mondo in cerca di ricchezza!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Uno de nuestros grupos de aventureros ha llegado a unas nuevas tierras en busca de riquezas!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_0</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. The Egyptian civilization coalesces under the recent unification of the Kingdoms of Lower and Upper Egypt. The fertile banks of the Nile make Egypt one of the wealthiest regions of the world. It is time to use this wealth to build monuments and establish a culture the world has never seen before.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_1</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1500 BC. After the collapse of the Harappan civilization, the Vedic Aryans reach the Indo-Gangetic plain. The following Vedic era features the development of a caste system and the Mahajanapada kingdoms, where the most important epics of Indian culture are authored, laying the foundation for the Indian religions.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_2</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. China is the easternmost region of the world where human civilization first develops. Through the dynasties of Xia, Shang and Zhou, cities develop mainly in the vicinity of the Yellow River, and the concept of a “Mandate of Heaven” is invented to legitimize the rule of the Middle Kingdom of China through the ages.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_LATE_2</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. After the Han Dynasty had collapsed, civil war between the Chinese kingdoms ensued. Only 11 years ago Emperor Wen of Sui managed to reunite China and reclaim the Mandate of Heaven. But the power of the Sui Dynasty is not completely consolidated, and the old challenges of China remain.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_3</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. The fertile crescent of Mesopotamia is home of the first urbanized cultures in the history of mankind and known as the cradle of civilization. Right now, the cities of Sumer and Akkad are thriving, but with the emergence of Babylon, they are soon to be overshadowed by the greatest metropolis of its time.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_4</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1600 BC. The first city states emerge on the Greek peninsula. While the division of the Greek civilization might seem as a disadvantage at first, their emphasis on independence favors the inception of new ideas in science and philosophy as well as new tactics in the art of warfare.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_5</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 844 BC. Persia has always been home to warlike peoples, but now the Achaemenid dynasty provides them with the unifying force to form an organized empire. While the Persian plateau is not particularly wealthy, it has rich and defenseless neighbors in India in the east and Mesopotamia in the east to conquer on their way to become the world's greatest empire.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_6</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1200 BC. Foreign invasions have weakened the Mesopotamian kingdoms, allowing the Phoenician city states to achieve independence. With the neighboring lands dominated by more powerful civilizations, the Phoenicians have turned their eyes to the west, seeing the opportunity to gain wealth by trade on the Mediterranean Sea.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_7</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 753 BC. The Latin people have just founded the city of Rome. Situated at a favorable position and governed by a superior political system, it is fated to control the whole Italian peninsula. Most of its neighboring regions in Europe are still barbaric and uncivilized. The city of Carthage is its only rival on the way to rule and civilize the whole Mediterranean.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_8</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 525 AD. The early Japanese polity centered around the Yamato province is introduced to Buddhism from Korea. This allows the spread of Chinese influences from the Sui and Tang dynasties to Japan, followed by a centralization of power into the Empire of Japan.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN__LATE_8</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. The early Japanese polity centered around the Yamato province is introduced to Buddhism from Korea. This allows the spread of Chinese influences from the Sui and Tang dynasties to Japan, followed by a centralization of power into the Empire of Japan.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_9</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 295 BC. The Ethiopian highlands are exceptionally fertile due to its temperate climate, but also quite remote from other civilizations. This changes when the major trade routes between the Roman Empire and Indians shift to the Red Sea, allowing the Ethiopian kingdom of Aksum to flourish.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_10</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 50 BC. The three Korean kingdoms of Silla, Baekje and Goguryeo form on the Korean peninsula, the first step of centralization of power away from their predecessor chiefdoms. The Chinese are close; Korea will have to have to adapt their more advanced organization without abandoning its own sovereignty.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_LATE_10</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. The three Korean kingdoms still thrive and Goguryeo has expanded the influence of Korean civilization into Manchuria. But now that China is reunited again, they have to be careful to protect their independence for the future.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_11</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 60 AD. Urbanization on the peninsula of Yucatan sparks the formation of the Mayan city states, whose technological and architectural advancements would create the first civilization in the Americas.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_12</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 330 AD. With the Roman Empire threatened by Barbarian invasions from the east, it becomes evident that the Empire cannot be governed from Rome alone. So Constantine the Great has founded Constantinopolis as a "New Rome", in hopes that the Eastern Empire will be able to withstand these incursions and eventually restore the glory of the Roman Empire.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_LATE_12</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. After the death of Justinian, most of his successes were unmade again. While the Lombards took Northern Italy and the Danube could be barely held against the Slavs, Byzantium was also plunged into a war against Sassanid Persia. Its victory proved Pyrrhic, and now the Empire is economically and militarily weakened.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_13</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 551 AD. The scarcity of food makes the inhabitants of Scandinavia excellent sailors that rely on fishing and trade. Their home kingdoms still can't sustain further population growth, and the Vikings have to turn to lands across the sea. Not only the coasts of the North Sea, but also the Mediterranean and even the New World make good targets for either plunder of settlement.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_14</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 622 AD. The founding of Islam units the Arabian people under the banner of the Caliphate. Arabia's direct neighbors, the Byzantine Empire and Sassanid Persia, are weakened from their recent wars. It is the right time to expand the House of Islam into their wealthy possessions, forming a melting pot of cultures that will bring culture and science to new heights.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_15</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 655 AD. The irregular nature of the South East Asian monsoons have so far prevented the formation of a developed civilization in the region. Not until the advanced Khmer water management techniques lead to the foundation of their capital Angkor, facilitating enormous population growth and urbanization.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_16</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 700 AD. Nearly all of the trade between China and India passes the Strait of Malacca. Benefitting from its position on the nearby island of Sumatra, the Indonesian Kingdom of Srivijaya rises to become a major trading power in South East Asia.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_17</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 718 AD. Arabs from the Ummayad Caliphate have overrun almost all of Iberia and put an end to Visigoth rule. Now the Spanish Kingdom of Asturias is founded in the mountainous north, seeking to restore Christian control over Iberia and expand it beyond.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_18</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 751 AD. After the collapse of the Western Roman Empire, the Merovingian Frankish Empire became the major Christian power in Europe. With the coronation of Pepin from the Carolingian dynasty, the Franks have come another step closer to reclaim Rome's legacy and dominate Christian Europe.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_19</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 829 AD. After the migration of Germanic peoples to Britain, the island has been divided between several Celtic, Norse and Anglo-Saxon kingdoms. Now the King of Wessex has been crowned Bretwalda and thus ruler of all of England. Now unified, the English people can turn their eyes from their island across the sea and gain rule of the waves.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_20</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 843 AD. The Treaty of Verdun brings the final separation of the Frankish Empire into West and East Francia. The eastern half dominated by German peoples, and not only would its German kings break with the Romantic Frankish culture, but also claim its imperial title and the continuation of the Holy Roman Empire.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_21</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 860 AD. Varangian travelers among the amber road between Scandinavia and Byzantium begin to set up states along their routes. Quickly mingling with their Slavic subjects, they would become the Rus and set out to settle the vast areas of Eastern Europe and beyond.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_22</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1500 AD. Situated at the confluence of Europe's most important trade routes, the Netherlands are the most populated and wealthiest region of the continent. Far too long this wealth has gone to foreign powers, but now, after long wars, the Dutch people have finally reached independence and established a Republic.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_23</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 989 AD. Sub-Saharan Africa is still underdeveloped compared to the rest of the old world. But the Malinese people control rich gold mines, which has caught the attention of its northern neighbors. Defending against foreign attempts to seize its riches by force, Mali has now the opportunity to truly become the richest civilization on Earth.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_24</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1128 AD. Portugal has just defeated Spain and gained independence. Situated at the western end of Europe, the kingdom is in a good position to send ships to ports all over the world and control the trade of all of Europe, Africa and Asia.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_25</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1150 AD. Manco Capac has just founded the Kingdom of Cuzco, the first Incan kingdom. Even in the harsh environment of the Andes and lacking suitable pack animals, they set out to create an empire never seen before in America.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_26</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1190 AD. For centuries, the peoples of the Mongolian steppe were too divided to pose an actual threat to the world. Now that Temujin has managed to unify all Mongolian tribes under his command, everything has changed, and soon both Orient and Occident will tremble in fear before his armies.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_27</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1195 AD. The Aztec peoples have founded the city of Tenochtitlan at Lake Texcoco in the Valley of Mexico. Through clever use of irrigation systems, Tenochtitlan can become the largest metropolis of Mesoamerica and dominate the surrounding cities.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_29</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1280 AD. After the collapse of the Seljuk Empire, the Anatolian Turks are divided into several small Beyliks. However, Byzantium is weakened itself, and now that the Osmanli Beylik is in the hands of a strong leader, a Turkish Ottoman Empire seems close. With the Bosphorus right within their grasp, they have the opportunity to form an empire that stretches over three continents.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_30</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1350 AD. The collapse of the Khmer Empire has allowed the Thai people to claim hegemony over South East Asia. They were able to raze the Khmer capital of Angkor and found their own kingdom west of it, in Ayutthaya.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_31</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1776 AD. Discontent with foreign domination, the people in the American colonies have risen up in revolution to found their own nation. However, their young democracy is still in danger of being reclaimed by European colonial powers and has to surpass its former masters to fulfill its manifest destiny.</English>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MONGOL_HORDE</Tag>
		<English>The Mongol hordes have invaded %s1_civ_adjective territory!</English>
		<German>Die mongolischen Horden sind in %s1_civ_adjective Territorium eingefallen!</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MONGOL_HORDE_HUMAN</Tag>
		<English>The Mongol hordes have invaded our territory!</English>
		<German>Die mongolischen Horden sind in unser Territorium eingefallen!</German>
	</TEXT>


</Civ4GameText>
