<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AMERICAN_MINUTEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Minutemen were members of teams of select men from the American colonial militia during the American Revolutionary War. They vowed to be ready for battle against the British within one minute of receiving notice. These teams consisted about a fourth of the entire militia, and generally were the younger and more mobile, serving as part of a network for early response to any threat.[PARAGRAPH:1]The minutemen were 25 years old or younger, and were chosen for their enthusiasm, political reliability, and strength. They were the first armed militia to arrive at or await a battle. Officers, as in the rest of the militia, were elected by popular vote, and each unit drafted a formal written covenant to be signed upon enlistment. The militia typically assembled as an entire unit in each town between two and four times per year for training during peacetime, but as the inevitability of a war became apparent, the militia trained more often. The minute companies trained three to four times per week. It was common for officers to make decisions through consultation and consensus with their men as opposed to giving orders to be followed without question, sometimes even in the midst of battle.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_COLOMBIAN_HACIENDA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Hacienda is a Spanish word for an estate. Some haciendas were plantations, mines or factories. Many haciendas combined these productive activities. The hacienda aimed for self-sufficiency in everything but luxuries meant for display, which were destined for the handful of people in the circle of the patrón, also known as the hacendado.[PARAGRAPH:1]Haciendas originated in land grants, mostly made to conquistadors. It is in Mexico that the hacienda system can be considered to have its origin in 1529, when the Spanish crown granted to Hernán Cortés the title of Marquess of the Valley of Oaxaca, which entailed a tract of land that included all of the present state of Morelos. Significantly, Cortés was also granted an encomienda, which included all the Native Americans then living on the land, and with power of life and death every person on his domains.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARGENTINE_REFRIGERATION_PLANT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An installation intended for the cooling, freezing, and cold storage of perishable food products and other perishables. It operates as an independent enterprise, comprises a cold-storage warehouse with truck and railroad platforms, compressor and condenser rooms for a refrigerating system, a cooling tower, reservoirs and a pumping station for a circulating water supply, administration and residential buildings, and other buildings and installations.[PARAGRAPH:1]Port cold-storage facilities are used for the short-term storage of freight when freight is transferred from one type of transport to another, for example, from water to railroad transport, and are usually built in river ports or seaports. Central cold-storage facilities are intended for the long-term storage of products drawn from processing-and-procurement cold-storage facilities for the purpose of creating reserves. Commercial cold-storage facilities, such as refrigerated cabinets and sectional coolers, are used for the short-term storage of products at trading depots and in, for example, stores, dining rooms, and restaurants. In addition to general-purpose cold-storage facilities, which are intended for the storage of a wide variety of products, specialized cold-storage facilities are built for the storage of such products as fruits, vegetables, eggs, and salted fish.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INCAN_TAMBO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Tambos (Quechua for "inn") were Incan structures built for administrative and military purposes. They were found alongside the Incan road network. They typically carried supplies, and served as lodging for itinerant state personnel (such as chasquis, Incan messengers, and quipucamayocs, those who could read and create quipus, for example) and as depositories of quipu-based records. Swift communication was achieved through the tambo network, and messages reached their destinations effectively and efficiently.[PARAGRAPH:1]Remains of tambos are scattered throughout modern-day Peru, Bolivia, Chile, and Colombia. Spanish conquistador and chronicler Pedro Cieza de León made numerous references to the tambos in his "Crónicas de Perú". In the following passage, Cieza de León described the general uses for the tambos that he learned from native peoples:[PARAGRAPH:1]And so there would be adequate supplies for their men, every four leagues there were lodgings and storehouses, and the representatives or stewards who lived in the capital of the provinces took great care to see that the natives kept these inns or lodgings (tambos) well supplied. And so certain of them would not give more than others, and all should make their contribution, they kept the accounts by a method of knots, which they call quipus, and in this way, after the troops had passed by, they could check and see that there had been no fraud.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BRAZIL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In March 1808 AD, the Portuguese royal family and ministers arrived in Rio de Janeiro to take refuge in Brazil as Napoleon's forces overran their homeland. The prince regent Joao, ruling in the stead of his mother Maria I, who was incapacitated due to mental illness, re-established his capital in Rio and ruled the empire from there. While in residence, he put in place all the ministries of a sovereign capital, as well as founding a royal library, a military academy, a royal mint, a printing office, and medical and law schools. In 1815, Joao declared Brazil a kingdom, co-equal with Portugal in the empire. Following the defeat of France, he preferred to remain in Brazil until called back to Portugal to deal with radical revolts. In April 1821, Joao appointed his son Pedro to the regency. Pedro's ministers, many Brazilian born, urged independence; the young regent issued a declaration of independence for Brazil in September 1822 and was crowned as Emperor Pedro I within three months. In 1825 the Portuguese government officially recognized Brazil's sovereignty, and within the year most of the European nations followed suit.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Ernesto Geisel assumed the presidency in 1974, and immediately launched into a "slow, gradual and safe" policy of returning rule to a democratic government. Over several years he ended the torture of political prisoners, censorship of the press, and finally the junta itself when he repealed the Fifth Institutional Act. His successor continued the process, and in 1985 the first free elections made Jose Sarney president. With a stable government and thriving economy, Brazil has since taken a leading role in regional affairs, being a founding member of organizations such as the Latin Union, Organization of American States, Mercosul, and Union of South American Nations. At the beginning of a new millennium, Brazil is poised to assume an equally influential role on the world stage.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BOLIVAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Simon Bolivar[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]President of Gran Colombia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] July 24, 1783 - December 17, 1830 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Simon Bolivar was one of South America's greatest generals. His victories over the Spaniards won independence for Bolivia, Panama, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, and Venezuela. He is called El Liberator (The Liberator) and the "George Washington of South America."[PARAGRAPH:1]Bolivar was born in July 24, 1783, at Caracas, Venezuela. His parents died when he was a child and he inherited a fortune. As a young man, he traveled in Europe.[PARAGRAPH:1]As he returned to Venezuela, Bolivar joined the group of patriots that seized Caracas in 1810 and proclaimed independence from Spain. He went to Great Britain in search of aid, but could get only a promise of British neutrality. When he returned to Venezuela, and took command of a patriot army, he recaptured Caracas in 1813 from the Spaniards.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Spaniards forced Bolivar to retreat from Venezuela to New Granada (now Colombia), also at war with Spain. He took command of a Colombian force and captured Bogota in 1814. The patriots, however, lacked men and supplies, and new defeats led Bolivar to flee to Jamaica. In Haiti he gathered a force that landed in Venezuela in 1816, and took Angostra (now Ciudad Bolivar). He also became dictator there.[PARAGRAPH:1]Bolivar marched into New Granada in 1819. He defeated the Spaniards in Boyar in 1819, liberating the territory of Colombia. He then returned to Angostura and led the congress that organized the original republic of Colombia (now Ecuador, Colombia, Panama, and Venezuela). Bolivar became its first president on December 17, 1819.[PARAGRAPH:1]Bolivar crushed the Spanish army at Carabobo in Venezuela on June 24, 1821. Next, he marched into Educador and added that territory to the new Colombian republic. After a meeting in 1822 with another great liberator, Bolivar became dictator of Peru. His army won a victory over the Spaniards at Auacucho in 1824, which needed Spanish power in South America. Upper Peru became a separate state, named Bolivia in Bolivar's honor, in 1825. The constitution, which he drew up for Bolivia, is one of his most important political pronouncements.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HARUN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Harun al-Rashid[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Caliph of Baghdad[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] March 17, 763 - March 24, 809 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Harun al-Rashid, "Harun the Orthodox", the fifth of the Abbasid caliphs of Bagdad, and the second son of the third caliph Mahdi. His full name was Harun ibn Muhammad ibn Abdallah ibn Muhammad ibn Ali ibn Abdallah ibn Abbas. He was born at Rai (Rhagae) on the 20th of March AD 763, according to some accounts, and according to others on the 15th of February AD 766. Harun al-Rashid was twenty-two years old when he ascended the throne. His father Mahdi just before his death conceived the idea of superseding his elder son Musa (afterwards known as Hadi, the fourth caliph) by Harun. But on Mahdi's death Harun gave way to his brother.[PARAGRAPH:1]Rashid owed his succession to the throne to the prudence and sagacity of Yahya bin Khalid the Barmecide, his secretary, whom on his accession he appointed his lieutenant and grand vizier. Under his guidance the empire flourished on the whole, in spite of several revolts in the provinces by members of the old Alid family. Successful wars were waged with the rulers of Byzantium and the Khazars. In 803, however, Harun became suspicious of the Barmecides, whom with only a single exception he caused to be executed. Henceforward the chief power was exercised by Fadl bin Rabi, who had been chamberlain not only under Harun himself but under his predecessors, Mansur, Madhi and Hadi. In the later years of Harun's reign troubles arose in the eastern parts of the empire. These troubles assumed proportions so serious that Harun himself decided to go to Khorasan. He died, however, at Tus in March 809.[PARAGRAPH:1]The reign of Harun was one of the most brilliant in the annals of the caliphate, in spite of losses in northwest Africa and Transoxiana. His fame spread to the West, and Charlemagne and he exchanged gifts and compliments as masters respectively of the West and the East. No caliph ever gathered around him so great a number of learned men, poets, jurists, grammarians, cadis and scribes, to say nothing of the wits and musicians who enjoyed his patronage. Harun himself was a scholar and poet, and was well versed in history, tradition and poetry. He possessed taste and discernment, and his dignified demeanor is extolled by the historians. In religion he was extremely strict; he prostrated himself a hundred times daily, and nine or ten times made the pilgrimage to Mecca. At the same time he cannot be regarded as a great administrator. He seems to have left everything to his viziers Yahya and Fadl, to the former of whom especially was due the prosperous condition of the empire. Harun is best known to Western readers as the hero of many of the stories in the Arabian Nights; and in Arabic literature he is the central figure of numberless anecdotes and humorous stories. Of his incognito walks through Bagdad, however, the authentic histories say nothing. His Arabic biographers are unanimous in describing him as noble and generous, but there is little doubt that he was in fact a man of little force of character, suspicious, untrustworthy and on occasions cruel.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LORENZO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Lorenzo di Piero de' Medici[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ruler of Florence[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] January 1, 1449 - April 9, 1492 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Lorenzo di Medici was destined to a brief but intense life that would go down in the history of Florence and Italy. He was one of the great leaders of the Italy of his time, which precisely in Florence witnessed on extraordinary flowering of intellectual activities. He was a politician, a man of power and culture.[PARAGRAPH:1]Lorenzo began his public life very early and he succeeded his father when he was not yet twenty-one. Immediatly he had to face difficult situations such as financial problems, conspiracies, relations with the Papacy, with Kings princes and milers of the countries. Nevertheless slowly the "balance of power" that Lorenzo maintained with Milan, Venice and Naples reinforced the florentine position, and wise economic measures improved the family finances. But Lorenzo's genius went further than this: he continued his family's traditional patronage of artists, opening his house and gardens to the younger ones. First Leonardo then Michelangelo and many others such as Botticelli, Filippino Lippi etc. turned to him for aid and protection.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 1485, Girolamo Savonarola, a Dominican from the convent of San Marco began to seduce the Florentines with his prophetic language. He spoke of the Apocalypse and of the dreadful God, first from the pulpit of San Marco and then from that of the cathedral. Although it had been Lorenzo who had brought the Dominican back from exile in Bologna, Savonarola's preaching soon took on a tone of implacable accusation against his benefactor.[PARAGRAPH:1]The friar accused Lorenzo publicy and univocably of ruining the state and squandering the wealth of the people deposited in the public coffers. Those who attempted to appease the spirit of the friar received the answer, "I do not care. But let (the Magnificent) know that I am a foreigner and he is a citizen and the first of the city: I am to stay and he is to go: I shall stay and not he." Many saw in these words a prophesy of Lorenzo's death, like the lightning-bolt that had struck Brunelleschi's dome a few months before his death. Accounts of this last meeting between Lorenzo the Magnificent and Savonarola, differ, but one may suppose, or hope, that in the end the friar remembered above all his duties as a priest. Lorenzo died peacefully in the night between April 8 and 9, 1492 in the Villa of Careggi. Florence was deeply shaken by his death which left an immense void in the world.[PARAGRAPH:1]Two years after Lorenzo's death his eldest son Piero, called the "unfortunate", was exiled from Florence for his political "incapacity" and only after 18 years the Medici family could return to its home-town.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SONGTSEN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Songtsen Gampo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dharmaraja of Tibet[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 617 - 649 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Songtsen Gampo was the first Dharmaraja of Tibet. He married a Nepalese and a Chinese princess and was famous for building the Jokhang Temple of Lhasa which still stands today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Songtsen Gampo was the forefather of Buddhism in Tibet. Two generations before King Trisong Detsen invited Shantarakshita and Padmasambhava to Tibet, King Songtsen Gampo cultivated the nation for its transformation, clearing pathways for the dharma to enter and ultimately permeate Tibetan culture. Without Songsten Gampo there would be no Tibetan alphabet, Lhasa would have no Jokang, and the supreme demoness of Central Tibet might still be roaming the earth unfettered.[PARAGRAPH:1]Songtsen Gampo reigned from 617 to 650. His Yarlung dynasty was based in Central Tibet during an imperialist period in Tibetan history. Bon was the dominant religion, and Buddhism was only seminally present. No Tibetan translations of the Buddhist scriptures existed, partially because there was no written form of Tibetan, so Songsten Gampo instructed his minister Thonmi Sambota to travel to India, study Sanskrit, and develop a Tibetan script. He then commissioned the translation of several thousand texts.[PARAGRAPH:1]His celebrated successes in battle expanded the Tibetan empire deep into Nepal and China, and it was during these battles that he gained an appreciation of the neighbouring cultures. As a reminder of the great empire that Songtsen Gampo ruled, a large pillar still stands before the Potala palace in Lhasa, erected during his reign, on which is inscribed the agreement between the Tibetan and Chinese rulers to respect each other's borders. He studied Chinese, became skilled in the art of leadership, and most importantly, he adopted sacred codes of conduct from Buddhist scripture. Under his rule, sacred practices began to replace the shamanistic practices of the Bonpos.[PARAGRAPH:1]Songtsen Gampo's two queens can be credited for a great part of his cultural awareness. Bhirkuti, from Kathmandu, brought the traditions of Himalayan Buddhism. Princess Wengchen, daughter of the Tang emperor, brought a treasure trove of ancient Chinese wisdom. She travelled across the steppes to her husband with a collection of Chinese classic literature and texts on sacred astrology, geomancy, and medicine.[PARAGRAPH:1]Many obstacles lay in Princess Wengchen's path as she headed to Yarlung. She had a vision of a gargantuan demoness who lay sprawled across the Himalayas, so large that one limb lay in Paro, Bhutan and another lay in Western Tibet. When she arrived in Yarlung, she shared her vision with her new husband. Recognizing the value of the treasures that his bride brought to him, as well as the importance of her vision, King Songsten Gampo commissioned thirteen demoness-subjugating temples across the land, built over the demoness's vital organs, ankles, wrists, and torso, forever binding her from wreaking havoc. The Lhasa Jokang was built over her heart centre, and Wengchin's Buddha statue was placed inside, where it still resides. Other such temples are Trenduk Lhakhang in Tsetang and Paro Kyichu in Bhutan.[PARAGRAPH:1]King Songtsen Gampo is considered a human emanation of Avalokiteshvara, and he was the grandfather of King Trisong Detsen. Songtsen Gampo meditated for several years in a cave that is now at the core of Potala palace, and is revered for his great patronage of Buddhism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Through his enlightened leadership, the path was cleared for the dharma to be propagated throughout the provinces, and for Buddhism to flourish.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_YAQUB_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Yaqub al-Mansur[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Caliph of Morocco and Al-Andalus[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c. 1160 - January 23, 1199 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Abu Yusuf Ya'qub al-Mansur, in full Abu Yusuf Ya'qub Ibn 'abd Al-mu'min Al-mansur (born c. 1160—died Jan. 23, 1199, Marrakech, Mor.), third ruler of the Mu'minid dynasty of Spain and North Africa, who during his reign (1184–99) brought the power of his dynasty to its zenith.[PARAGRAPH:1]When his father, Abu Ya'qub Yusuf, died on July 29, 1184, Abu Yusuf Ya'qub succeeded to the throne with minor difficulties. In November factious tribes in Algeria captured Algiers and other towns, but by 1188 he had pacified his African territories and returned to his Spanish possessions to check the encroachments of the Portuguese and Castilians. His efforts took seven years—until the Battle of Alarcos (July 18, 1195), when he decisively defeated the Castilian army of Alfonso VIII and took the title of al-Mansur (“the Victor”). The following year he advanced as far as Madrid but was unable to take it.[PARAGRAPH:1]Having defeated all of his enemies, al-Mansur returned to Marrakech, where he went into partial retirement and appointed his son Muhammad as his heir. Al-Mansur was a great builder of public works, many of which still stand.</English>
		<French>No translation yet</French>
		<German>No translation yet</German>
		<Italian>No translation yet</Italian>
		<Spanish>No translation yet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
