<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_AGRARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Agrarianism has two common meanings. The first meaning refers to a social philosophy or political philosophy which values rural society as superior to urban society, the independent farmer as superior to the paid worker, and sees farming as a way of life that can shape the ideal social values. It stresses the superiority of a simpler rural life as opposed to the complexity of city life, with its banks and factories. The American Thomas Jefferson was a representative agrarian who built Jeffersonian Democracy around the notion that farmers are "the most valuable citizens" and the truest republicans.[PARAGRAPH:2]The philosophical roots of agrarianism include European and Chinese philosophers. The Chinese School of Agrarianism was a philosophy that advocated peasant utopian communalism and egalitarianism. This influenced European intellectuals like François Quesnay, an avid Confucianist and advocate of China's agrarian policies, forming the French agrarian philosophy of Physiocracy. The Physiocrats, along with the ideas of John Locke and the Romantic Era, formed the basis of modern European and American agrarianism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Secondly, the term "agrarianism" means political proposals for land redistribution, specifically the distribution of land from the rich to the poor or landless. This terminology is common in many countries, and originated from the "Lex Sempronia Agraria" or "agrarian laws" of Rome in 133 BC, imposed by Tiberius Gracchus, that seized the lands of the rich and distributed them to the poor. This definition of agrarianism is commonly known as "agrarian reform".[PARAGRAPH:2]In societies influenced by Confucianism, the farmer was considered an esteemed productive member of society, whereas merchants who made money were looked down upon. In eighteenth- and nineteenth-century England, the word identified any land reform movement that sought to redistribute cultivated lands equally. Today, the word has largely shed this radical political meaning. Instead, agrarianism points to a collection of political, philosophical, and literary ideas that together tend to describe farm life in ideal terms.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ANIMISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Allows the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Persecution[COLOR_REVERT] of other religions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Animism (from Latin anima "soul, life") is a set of beliefs based on the existence of non-human "spiritual beings" or similar kinds of embodied principles.[PARAGRAPH:2]Animism encompasses the beliefs that there is no separation between the spiritual and physical (or material) world, and souls or spirits exist, not only in humans, but also in all other animals, plants, rocks, geographic features such as mountains or rivers, or other entities of the natural environment. Animism may further attribute souls to abstract concepts such as words, true names, or metaphors in mythology. Examples of Animism can be found in forms of Shinto, Serer, Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, Pantheism, Paganism, and Neopaganism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Throughout European history, philosophers such as Aristotle and Thomas Aquinas, among others, contemplated the possibility that souls exist in animals, plants, and people; however, the currently accepted definition of animism was only developed in the 19th century by Sir Edward Tylor, who created it as "one of anthropology's earliest concepts, if not the first".[PARAGRAPH:2]According to the anthropologist Tim Ingold, animism shares similarities to totemism but differs in its focus on individual spirit beings which help to perpetuate life, whereas totemism more typically holds that there is a primary source, such as the land itself or the ancestors, who provide the basis to life. Certain indigenous religious groups such as the Australian Aborigines are more typically totemic, whereas others like the Inuit are more typically animistic in their worldview.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_AUTOCRACY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An Autocracy is a system of government in which a supreme political power is concentrated in the hands of one person, whose decisions are subject to neither external legal restraints nor regularized mechanisms of popular control (except perhaps for the implicit threat of coup d'état or mass insurrection).[PARAGRAPH:2]Autocracy is any form of government in which one person is the supreme power within the state. It is derived from the Greek "auto" ("self") and "kratos" ("rule"), and may be translated as "one who rules by himself". It is distinct from oligarchy ("rule by the few") and democracy ("rule by the people"). Like "despot", "tyrant", "strongman" and "dictator", "autocrat" has become a loaded word with a negative value judgment in contemporary English usage.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term autokrator is employed in antiquity to translate the Latin imperator into Greek. It was the primary word used by grecophones to the Roman Emperor during the later Roman Empire through the seventh century AD and continued to be used in the Byzantine period, although it lost favor to Sebastos ("augustus") and Basileus (obscure: prob. "chieftain;" later "king") as synonyms for "emperor". This use remains current in the modern Greek language, where the term is used for anyone holding the title "emperor," regardless of the actual power of the monarch.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CAPITALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Capitalism is an economic system that is based on private ownership of the means of production and the creation of goods or services for profit. Competitive markets, wage labor, capital accumulation, voluntary exchange, and personal finance are also considered capitalistic. Competitive markets, capital accumulation, voluntary exchange, and personal finance may be parts of capitalism, however in practice there are never pure capitalist economies. Often, other non-capitalist systems such as market socialism and worker cooperatives retain aspects of capitalism. There are multiple variants of capitalism, including laissez-faire and state capitalism. Capitalism is considered to have been applied in a variety of historical cases, varying in time, geography, politics, and culture. There is general agreement that capitalism became dominant in the Western world following the demise of feudalism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Economists, political economists and historians have taken different perspectives on the analysis of capitalism. Economists usually emphasize the degree to which government does not have control over markets (laissez faire), as well as the importance of property rights. Most political economists emphasize private property as well, in addition to power relations, wage labor, class, and the uniqueness of capitalism as a historical formation. The extent to which different markets are free, as well as the rules defining private property, is a matter of politics and policy. Many states have what are termed mixed economies, referring to the varying degree of planned and market-driven elements in a state's economic system. A number of political ideologies have emerged in support of various types of capitalism, the most prominent being economic liberalism.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term capitalism gradually spread throughout the Western world in the 19th and 20th centuries largely through the writings of Karl Marx. However, it is the default economic system and it has its roots tracing back to the beginning of recorded history.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CITY_STATES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A city-state is an independent or autonomous entity whose territory consists of a city which is not administered as a part of another local government. A city-state can also be defined as a central city and its surrounding villages, which together follow the same law, have one form of government, and share languages, religious beliefs, and ways of life. Today, only three independent, sovereign city-states exist: Monaco, Singapore, and the Vatican City.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EGALITARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Egalitarianism (from French égal, meaning "equal") is a trend of thought that favors equality among living entities. Egalitarian doctrines maintain that all humans are equal in fundamental worth or social status, according to The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. The Cultural theory of risk holds egalitarianism as defined by (1) a negative attitude towards rules and principles, and (2) a positive attitude towards group decision-making, with fatalism termed as its opposite. According to the Merriam-Webster Dictionary, the term has two distinct definitions in modern English. It is defined either as a political doctrine that all people should be treated as equals and have the same political, economic, social, and civil rights or as a social philosophy advocating the removal of economic inequalities among people or the decentralization of power. Some sources define egalitarianism as the point of view that equality reflects the natural state of humanity.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PANTHEON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Religious Victory:[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Make sure there are 15 pagan temples in the world[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Control ten wonders that require no state religion[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Don't allow more than half of your cities to have a religion[NEWLINE]Allows construction of [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Pagan Temples[COLOR_REVERT] and also the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ishtar Gate[COLOR_REVERT], [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Machu Picchu[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseum[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colossus[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Cothan[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Library[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Lighthouse[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Sphinx[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Oracle[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Parthenon[COLOR_REVERT], the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Pyramids[COLOR_REVERT] and the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Artemis[COLOR_REVERT] World Wonders. [PARAGRAPH:2]A pantheon (literally "a temple of all gods", "of or common to all gods") is a set of all the gods of a particular polytheistic religion or mythology.[PARAGRAPH:2]Max Weber's 1922 opus, Economy and Society, discusses the link between a pantheon of gods and the development of monotheism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Pantheon can also refer to a temple or sacred building explicitly dedicated to "all deities", avoiding the difficulty of giving an exhaustive list. The most known such structure is the Pantheon of Rome, built in the year 27 BC. The building was dedicated to "all gods" as a gesture embracing the religious syncretism in the increasingly multicultural Roman Empire, with subjects worshipping gods from many cultures and traditions. The building was later renovated for use as a Christian church in 609 under Pope Boniface IV.[PARAGRAPH:2]Since the 16th century "pantheon" also refers in a secular sense to the set of a society's exalted persons. For example "Mick Jagger was exalted into the pantheon of rock megastars".</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_REPUBLIC_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Allows construction of the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Statue of Liberty[COLOR_REVERT] World Wonder.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]In a republic, the head of state is not a monarch and there are no legal privileges for the nobility. The exact form of government can vary widely, from absolute despotism to direct democracy, but the most important difference between a republic and any form of monarchy is the much-diminished role of family and lineage in government.[PARAGRAPH:2]Before the French Revolution, a republic in Europe was an aberration. The state enjoyed none of the external security provided by royal family ties. Internally, the succession was decided to some extent by merit, even if this often meant merely that the man with the best ability to take power would do so.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SCHOLASTICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Allows the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Persecution[COLOR_REVERT] of other religions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Scholasticism is a method of critical thought which dominated teaching by the academics (scholastics, or schoolmen) of medieval universities in Europe from about 1100-1500, and a program of employing that method in articulating and defending orthodoxy in an increasingly pluralistic context. It originated as an outgrowth of, and a departure from, Christian monastic schools.[PARAGRAPH:2]Not so much a philosophy or a theology as a method of learning, scholasticism places a strong emphasis on dialectical reasoning to extend knowledge by inference, and to resolve contradictions. Scholastic thought is also known for rigorous conceptual analysis and the careful drawing of distinctions. In the classroom and in writing, it often takes the form of explicit disputation: a topic drawn from the tradition is broached in the form of a question, opponents' responses are given, a counterproposal is argued and opponent's arguments rebutted. Because of its emphasis on rigorous dialectical method, scholasticism was eventually applied to many other fields of study.[PARAGRAPH:2]As a program, scholasticism began as an attempt at harmonization on the part of medieval Christian thinkers: to harmonize the various authorities of their own tradition, and to reconcile Christian theology with classical and late antiquity philosophy, especially that of Aristotle but also of Neoplatonism.[PARAGRAPH:2]The main figures of scholasticism historically are Anselm of Canterbury, Peter Abelard, Alexander of Hales, Albertus Magnus, Duns Scotus, William of Ockham, Bonaventure and Thomas Aquinas. Thomas Aquinas's masterwork, the Summa Theologica, is often seen as the highest fruit of Scholasticism. Important work in the scholastic tradition has been carried on, however, well past Aquinas' time, for instance by Francisco Suárez and Molina, and also among Lutheran and Reformed thinkers.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SECULARISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Religious Victory:[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Tolerance: Control the temples of seven different religions[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Humanism: Make sure there are 20 universities controlled by secular civilizations[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET]Modernization: Be the first to enter the Industrial and Modern eras[PARAGRAPH:2][TAB]Secularism is the principle of separation between government institutions and the persons mandated to represent the State from religious institutions and religious dignitaries. In one sense, secularism may assert the right to be free from religious rule and teachings, and the right to freedom from governmental imposition of religion upon the people within a state that is neutral on matters of belief. (See also separation of church and state and Laïcité.) In another sense, it refers to the view that human activities and decisions, especially political ones, should be unbiased by religious influence. Some scholars are now arguing that the very idea of secularism will change.[PARAGRAPH:2]Secularism draws its intellectual roots from Greek and Roman philosophers such as Marcus Aurelius and Epicurus; medieval Muslim polymaths such as Ibn Rushd; Enlightenment thinkers such as Denis Diderot, Voltaire, Baruch Spinoza, John Locke, James Madison, Thomas Jefferson, and Thomas Paine; and more recent freethinkers, agnostics, and atheists such as Robert Ingersoll and Bertrand Russell.[PARAGRAPH:2]The purposes and arguments in support of secularism vary widely. In European laicism, it has been argued that secularism is a movement toward modernization, and away from traditional religious values (also known as secularization). This type of secularism, on a social or philosophical level, has often occurred while maintaining an official state church or other state support of religion. In the United States, some argue that state secularism has served to a greater extent to protect religion and the religious from governmental interference, while secularism on a social level is less prevalent. Within countries as well, differing political movements support secularism for varying reasons.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SELF_SUFFICIENCY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Self-sufficiency is the state of not requiring any aid, support, or interaction, for survival; it is therefore a type of personal or collective autonomy. On a national scale, a totally self-sufficient economy that does not trade with the outside world is called an autarky.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term self-sufficiency is usually applied to varieties of sustainable living in which nothing is consumed outside of what is produced by the self-sufficient individuals. Examples of attempts at self-sufficiency in North America include simple living, homesteading, off-the-grid, survivalism, DIY ethic and the back-to-the-land movement.[PARAGRAPH:2]Practices that enable or aid self-sufficiency include autonomous building, permaculture, sustainable agriculture, and renewable energy.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term is also applied to limited forms of self-sufficiency, for example growing one's own food or becoming economically independent of state subsidies.[PARAGRAPH:2]The entire population of the world was, at one time, self sufficient. They made their own clothing, tools, weapons, boats, huts, and food. They used gathering, hunting, herding and farming to find/hunt/grow their own food. As the human population of he world grew, the wild food supply dwindled. People began to rely on herding and farming more; reling less upon gathering and hunting. In modern times, automated food production on farms makes food. The vast populations now depend on a fewer farmers to make their food for them. Many in developed nations now depend on job salaries to buy food, clothes, and shelter, rather than making these things from raw materials found in the environment. But in a few places in the world, native societies continue to be self sufficient, never having given up their traditional ways of food gathering and food making. Because these native peoples have no jobs and make no salaries, they are often listed as unemployed.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_TOTALITARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Totalitarianism (or totalitarian rule) is a political system where the state recognizes no limits to its authority and strives to regulate every aspect of public and private life wherever feasible. Totalitarian regimes stay in political power through an all-encompassing propaganda campaign, which is disseminated through the state-controlled mass media, a single party that is often marked by political repression, personality cultism, control over the economy, regulation and restriction of speech, mass surveillance, and widespread use of terror. It is not synonymous with dictatorship, as authoritarian regimes also exhibit dictatorial features, but do not create an all-controlling, all-politicised society. Furthermore, non-dictatorial governments and societies are sometimes denounced as having totalitarian features, including democratic socialism, capitalism and liberal democracy.[PARAGRAPH:2]The concept of totalitarianism was first developed in a positive sense in the 1920s by the Italian fascists. The concept became prominent in Western anti-communist political discourse during the Cold War era in order to highlight perceived similarities between Nazi Germany and other fascist regimes on the one hand, and Soviet communism on the other.[PARAGRAPH:2]Aside from fascist and Stalinist movements that are totalitarian, there have been other movements that are totalitarian. The leader of the historic Spanish reactionary conservative movement called the Spanish Confederation of the Autonomous Right declared his intention to "give Spain a true unity, a new spirit, a totalitarian polity..." and went on to say "Democracy is not an end but a means to the conquest of the new state. When the time comes, either parliament submits or we will eliminate it." Baathist Iraq was distinctly ultra-nationalist and totalitarian, and has been dubbed by historian Stanley G. Payne as "the closest" reproduction of the Third Reich. Several revolutionary fundamentalist regimes have been pointed out as totalitarian, including post-revolutionary Iran.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_LIMITED_UNIT_HAPPINESS</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad per Military Unit Stationed in a City up to a Maximum of %D3</English>
		<French>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad par unit&#233; militaire en garnison dans une ville</French>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad pro in einer Stadt stationierter Milit&#228;reinheit bis zu einem Maximum von %D3</German>
		<Italian>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit%F2_HappyOrSad per le unit&#224; militari stazionate in citt&#224;</Italian>
		<Spanish>[ICON_BULLET]%D1_PerUnit %F2_HappyOrSad por cada unidad militar destacada en la ciudad</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EGALITARIANISM_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Unable to Use Slaves[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET][ICON_UNHAPPY] Penalty for Slaves in Civs without [LINK=literal]Egalitarianism[\LINK]</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MILITIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The most basic method of organizing an armed defense for the community is that of the militia. In primitive societies, every adult male is expected to fight (with varying competence) to either protect the village or to raid and harass neighbors. In more settled and organized societies, the duty of forming a militia tends to fall on volunteers armed and trained at community expense, or on elite classes of citizens who can afford their own weapons.[PARAGRAPH:2]Militia have the strategic advantages of being numerous, cheap to maintain from the central government's perspective, and of having reliable local loyalties that make them difficult to suborn. The large, corresponding disadvantages are that they are often less competent than more professional forces, difficult to keep in the field for long periods, and reluctant to fight far from their homes.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_STANDING_ARMY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As nations grow large and prosperous, it is natural for them to expand their permanent cadre of armed forces into a professional organization that exists through times of both war and peace. Soldiers in these standing armies are paid for service on much the same basis as civilian employees would be. The rise of a professional military is usually accompanied by the rise of a dedicated bureaucracy or staff, which makes management of manpower and the military-industrial complex more efficient. Easy access into a volunteer military from citizens of all classes also makes the military an organ of social cohesion.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_WARRIOR_CODE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Many societies have a distinct class that supplies the nation's fighting manpower during war. Such a class usually sets itself apart from the common run of the people, adopting distinct cultural behaviors and attitudes to meet the special needs of men who must be ready and able to fight at any time. Since powerful military figures tend to dominate their societies, this class often has the wealth and power to make its cultural preferences known throughout the land, finding expression in art and poetry that promotes the ideals of the heroic warrior and provides examples of such to the next generation. Even where an elite martial class is not present or not dominant over the mercantile and agricultural classes, military traditions can spill over into common society and come to dominate it - witness the rise of militarism in 19th century Prussia for an example.[PARAGRAPH:2]In general, this kind of war-culture promotes military fitness among the citizens and makes for a keen, well-led army. On the other hand, it often leads to the neglect of social or economic problems in favor of fixation on martial virtues. It can also lead to arrogant overconfidence when faced with a foe who doesn't share one's own warrior values.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_FANATICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Allows the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Persecution[COLOR_REVERT] of other religions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Fanaticism is strict adherence to a specific set of theological doctrines. These doctrines are usually considered to be of much greater importance and relevance than any man-made laws; in many cases a fanatical state adopts them as state law and strives to impose them on other civilizations as well. Other religions are regarded with disdain or even open hostility. Alternatively, some fanatical states prefer to isolate themselves from the heathens and secularism of the world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ORGANIZED_RELIGION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Allows the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Persecution[COLOR_REVERT] of other religions.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]An organized religion is one in which there is a central authority which interprets or determines theology, which decides which ceremonies are to be performed at which times, and which appoints priests or holy men to keep worshipers on the correct path. The central authority may be a rigid and powerful hierarchy with great religious and secular power, or it may be a group of elders who meet periodically to discuss matters of importance to their members. [PARAGRAPH:2]An organized religion can be a mighty thing, more powerful than kings or despots. Its followers may provide it with great wealth, and may construct mighty edifices in their gods' honor. Usually, however, organized religions are less powerful than that and must live in uneasy harmony with the local secular governments. </English>
		<French>[TAB]Une religion organis&#233;e dispose d'une autorit&#233; centralis&#233;e qui interpr&#232;te et d&#233;termine la th&#233;ologie, qui d&#233;cide quand et comment sont organis&#233;es les c&#233;r&#233;monies du culte et qui se charge de nommer les pr&#234;tres et autres hommes d'&#233;glise qui dirigeront les fid&#232;les. L'autorit&#233; centrale peut prendre la forme d'une hi&#233;rarchie rigide et puissante ayant un pouvoir &#224; la fois religieux et la&#239;c. Elle peut aussi &#234;tre compos&#233;e d'un groupe d'anciens qui se r&#233;unissent r&#233;guli&#232;rement pour discuter des probl&#232;mes que rencontre leur communaut&#233;. [PARAGRAPH:2]Une religion organis&#233;e peut &#234;tre puissante et avoir davantage de pouvoir qu'un roi ou qu'un despote. Ses fid&#232;les peuvent la rendre riche et b&#226;tir des &#233;difices majestueux en l'honneur de leur Dieu. Cependant, les religions organis&#233;es sont rarement aussi puissantes et doivent g&#233;n&#233;ralement vivre tant bien que mal en harmonie avec un v&#233;ritable pouvoir la&#239;que. </French>
		<German>[TAB]Eine organisierte Religion hat eine zentrale Autorit&#228;t, die f&#252;r die Interpretation der Theologie, die Liturgie, die Priesterweihe und Heiligsprechungen verantwortlich ist. Diese zentrale Autorit&#228;t ist nicht selten eine einflussreiche Beh&#246;rde mit betr&#228;chtlicher geistlicher und weltlicher Macht. [PARAGRAPH:2]Organisierte Religionen konnten sehr m&#228;chtig werden, m&#228;chtiger noch als K&#246;nige oder Despoten. Oft h&#228;uften ihre Gl&#228;ubigen gro&#223;e Reicht&#252;mer an und errichteten zu Ehren ihres Gottes pr&#228;chtige Geb&#228;ude. Heute ist der politische und religi&#246;se Einfluss organisierter Religionen allerdings eher gering.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]In una organizzazione religiosa esiste un'autorit&#224; centrale che interpreta o determina la teologia, che decide quando e quali cerimonie devono essere eseguite, che nomina i sacerdoti o gli uomini santi per mantenere i fedeli sulla retta via. L'autorit&#224; centrale pu&#242; essere una gerarchia potente e rigida di grandi religioni e potere secolare, oppure pu&#242; essere rappresentata da un gruppo di anziani che si incontrano periodicamente per discutere questioni importanti. [PARAGRAPH:2]Una organizzazione religiosa pu&#242; rappresentare un grande potere, pi&#249; di quello di un re o un despota: i seguaci possono fornire ricchezze e finanziare la realizzazione di grandi edifici in onore degli dei. Tuttavia, le organizzazioni religiose sono meno potenti e devono vivere in una difficile armonia con i governi locali laici.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Una religi&#243;n organizada es una en la que existe una autoridad central que interpreta o establece la teolog&#237;a, decide qu&#233; ceremonias se llevan a cabo y nombra a los sacerdotes u hombres santos encargados de mantener al reba&#241;o en el recto camino. La autoridad central puede ser una jerarqu&#237;a r&#237;gida y poderosa dotada de gran poder religioso y secular o puede estar formada por un consejo de ancianos que se re&#250;ne peri&#243;dicamente para debatir todos los asuntos concernientes a sus fieles.  [PARAGRAPH:2]Las religiones organizadas pueden ser muy poderosas, m&#225;s incluso que los reyes o los d&#233;spotas. Sus seguidores pueden proporcionarle enormes riquezas y erigir impresionantes edificios en honor a sus dioses.  Sin embargo, lo normal es que no sean tan poderosas y se vean obligadas a convivir en un estado de complicada armon&#237;a con los poderes seculares. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PUBLIC_WELFARE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An early version of the welfare state appeared in China during the Song Dynasty in the 11th century. Prime Minister Wang Anshi believed that the state was responsible for providing its citizens the essentials for a decent living standard. Accordingly, under his direction the state initiated agricultural loans to relieve the farming peasants. He appointed boards to regulate wages and plan pensions for the aged and unemployed. These reforms were known as the "new laws," New Policies, or xin fa.[PARAGRAPH:2]Modern welfare states developed through a gradual process beginning in the late 19th century and continuing through the 20th. They differed from previous schemes of poverty relief due to their relatively universal coverage. The development of social insurance in Germany under Bismarck was particularly influential. Some schemes, like those in Scandinavia, were based largely in the development of autonomous, mutualist provision of benefits. Others were founded on state provision. The term was not, however, applied to all states offering social protection. The sociologist T.H. Marshall identified the welfare state as a distinctive combination of democracy, welfare and capitalism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Examples of early welfare states in the modern world are Sweden (Folkhemmet), Germany, the Netherlands, and New Zealand in the 1930s. Germany is generally held to be the first social welfare state. Changed attitudes in reaction to the Great Depression were instrumental in the move to the welfare state in many countries, a harbinger of new times where "cradle-to-grave" services became a reality after the poverty of the Depression. During the Great Depression, it was seen as an alternative "middle way" between communism and fascism. In the period following the Second World War, many countries in Europe moved from partial or selective provision of social services to relatively comprehensive coverage of the population.[PARAGRAPH:2]The activities of present-day welfare states extend to the provision of both cash welfare benefits (such as old-age pensions or unemployment benefits) and in-kind welfare services (such as health or childcare services). Through these provisions, welfare states can affect the distribution of wellbeing and personal autonomy among their citizens, as well as influencing how their citizens consume and how they spend their time.[PARAGRAPH:2]After the discovery and inflow of the oil revenue, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, and United Arab Emirates all became welfare states. However, the services are strictly for citizens and these countries do not accept immigrants; even those born in these countries do not qualify for citizenship unless they are of the parentage belonging to their respective countries.[PARAGRAPH:2]The beginning of the modern welfare state was in 1911 when David Lloyd George suggested everyone in work should pay national insurance contribution for unemployment and health benefits from work.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1942, the 'Social Insurance and Allied Services' was created by Sir William Beveridge in order to aid those who were in need of help, or in poverty. Beverage worked as a volunteer for the poor, and set up national insurance. He stated that 'All people of working age should pay a weekly national insurance contribution. In return, benefits would be paid to people who were sick, unemployed, retired or widowed.' The basic assumptions of the report were the National Health Service, which provided free health care to the UK. The Universal Child Benefit was a scheme to to give child benefits, which encouraged people to have children so they could afford to keep them alive and not for them to starve to death. This was particularly useful after the second world war, where the population in England declined, so encouragement for new babies was encouraged, which sparked the baby boom. The impact of the report was huge and 600,000 copies were made. He recommended to the government that they should find ways of tackling the five giants, being Want, Disease, Ignorance, Squalor and Idleness. He argued to cure these problems, the government should provide adequate income to people, adequate health care, adequate education, adequate housing and adequate employment. Before 1939, health care had to be paid for, this was done through a vast network of friendly societies, trade unions and other insurance companies which counted the vast majority of the UK working population as members. These friendly societies provided insurance for sickness, unemployment and invalidity, therefore providing people with an income when they were unable to work. But because of the 1942 Berveridge Report, in 5th July 1948, the National Insurance Act, National Assistance Act and National Health Service Act came into force, thus this is the day that the modern UK welfare state was founded.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CENTRAL_PLANNING_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Central planning represents an economy completely controlled, owned and planned by the government, otherwise known as state capitalism. Under a centrally planned economy, all labor, capital, production, agriculture, utilities, and finances are run by the government, and all service businesses are owned by the government. Because there are no private companies, no trade exists. Centrally planned economies are able to concentrate their resources on major projects such as world wonders and world projects, but are very costly to maintain.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ABSOLUTISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Absolute monarchy (or simply absolutism) is a monarchical form of government where the monarch has the power to rule his or her land or country and its citizens freely, with no laws or legally-organized direct opposition in force. Although some religious authority may be able to discourage the monarch from some acts and the sovereign is expected to act according to custom, in an absolute monarchy there is no constitution or body of law above what is decreed by the sovereign (king or queen). As a theory of civics, absolute monarchy puts total trust in well-bred and well-trained monarchs raised for the role from birth.[PARAGRAPH:2]The theory of absolute monarchy developed in the late Middle Ages from feudalism, during which a monarch was still very much the "first among equals" (primes inter pares) among the nobility. With the creation of centralized administrations and standing armies backed by expensive artillery, the power of the monarch gradually increased relative to that of the nobles (whose military power had declined with the effectiveness of heavy cavalry), and from this was created the theory of absolute monarchy.[PARAGRAPH:2]In theory, an absolute monarch has total power over his or her people and land, including the aristocracy and sometimes the clergy (see caesaropapism). In practice, absolute monarchs have often found their power limited - generally by one or other of those groups.[PARAGRAPH:2]Some monarchies (for example the German Empire, 1871-1918) have powerless or symbolic parliaments and other governmental bodies that the monarch can alter or dissolve at will. Despite effectively being absolute monarchies, they are technically constitutional monarchies due to the existence of a constitution and national canon of law.[PARAGRAPH:2]The popularity of the notion of absolute monarchy declined substantially after the French Revolution and American Revolution, which promoted theories of government based on popular sovereignty. Among the few states that retain a rather absolute monarchy are Bhutan, Brunei, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Swaziland, and the Vatican City (the papal city-state, a theocractic elective monarchy).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_DYNASTICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A dynasty is a sequence of rulers considered as members of the same family. Historians traditionally consider many sovereign states' history within a framework of successive dynasties, e.g., Ancient Egypt, Persian Empire, and Imperial China. Much of European political history is dominated by dynasties such as the Carolingians, the Capetians, the Bourbons, the Habsburgs, the Stuarts, the Hohenzollerns and the Romanovs. Until the 19th century, it was taken for granted that a legitimate function of a monarch was to aggrandize his dynasty: that is, to increase the territory, wealth and power of family members.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_LEVY_ARMIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Under the feudal conditions for holding land in the medieval period, most peasants and freemen were liable to provide one man of suitable age per family for military duty when required by either the king or the local lord. The levies raised in this way fought as infantry under local superiors. Although the exact laws varied greatly depending on the country and the period, generally these levies were only obliged to fight for one to three months. Most were subsistence farmers, and it was in everyone's interest to send the men home for harvest-time.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A mercenary is a person who takes part in an armed conflict, who is not a national or a party to the conflict and is "motivated to take part in the hostilities by the desire for private gain." The term "mercenary" is also used to describe the army itself.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TECH_MERCENARIES_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The mercenary is the oldest profession in the world. A mercenary is a soldier, who is recruited by payment and is bound by a fixed-term contract. Mercenaries could be usually recruited in certain cities or areas and often counted to the elite units of an army due to their war experience and their good equipment. Famous groups of mercenaries were the slingers from the Balearic Islands, the Bactrian riders and Syrian elite units.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The mercenary is the oldest profession in the world. A mercenary is a soldier, who is recruited by payment and is bound by a fixed-term contract. Mercenaries could be usually recruited in certain cities or areas and often counted to the elite units of an army due to their war experience and their good equipment. Famous groups of mercenaries were the slingers from the Balearic Islands, the Bactrian riders and Syrian elite units.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das S&#246;ldnertum ist das &#228;lteste Gewerbe der Welt. Ein S&#246;ldner ist ein gegen Bezahlung (Sold) angeworbener, zumeist zeitlich befristet dienender und durch Vertrag gebundener Soldat. S&#246;ldner konnten meist in bestimmten St&#228;dten oder Gebieten rekrutiert werden und z&#228;hlten oft aufgrund ihrer Kriegserfahrung und ihrer guten Ausr&#252;stung zu den Eliteeinheiten einer Armee. Ber&#252;hmte S&#246;ldnergruppen bildeten die balearischen Steinschleuderer, die baktrischen Reiter und syrische Eliteeinheiten.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The mercenary is the oldest profession in the world. A mercenary is a soldier, who is recruited by payment and is bound by a fixed-term contract. Mercenaries could be usually recruited in certain cities or areas and often counted to the elite units of an army due to their war experience and their good equipment. Famous groups of mercenaries were the slingers from the Balearic Islands, the Bactrian riders and Syrian elite units.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Se conoce como mercenario (del lat&#237;n merces, - eris, &#171;pago&#187;), a aquel soldado que lucha o participa en un conflicto b&#233;lico por su beneficio econ&#243;mico y personal, normalmente con poca o nula consideraci&#243;n en la ideolog&#237;a, nacionalidad o preferencias pol&#237;ticas con el bando para el que lucha. Generalmente se les menciona como asesinos a sueldo, criminales ap&#225;tridas, sicarios, etc. Sin embargo, cuando este t&#233;rmino (mercenario) se usa para referirse a un soldado de un ej&#233;rcito regular, se considera normalmente un insulto a su honra. [NEWLINE] [NEWLINE]El soldado, que representa a su naci&#243;n, est&#225; dispuesto a luchar por una causa que es de su comunidad o pa&#237;s. Sin embargo, el mercenario lo hace solamente con &#225;nimo de lucro. De ah&#237; que a los mercenarios se les conozca tambi&#233;n como soldados de fortuna.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_TYRANNY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In classical politics, a tyrant (Greek, tyrannos) is one who illegally seizes and controls a governmental power in a polis. Tyrants were a group of individuals who took over many Greek poleis during the uprising of the middle classes in the sixth and seventh centuries BC, ousting the aristocratic governments. Plato and Aristotle define a tyrant as, "one who rules without law, looks to his own advantage rather than that of his subjects, and uses extreme and cruel tactics -- against his own people as well as others". During the sixth and seventh centuries BC, tyranny was often looked upon as an intermediate stage between narrow oligarchy and more democratic forms of polity. However, in the late fifth and fourth centuries, a new kind of tyrant, the military dictator arose, specifically in Sicily. In ancient Greece, tyrants were influential opportunists that came to power by securing the support of different factions of a deme. The word "tyrannos", possibly pre-Greek, Pelasgian or eastern in origin, then carried no ethical censure; it simply referred to anyone, good or bad, who obtained executive power in a polis by unconventional means. Support for the tyrants came from the growing middle class and from the peasants who had no land or were in debt to the wealthy land owners. It is true that they had no legal right to rule, but the people preferred them over kings or the aristocracy. The Greek tyrants stayed in power by using mercenary soldiers from outside of their respective city-state. To mock tyranny, Thales wrote that the strangest thing to see is "an aged tyrant" meaning that tyrants do not have the public support to survive for long. In Corinth, growing wealth from colonial enterprises, and the wider horizons brought about by the export of wine and oil, together with the new experiences of the Eastern Mediterranean brought back by returning mercenary hoplites employed overseas allowed Cypselus, the first tyrant of Corinth in the 7th century BC, to overthrow the aristocratic power of the dominant but unpopular Bacchiadae, who were killed, executed, driven out and exiled in 657 BC. Corinth prospered economically under his rule and Cypselus manages to rule without a bodyguard but when he managed to bequeath his position to his son, Periander, whose position was less secure, his son required a bodyguard of mercenary soldiers personally loyal to himself. Nevertheless, under Cypselus and Periander, Corinth extended and tightened her control over her colonial enterprises, and exports of Corinthian pottery flourished. However, tyrants seldom succeeded in establishing an untroubled line of succession. Perianders successor was less fortunate and was expelled, Corinth was ruled by a lack-lustre oligarchy, and was exclipsed by the rising powers of Athens and Sparta. In Athens, the inhabitants first gave the title of tyrant to Peisistratus, a relative of Solon, the Athenian lawgiver, who succeeded in 546 BC, after 2 failed attempts, to install himself as tyrant. Supported by prosperity of the pesantry and landowning interests of the plain (prospering from the rise of olive exports), and his clients from Marathon, he managed to achieve supreme power. Through an ambitious program of public works, by fostering the state cult of Athena, by encouraging the creation of festivals and supporting the Panathenaean games, in which prizes were jars of olive oil, and in his support of the Dionosia (leading to the development of Athenian drama) Peisistratus managed to maintain his personal popularity. He was followed by his sons, and with the subsequent growth of Athenian democracy, the title "tyrant" took on its familiar negative connotations. The murder of his son, the tyrant Hipparchus by Aristogeiton and Harmodios in Athens in 514 BC marked the beginning of the so-called "cult of the tyrannicides" (i.e., of killers of tyrants). Contempt for tyranny characterised this cult movement. Despite financial help from Persia, in 510 the Peisistratids were expelled by a combination of intrigue, exile and Spartan arms. The anti-tyrannical attitude became especially prevalent in Athens after 508 BC, when Cleisthenes reformed the political system so that it resembled demokratia (ancient participant democracy as opposed to the modern representative democracy).</English>
		<French>[TAB]In classical politics, a tyrant (Greek, tyrannos) is one who illegally seizes and controls a governmental power in a polis. Tyrants were a group of individuals who took over many Greek poleis during the uprising of the middle classes in the sixth and seventh centuries BC, ousting the aristocratic governments. Plato and Aristotle define a tyrant as, "one who rules without law, looks to his own advantage rather than that of his subjects, and uses extreme and cruel tactics -- against his own people as well as others". During the sixth and seventh centuries BC, tyranny was often looked upon as an intermediate stage between narrow oligarchy and more democratic forms of polity. However, in the late fifth and fourth centuries, a new kind of tyrant, the military dictator arose, specifically in Sicily. In ancient Greece, tyrants were influential opportunists that came to power by securing the support of different factions of a deme. The word "tyrannos", possibly pre-Greek, Pelasgian or eastern in origin, then carried no ethical censure; it simply referred to anyone, good or bad, who obtained executive power in a polis by unconventional means. Support for the tyrants came from the growing middle class and from the peasants who had no land or were in debt to the wealthy land owners. It is true that they had no legal right to rule, but the people preferred them over kings or the aristocracy. The Greek tyrants stayed in power by using mercenary soldiers from outside of their respective city-state. To mock tyranny, Thales wrote that the strangest thing to see is "an aged tyrant" meaning that tyrants do not have the public support to survive for long. In Corinth, growing wealth from colonial enterprises, and the wider horizons brought about by the export of wine and oil, together with the new experiences of the Eastern Mediterranean brought back by returning mercenary hoplites employed overseas allowed Cypselus, the first tyrant of Corinth in the 7th century BC, to overthrow the aristocratic power of the dominant but unpopular Bacchiadae, who were killed, executed, driven out and exiled in 657 BC. Corinth prospered economically under his rule and Cypselus manages to rule without a bodyguard but when he managed to bequeath his position to his son, Periander, whose position was less secure, his son required a bodyguard of mercenary soldiers personally loyal to himself. Nevertheless, under Cypselus and Periander, Corinth extended and tightened her control over her colonial enterprises, and exports of Corinthian pottery flourished. However, tyrants seldom succeeded in establishing an untroubled line of succession. Perianders successor was less fortunate and was expelled, Corinth was ruled by a lack-lustre oligarchy, and was exclipsed by the rising powers of Athens and Sparta. In Athens, the inhabitants first gave the title of tyrant to Peisistratus, a relative of Solon, the Athenian lawgiver, who succeeded in 546 BC, after 2 failed attempts, to install himself as tyrant. Supported by prosperity of the pesantry and landowning interests of the plain (prospering from the rise of olive exports), and his clients from Marathon, he managed to achieve supreme power. Through an ambitious program of public works, by fostering the state cult of Athena, by encouraging the creation of festivals and supporting the Panathenaean games, in which prizes were jars of olive oil, and in his support of the Dionosia (leading to the development of Athenian drama) Peisistratus managed to maintain his personal popularity. He was followed by his sons, and with the subsequent growth of Athenian democracy, the title "tyrant" took on its familiar negative connotations. The murder of his son, the tyrant Hipparchus by Aristogeiton and Harmodios in Athens in 514 BC marked the beginning of the so-called "cult of the tyrannicides" (i.e., of killers of tyrants). Contempt for tyranny characterised this cult movement. Despite financial help from Persia, in 510 the Peisistratids were expelled by a combination of intrigue, exile and Spartan arms. The anti-tyrannical attitude became especially prevalent in Athens after 508 BC, when Cleisthenes reformed the political system so that it resembled demokratia (ancient participant democracy as opposed to the modern representative democracy).</French>
		<German>[TAB]Der Begriff der Tyrannis umschreibt eine Herrschaftsform der griechischen Antike, die besonders im Zeitraum zwischen 600 v. Chr. und 200 v. Chr. vorkam. Es handelte sich um eine Art von Alleinherrschaft, wobei man in der Regel zwei Phasen unterscheidet: die &#196;ltere (oder Archaische) Tyrannis, die im 7. Jahrhundert v. Chr. aufkam und sp&#228;testens 461 v. Chr. endete, sowie die J&#252;ngere Tyrannis, die gegen Ende des 5. Jahrhunderts v. Chr. aufkam und vor allem au&#223;erhalb des griechischen Mutterlandes (vor allem auf Sizilien) verbreitet war. Im Gegensatz zur Basileia (K&#246;nigtum) bezeichnete der Begriff Tyrannis dabei in der Regel eine illegitime Form der Alleinherrschaft &#252;ber eine Polis, in der eine monarchische Staatsform eigentlich nicht vorgesehen und mit den nomoi (Gesetzen) schwer oder gar nicht vereinbar war.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]In classical politics, a tyrant (Greek, tyrannos) is one who illegally seizes and controls a governmental power in a polis. Tyrants were a group of individuals who took over many Greek poleis during the uprising of the middle classes in the sixth and seventh centuries BC, ousting the aristocratic governments. Plato and Aristotle define a tyrant as, "one who rules without law, looks to his own advantage rather than that of his subjects, and uses extreme and cruel tactics -- against his own people as well as others". During the sixth and seventh centuries BC, tyranny was often looked upon as an intermediate stage between narrow oligarchy and more democratic forms of polity. However, in the late fifth and fourth centuries, a new kind of tyrant, the military dictator arose, specifically in Sicily. In ancient Greece, tyrants were influential opportunists that came to power by securing the support of different factions of a deme. The word "tyrannos", possibly pre-Greek, Pelasgian or eastern in origin, then carried no ethical censure; it simply referred to anyone, good or bad, who obtained executive power in a polis by unconventional means. Support for the tyrants came from the growing middle class and from the peasants who had no land or were in debt to the wealthy land owners. It is true that they had no legal right to rule, but the people preferred them over kings or the aristocracy. The Greek tyrants stayed in power by using mercenary soldiers from outside of their respective city-state. To mock tyranny, Thales wrote that the strangest thing to see is "an aged tyrant" meaning that tyrants do not have the public support to survive for long. In Corinth, growing wealth from colonial enterprises, and the wider horizons brought about by the export of wine and oil, together with the new experiences of the Eastern Mediterranean brought back by returning mercenary hoplites employed overseas allowed Cypselus, the first tyrant of Corinth in the 7th century BC, to overthrow the aristocratic power of the dominant but unpopular Bacchiadae, who were killed, executed, driven out and exiled in 657 BC. Corinth prospered economically under his rule and Cypselus manages to rule without a bodyguard but when he managed to bequeath his position to his son, Periander, whose position was less secure, his son required a bodyguard of mercenary soldiers personally loyal to himself. Nevertheless, under Cypselus and Periander, Corinth extended and tightened her control over her colonial enterprises, and exports of Corinthian pottery flourished. However, tyrants seldom succeeded in establishing an untroubled line of succession. Perianders successor was less fortunate and was expelled, Corinth was ruled by a lack-lustre oligarchy, and was exclipsed by the rising powers of Athens and Sparta. In Athens, the inhabitants first gave the title of tyrant to Peisistratus, a relative of Solon, the Athenian lawgiver, who succeeded in 546 BC, after 2 failed attempts, to install himself as tyrant. Supported by prosperity of the pesantry and landowning interests of the plain (prospering from the rise of olive exports), and his clients from Marathon, he managed to achieve supreme power. Through an ambitious program of public works, by fostering the state cult of Athena, by encouraging the creation of festivals and supporting the Panathenaean games, in which prizes were jars of olive oil, and in his support of the Dionosia (leading to the development of Athenian drama) Peisistratus managed to maintain his personal popularity. He was followed by his sons, and with the subsequent growth of Athenian democracy, the title "tyrant" took on its familiar negative connotations. The murder of his son, the tyrant Hipparchus by Aristogeiton and Harmodios in Athens in 514 BC marked the beginning of the so-called "cult of the tyrannicides" (i.e., of killers of tyrants). Contempt for tyranny characterised this cult movement. Despite financial help from Persia, in 510 the Peisistratids were expelled by a combination of intrigue, exile and Spartan arms. The anti-tyrannical attitude became especially prevalent in Athens after 508 BC, when Cleisthenes reformed the political system so that it resembled demokratia (ancient participant democracy as opposed to the modern representative democracy).</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La tiran&#237;a (del griego tyrannos), en el sentido que se dio al t&#233;rmino en la Grecia antigua, era el r&#233;gimen de poder absoluto, de ordinario unipersonal, que con frecuencia instauraba el tirano, aquel o aquellos que hab&#237;an derrocado el gobierno de una ciudad-estado, normalmente gracias al apoyo popular, pero tambi&#233;n mediante un golpe de estado militar o una intervenci&#243;n extranjera. [NEWLINE] [NEWLINE]Parece que el t&#233;rmino "tirano" se aplic&#243; por primera vez a Fid&#243;n de Argos y a C&#237;pselo de Corinto. El periodo de esplendor de los reg&#237;menes de tiran&#237;a fue el siglo VI a. C., cuando muchos gobiernos del Egeo fueron derribados y Persia tuvo ocasi&#243;n de hacer sus primeras incursiones en Grecia, al buscar diversos tiranos su apoyo para consolidarse en el poder. Pis&#237;strato y sus descendientes, los pisistr&#225;tidas (Hipias e Hiparco), son el ejemplo de estos gobernantes para Atenas; Pol&#237;crates para Samos, y muchos otros. [NEWLINE] [NEWLINE]La tiran&#237;a griega fue fruto de la lucha de las clases populares contra los abusos de la aristocracia y los reyes-sacerdotes, cuyo derecho a gobernar ven&#237;a sancionado por las tradiciones ancestrales y la mitolog&#237;a. Los tiranos llegaron con frecuencia al poder a trav&#233;s de revueltas populares y gozaron de la simpat&#237;a p&#250;blica como gobernantes, al menos en sus primeros a&#241;os en el poder. De Pis&#237;strato, por ejemplo, cuenta Arist&#243;teles que eximi&#243; de impuestos a un agricultor a causa de lo particularmente inf&#233;rtiles que eran sus tierras, y se dice que Cipselo pod&#237;a pasear por las calles de Corinto sin escolta de ninguna clase.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_NAVAL_DOMINANCE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In the modern western countries, the European "Age of Sail" is the period in which international trade and naval warfare were both dominated by sailing ships. The age of sail mostly coincided with the age of discovery, from the 15th to the 18th century. After the 17th century, English naval maps stopped using the term of British Sea for the English Channel. From 15th to the 18th centuries, the period saw square rigged sailing ships[26] carry European settlers to many parts of the world in one of the most important human migrations in recorded history. This period was marked by extensive exploration and colonization efforts on the part of European kingdoms. The sextant, developed in the 18th century, made more accurate charting of nautical position possible.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_DIRECT_RULE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English></English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_NO_UPGRADE</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Cannot Be Upgraded</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kann nicht aufgerüstet werden</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_EXTRA_UPKEEP_TEXT</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Costs %d1 [ICON_GOLD] Additional Upkeep</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Kostet %d1 [ICON_GOLD] zusätzlichen Unterhalt</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]Hurried Units Start with the [LINK=literal]Mercenary[\LINK] promotion</English>
		<German>[ICON_BULLET]Beschleunigte Einheiten starten mit der [LINK=literal]Söldner[\LINK]-Beförderung</German>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>