<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_NEWCIV_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>A new civilization is being born</English>
		<French>Naissance d'une nouvelle civilisation</French>
		<German>Eine neue Zivilisation entsteht</German>
		<Italian>Nasce una nuova civilt&#224;</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ha nacido una nueva civilizaci&#243;n</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_NEWCIV_MESSAGE2</Tag>
		<English> empire?</English>
		<French> ?</French>
		<German> Reich übernehmen?</German>
		<Italian>?</Italian>
		<Spanish>  </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIPMESSAGE1</Tag>
		<English>The following cities:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</English>
		<French>Les villes suivantes :[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</French>
		<German>Die folgenden St&#228;dte:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</German>
		<Italian>Le seguenti citt&#224;:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</Italian>
		<Spanish>Las ciudades de[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIPMESSAGE2</Tag>
		<English>[NEWLINE]want to flip to a rising civilization. Our refusal may lead to a war and some of our troops may join it. Should we let them go?</English>
		<French>[NEWLINE]désirent rejoindre une civilisation émergente. Notre refus pourrait conduire à une guerre et certaines de nos troupes pourraient s'y joindre. Devons-nous les laisser y aller ?</French>
		<German>[NEWLINE]wollen sich einer aufstrebenden Zivilisation anschließen. Wenn wir es ihnen verweigern, hätte das einen Krieg zur Folge und einige unserer Truppen k&#246;nnten sich dem Feind anschließen. Sollen wir die St&#228;dte ziehen lassen?</German>
		<Italian>[NEWLINE]vogliono passare a una nuova civilt&#224;. Il nostro rifiuto potrebbe portare alla guerra e alcune nostre truppe potrebbero unirsi a loro. Le lasciamo andare?</Italian>
		<Spanish>[NEWLINE]quieren unirse a la incipiente civilizaci&#243;n. Una negativa por nuestra parte podr&#237;a provocar la guerra y parte de nuestras tropas podr&#237;an unirse a ella. ¿Debemos permitir que se unan?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_AGREED</Tag>
		<English>We agreed to the flip!</English>
		<French>Nous acceptons de céder la ville !</French>
		<German>Wir lassen sie ziehen!</German>
		<Italian>Siamo d'accordo sul passaggio!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Hemos accedido a la cesi&#243;n!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_REFUSED</Tag>
		<English>We refused the flip, this means war!</English>
		<French>Nous refusons de céder la ville, cela signifie la guerre !</French>
		<German>Wir lassen sie nicht ziehen. Das bedeutet Krieg!</German>
		<Italian>Abbiamo rifiutato il passaggio: ci&#242; significa guerra!</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nos hemos negado a la cesi&#243;n, ¡esto significa la guerra!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_BETRAYAL</Tag>
		<English>Some of our forces are joining the enemy to help their war of liberation!</English>
		<French>Certaines de nos forces se joignent à l'ennemi pour les aider dans leur guerre de libération !</French>
		<German>Einige unserer Streitkr&#228;fte schlie&#223;en sich dem Feind an, um ihm bei seinem Befreiungskrieg zu helfen!</German>
		<Italian>Alcune delle nostre forze si uniscono al nemico per aiutarne la guerra di liberazione!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Algunas de nuestras unidades se han unido al enemigo para luchar en su guerra de liberaci&#243;n!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FLIP_BETRAYAL_NEW</Tag>
		<English>Some of our enemy's forces are joining us to help our war of liberation!</English>
		<French>Certaines des forces ennemies se joignent à nous pour nous aider dans notre guerre de libération !</French>
		<German>Einige feindliche Streitkr&#228;fte schlie&#223;en sich uns an, um uns bei unserem Befreiungskrieg zu helfen!</German>
		<Italian>Alcune forze del nemico si uniscono a noi per aiutarci nella guerra di liberazione!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Algunas de las unidades del enemigo se han unido a nosotros para apoyarnos en nuestra guerra de liberaci&#243;n!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MISC_CIV_IS_BORN</Tag>
		<English>A new civilization is born: %s1_CityName</English>
		<French>Naissance d'une nouvelle civilisation : %s1_CityName</French>
		<German>Eine neue Zivilisation wurde geboren: %s1_CityName</German>
		<Italian>&#200; nata una nuova civilt&#224;: %s1_CityName</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ha nacido una nueva civilizaci&#243;n: %s1_CityName</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INDEPENDENCE1</Tag>
		<English/>
		<French/>
		<German/>
		<Italian>&#200; nata una nuova civilt&#224;: %s1_CityName</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ha nacido una nueva civilizaci&#243;n: %s1_CityName</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INDEPENDENCE2</Tag>
		<English>cities have declared independence from their foreign domination!</English>
		<French> ont déclaré leur indépendance par rapport à la domination étrangère !</French>
		<German>St&#228;dte haben ihre Unabh&#228;ngigkeit von der Fremdherrschaft erkl&#228;rt!</German>
		<Italian>citt&#224; hanno dichiarato la propria indipendenza dal dominio straniero!</Italian>
		<Spanish>ciudades han declarado su independencia del dominio extranjero.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_REBELLION_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>Independence!</English>
		<French>Indépendance !</French>
		<German>Unabh&#228;ngigkeit!</German>
		<Italian>Indipendenza!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Independencia!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_REBELLION_MESSAGE</Tag>
		<English>cities have declared their independence from us and expelled our garrisons. Shall we leave them free?</English>
		<French>ont déclaré leur indépendance et attaquent nos garnisons. Devons-nous les laisser libres ?</French>
		<German>St&#228;dte haben ihre Unabh&#228;ngigkeit von uns erkl&#228;rt und unsere Garnisonen vertrieben. Sollen wir sie gewähren lassen?</German>
		<Italian>citt&#224; hanno dichiarato la propria indipendenza, espellendo le nostre guarnigioni. Dobbiamo lasciarle libere?</Italian>
		<Spanish>ciudades han declarado su independencia de nosotros y han expulsado a nuestras guarniciones. ¿Debeos permitir su libertad?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>Exile!</English>
		<French>Exil !</French>
		<German>Exil!</German>
		<Italian>Esilio!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Al exilio!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TEXT1</Tag>
		<English>You have been captured by the</English>
		<French>Vous avez été capturé par les</French>
		<German>Ihr wurdet von den</German>
		<Italian>Sei stato catturato dai</Italian>
		<Spanish>El</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TEXT2</Tag>
		<English>and exiled to the unimportant lands of</English>
		<French>et exilé dans les terres inintéressantes de</French>
		<German>gefangen genommen und seid ins Exil geschickt worden - in das unbedeutende Land von</German>
		<Italian>ed esiliato nelle insignificanti terre di</Italian>
		<Spanish>os ha capturado y exiliado a las insignificantes tierras de</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_EXILE_TEXT3</Tag>
		<English>. You have a short period of time for retaking your capital and gain back your position.</English>
		<French>. Vous avez peu de temps pour reprendre votre capitale et récupérer votre situation.</French>
		<German>. Es bleibt Euch nur wenig Zeit, um Eure Hauptstadt zur&#252;ckzuerobern und Eure Position wiederzuerlangen.</German>
		<Italian>. Hai un breve periodo di tempo per riprendere la tua capitale e riguadagnare la tua posizione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>. Dispon&#233;is de un breve periodo de tiempo para recuperar vuestra capital y vuestra posici&#243;n.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ESCAPE_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>You have escaped!</English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes échappé !</French>
		<German>Ihr seid entkommen!</German>
		<Italian>Sei riuscito a fuggire!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Hab&#233;is escapado!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ESCAPE_TEXT1</Tag>
		<English>You have escaped and regained control of </English>
		<French>Vous vous êtes échappé et avez regagné le contrôle du territoire </French>
		<German>Ihr seid entkommen und habt die Kontrolle über das </German>
		<Italian>Sei riuscito a fuggire e a riguadagnare il controllo del territorio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hab&#233;is escapado y recuperado el control del territorio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ESCAPE_TEXT2</Tag>
		<English>territory. Now let's teach our enemies a lesson!</English>
		<French>. A présent, donnons une leçon à nos ennemis !</French>
		<German>Territorium wiedererlangt. Nun sollten wir unseren Feinden eine Lektion erteilen!</German>
		<Italian>. Ora diamo una bella lezione ai nostri nemici!</Italian>
		<Spanish>. ¡D&#233;mosles una lecci&#243;n a nuestros enemigos!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FIRST_CONTACT_NEWWORLD</Tag>
		<English>Conquerors from a far away continent are invading our lands searching for wealth!</English>
		<French>Des conquérants d'un continent lointain envahissent nos terres à la recherche de richesses !</French>
		<German>Eroberer von einem weit entfernten Kontinent fallen auf der Suche nach Reichtum in unser Land ein!</German>
		<Italian>I conquistatori provenienti da un continente lontano invadono le nostre terre in cerca di ricchezza!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Unos conquistadores de un continente lejano est&#225;n invadiendo nuestras tierras en busca de riquezas!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FIRST_CONTACT_OLDWORLD</Tag>
		<English>A group of our own adventurers has arrived in the new world searching for wealth!</English>
		<French>Un groupe de nos aventuriers est arrivé dans le nouveau monde à la recherche de richesses !</French>
		<German>Eine Gruppe Eurer eigenen Abenteurer ist auf der Suche nach Reichtum in der Neuen Welt angekommen!</German>
		<Italian>Un gruppo di nostri avventurieri &#232; arrivato nel nuovo mondo in cerca di ricchezza!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Uno de nuestros grupos de aventureros ha llegado a unas nuevas tierras en busca de riquezas!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MONGOL_HORDE</Tag>
		<English>The Mongol hordes have invaded %s1_civ_adjective territory!</English>
		<German>Die mongolischen Horden sind in %s1_civ_adjective Territorium eingefallen!</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_MONGOL_HORDE_HUMAN</Tag>
		<English>The Mongol hordes have invaded our territory!</English>
		<German>Die mongolischen Horden sind in unser Territorium eingefallen!</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_INVADERS_HUMAN</Tag>
		<English>%s1 armies have invaded our territory!</English>
		<German>%s1 Armeen sind in unser Territorium eingefallen!</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VASSAL_GENERIC_COLONY</Tag>
		<English>Colony of %s1</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VASSAL_GENERIC_PROTECTORATE</Tag>
		<English>Protectorate of %s1</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SCHISM_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>The Great Schism</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_SCHISM_MESSAGE</Tag>
		<English>The institution of papacy has already existed for several centuries. However, the Pope's claim to be the sole representative of God on Earth is threatening our own theological authority. Many clergymen in our civilization are also worried that his interpretation of the Word of God has strayed too far from the true origins of Christianity. Shall we heed their call to separate from the Catholic Church in a Great Schism and follow Orthodox Christianity instead?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ASKCOLONIALCITY_TITLE</Tag>
		<English>The %s1 Trading Company</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ASKCOLONIALCITY_MESSAGE</Tag>
		<English>The %s1 Trading Company asks for the control of %s3 and offers %d2 gold. Refusal will lead to war. Shall we accept their offer?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELEASE_CIVILIZATION</Tag>
		<English>Release %s1_citylist to %s2</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_LIBERATE_MINOR</Tag>
		<English>Grant independence to %s1_city</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
