<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CARTHAGINIAN_WAR_ELEPHANT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Carthage maintained a stable of 300 elephants, both the larger central African species and the slightly smaller elephant from Barbary. Slaves and enemies were used to train elephants in the art of stomping people to death, at least according to the Roman propaganda of the time. Elephants were used against the Romans in Sicily, against Regulus, and later in the conquest of Spain. Then came Hannibal's fantastic feat of marching his troops and 40 elephants over the Pyrenees and the Alps into northern Italy. Elephants are difficult to get across swift rivers; do not do well on narrow, rocky trails; and are not accustomed to the cold. Still, Hannibal got them across, only to lose most of them in northern Italy, in Piedmont. One survived and was used by Hannibal himself to enhance his presence. The native Celts of northern Italy and the Italian peasants further south were duly impressed. But the Romans eventually found a way to cope with the dangerous elephant charges. In Hannibal's last battle (Zama, 202 BC), his elephant charge was ineffective because the Roman maniples simply made way for them to pass. After the Carthaginians were defeated, the treaty signed at Zama with the Romans specified that they were to give up their elephants and train no more. Thus ended about 60 years where the elephant was a central part of the Carthaginian attack force.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BOMBARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A bombard is a medieval cannon or mortar, used chiefly in sieges for throwing heavy stone balls. This weapon was usually used during sieges to hurl various forms of missile into enemy fortifications. Projectiles such as stone or metal balls, burning materials and weighted cloth soaked in quicklime or Greek fire are documented.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Bombarde ist eine Bezeichnung für Pulvergeschütze im Spätmittelalter. Sie ersetzten die bisher bei Belagerungen verwendeten mechanischen Wurfwaffen, wie das Trebuchet. Außer dass es sich um eine Steinbüchse (Geschütz zum Verschießen von Projektilen aus Stein) handelt, gibt es keine eindeutige technische Beschreibung. Vielfach wird von kurzen Geschützen mit verhältnismäßig großen Kalibern, also Mörsern, geschrieben. Teilweise wird die Mündung als trichterförmig beschrieben. Andere Quellen beschreiben die Bombarde als ein Geschütz mit längerem Rohr, also Kanone, in der Bauart als Kammergeschütz (also als frühen Hinterlader). Teilweise wird die Bauart als Stabringgeschütz beschrieben.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_THAI_CHANG_SUEK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Dynasties of Siam and Thailand bred and kept their own trained elephants for war. War elephants were important, although not widespread, weapons in ancient military history. Their main use was in charges, to trample the enemy and/or break their ranks. Elephant taming began in the Indus Valley civilization around 4,000 years ago. The first species to be tamed was thus the Asian elephant, for agricultural ends. The first military application of elephants dates from around 1100 BC in northern India and Pakistan, which is mentioned in several Vedic Sanskrit hymns from this era.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CIDAINH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Cidainh was an ancient Celtic chariot, drawn by a team of two horses controlled by a driver and with a warrior riding on the back. Tt was constructed from wood and wicker-work, with one-piece iron rims for the wheels (probably a Celtic invention). Another Celtic innovation was the free-hanging axle, suspended from the platform with rope and possibly even with a leather suspension system. This resulted in a much smoother and controlled ride on rough terrain.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Julius Caesar provides the only significant eyewitness report of Celtic chariot warfare: "Their mode of fighting with their chariots is this: firstly, they drive about in all directions and throw their weapons and generally break the ranks of the enemy with the very dread of their horses and the noise of their wheels; and when they have worked themselves in between the troops of horse, leap from their chariots and engage on foot. The charioteers in the meantime withdraw some little distance from the battle, and so place themselves with the chariots that, if their masters are overpowered by the number of the enemy, they may have a ready retreat to their own troops. Thus they display in battle the speed of horse, together with the firmness of infantry; and by daily practice and exercise attain to such expertness that they are accustomed, even on a declining and steep place, to check their horses at full speed, and manage and turn them in an instant and run along the pole, and stand on the yoke, and thence betake themselves with the greatest celerity to their chariots again."</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TIBETAN_KHAMPA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Kham was traditionally referred to as Chushi Gangdruk, i.e. 'four rivers and six ranges'. The peoples of Kham have endured a tumultuous past, their sovereignty often encroached upon and marginalized by both Tibetans to the West and the Han Chinese to the East.[NEWLINE][TAB]Kham was never controlled by a single king, but most of the chieftains revered the Dalai Lamas and often made contact with the Lhasa government. Kham was a patchwork of two dozen or more kingdoms, tribes, and chiefdoms that were constantly at war with each other. Since the collapse of the Tibetan Empire in the mid-9th century, the peoples of Kham had aggressively maintained their independence from invading nations. Local chieftains ruled their respective territories with hereditary titles bestowed by the Tibetan government. Chieftains were able to rule with a large degree of independence from both China and Tibet.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1717, Dzungar tribes of Mongolia invaded Tibet, and a period of internal strife and civil war followed. The Kangxi emperor sent armies into the area for 20 years, and local leaders were forced to pledge their allegiance to the Qing Empire. In 1724, the regions of Amdo and Kham were made into the province of Kokonor, with parts of Eastern Kham incorporated into neighboring Chinese provinces.[NEWLINE][TAB]In the early 19th century, Gombo Namgye raised a rebellion in Nyarong, an area of Eastern Kham. He is reported to have taken control of Eastern Tibet, excepting Amdo. Residents of Derge and the Hor States appealed to both Lhasa and the Manchu government for help against Namgye. China was unable to take action, but Tibetan authorities sent an army in 1863, and defeated Namgye in 1865. Tibet then claimed Nyarong, Derge (or De-ge) and the Hor States north of Nyarong. This appears to have been accepted by the Manchu emperor.[NEWLINE][TAB]Tibetan control of the Batang region of Kham appears to have continued uncontested from an agreement made in 1726 until soon after the invasion of Tibet by Francis Younghusband in 1904, which alarmed the Qing rulers in China. They sent an imperial official to the region to begin reasserting Qing control, but the locals revolted and killed him. The Qing government in Beijing then appointed Zhao Erfeng, the Governor of Xining, "Army Commander of Tibet" to reintegrate Tibet into China. He was sent in 1905 (though other sources say this occurred in 1908) on a punitive expedition and began destroying many monasteries in Kham and Amdo and implementing a process of sinification of the region:[NEWLINE][TAB]"He abolished the powers of the Tibetan local leaders and appointed Chinese magistrates in their places. He introduced new laws that limited the number of lamas and deprived monasteries of their temporal power and inaugurated schemes for having the land cultivated by Chinese immigrants.[NEWLINE][TAB]Zhao's methods in eastern Tibet uncannily prefigured the Communist policies nearly half a century later. They were aimed at the extermination of the Tibetan clergy, the assimilation of territory and repopulation of the Tibetan plateaus with poor peasants from Sichuan. Like the later Chinese conquerors, Zhao's men looted and destroyed Tibetan monasteries, melted down religious images and tore up sacred texts to use to line the soles of their boots and, as the Communists were also to do later, Zhao Erfeng worked out a comprehensive scheme for the redevelopment of Tibet that covered military training reclamation work, secular education, trade and administration."[NEWLINE][TAB]In 1910, the Qing government sent a military expedition of its own to establish direct Chinese rule. They deposed the 13th Dalai Lama in an imperial edict and instigated a search for a new incarnation.. The Dalai Lama then fled to British India in February 1910. While in India, the Dalai Lama became a close friend of Charles Alfred Bell, a British diplomatic officer stationed in Sikkim and a critic of Great Britain's policies in the region. "By going in and then coming out again, we knocked the Tibetans down and left them for the first comer to kick," wrote Bell later. The situation was soon to change, however, as, after the fall of the Qing dynasty in October 1911, Zhao's soldiers mutinied and beheaded him.[NEWLINE][TAB]The 13th Dalai Lama fled to British India in February 1910. The same month, the Chinese Qing government issued a proclamation deposing the Dalai Lama and instigating the search for a new incarnation.[NEWLINE][TAB]The official position of the British Government was it would not intervene between China and Tibet and would only recognize the de facto government of China within Tibet at this time. Bell, in his history of Tibet, wrote of this time that "the Tibetans were abandoned to Chinese aggression, an aggression for which the British Military Expedition to Lhasa and subsequent retreat [and consequent power vacuum within Tibet) were primarily responsible". Later, Britain defined the Indo-Tibetan border at the 1914 Simla Accord with the McMahon Line. China's delegation refused to agree to the line and still claims the land India received from Tibet as South Tibet, although the McMahon line remains the de facto border.[NEWLINE][TAB]In 1932, an agreement signed between Chinese warlord Liu Wenhui and Tibetan forces formalized the partition of Kham into two regions: Eastern Kham, which was administered by Chinese forces, and Western Kham, which was administered by Tibet. Eastern Kham subsequently became the actual area of control of China's Xikang province. The border between eastern and western Kham is the Yangtze River - Dri Chu in Tibetan and Jinsha Jiang, or Chang Jiang respectively, in Chinese.[NEWLINE][TAB]In 1950, following the defeat of the Kuomintang rulers of China by communist forces in the Chinese Civil War, the People's Liberation Army entered western Kham. Western Kham was then set up as a separate Qamdo Territory , then merged into Tibet Autonomous Region in 1965. Meanwhile, Xikang province, comprising eastern Kham, was merged into Sichuan province in 1955. The border between Sichuan and Tibet Autonomous Region has remained the Yangtze River. The northernmost region of Kham, Yushu, has been a part of Qinghai province since the 18th century.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_NUBIAN_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Arabs had taken Egypt in 641, and the jihad soon turned south. Makuria was one of the few states in the world to effectively resist Muslim conquest. Makurians defeated an Arab army at the First Battle of Dongola in in 642. They repeated this feat again in 652 at the Second Battle of Dongola. In both battles, Arab writers noted the Makurians skill with the bow.</English>
		<German>[TAB]Unter dem Namen Medjau (auch Medjai oder Medja) wurden im Alten Ägypten vom Ende des Alten bis zum Neuen Reich Menschen bezeichnet, die in der Nubischen Wüste, im Roten-Meer-Gebirge und westlich davon in Atbai lebten. Sie dienten den Ägyptern als Karawanenführer, Polizisten und Berufssoldaten. Die Medjau waren aber auch gefährliche Feinde. Historische Aufzeichnungen berichten von häufigen Auseinandersetzungen mit den Ägyptern.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTED_BRAVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The term "brave" simply means a Native American warrior. However, the term comes with good reason, as Native American warriors were renowned for their bravery and strong will. Although the braves originally used somewhat primitive weaponry, the Native Americans began to use guns when the Europeans arrived (which they generally traded for with furs, crops, or other things that would help the colonists survive). The Native Americans were also introduced to horses when the Spaniards arrived in the 16th century. The introduction of horses had the largest impact on the Plains Indians, which includes the Sioux. The Plains Indians used horses for trading, hunting, and raiding, among other things.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_INDONESIAN_ORANG_LAUT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Orang Laut, or Bajau Laut are a group of Malay people living in the Riau Islands of Indonesia. It also may refer to any Malay origin people living on coastal islands, including those of Andaman Sea islands in Thailand and Burma, commonly known as Moken.[PARAGRAPH:2]Historically, the orang laut were principally pirates but they also played important roles in Srivijaya, the Sultanate of Malacca, and the Sultanate of Johor. They patrolled the adjacent sea areas, repelling real pirates, directing traders to their employers' ports and maintaining those ports' dominance in the area.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_QIZILBASH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Qizilbash ("Crimson/Red Heads") is the label given to a wide variety of Shia Islamic militant groups that flourished in Anatolia and Kurdistan from the late 13th century onwards, some of which contributed to the foundation of the Safavid dynasty of Iran. The expression "Red Heads" is derived from their distinctive twelve gored crimson headwear, indicating their adherence to the twelve Ithna'ashari Imams and to Haydar Safavi, the spiritual leader (sheikh) of the Safaviyya movement. The Qizilbash were a coalition of many different peoples of predominantly (but not exclusively) Turkic-speaking Azerbaijani background, united in their adherence to the Safavid doctrine of Shiism.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MUGHAL_SIEGE_ELEPHANT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Siege Elephant is a war elephant with a swivel gun or small cannon mounted on top. While not particularly effective as artillery, it can certainly be intimidating!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SLAVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Slaves were depended workers, which used in the whole ancient world. Slaves were treat like things and were mostly prisoners of war or childrens of slaves. Slaves were used mostly in civil engineering and in the mines, which was one of the most dangeroust work in the ancient world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_POLISH_WINGED_HUSSAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first hussar units in the Kingdom of Poland were formed by the Sejm, the Polish Parliament, in 1503 which hired three banners of Hungarian mercenaries. Soon, recruitment also began among Polish and Lithuanian citizens. The Hussars proved vital to Poland because they were more maneuverable than the previously used lancers. But the reign of King Stefan Batory, the hussars formed the bulk of the Polish and Lithuanian cavalry. Over many years, hussars in Hungary became heavier. When Stefan Batory was elected king of Poland, he reorganized the Polish-Lithuanian hussars of his Royal Guard making them a heavy formation, and equipping lancers as their main weapon. These Polish 'heavy' hussars were known in their homeland as "husaria"[PARAGRAPH:2]With the Battle of Lubiszew in 1577, the "Golden Age" of the hussar began. Until the Battle of Vienna, Polish-Lithuanian hussars rarely lost in battle. Throughout many battles the Polish-Lithuanian hussars would prove to be an important factor against overwhelming odds.[PARAGRAPH:2]The primary battle tactic of the Polish-Lithuanian hussars was the charge. They also tended to repeat the charge until the enemy formation broke. The hussars fought with a long lance, a szabla, one or two pistols, and a carbine or arquebus, known in Polish as a "bandolet". Polish hussars were also famous for the wings they wore on their backs. According to some theories, they were designed to foil attacks by Tatar lassos, another theory being that the vibrating of feathers made a strange sound that frightened enemy horses. However, experiments carried out by re-enactors and movie-makers since the 1970s and more recently by Polish historians in 2001 contradict such ideas. Possibly the wings were worn only during parades and not during combat, but this explanation is also disputed.</English>
		<French>[TAB]La premi&#195;&#168;re hussarde unit&#195;&#169;s dans le Royaume de Pologne ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; form&#195;&#169;s par le Sejm, le Parlement polonais, en 1503, qui a engag&#195;&#169; trois banni&#195;&#168;res de mercenaires hongrois. Bient&#195;&#180;t, le recrutement a commenc&#195;&#169; entre les citoyens polonais et lituaniens. Les Hussards av&#195;&#169;r&#195;&#169;e vitale pour la Pologne, parce qu'ils &#195;&#169;taient plus manoeuvrable que les lanciers pr&#195;&#169;c&#195;&#169;demment utilis&#195;&#169;s. But le r&#195;&#168;gne du roi Stefan Batory, les hussards formaient le gros de la cavalerie polonaise et lituanienne. Depuis de nombreuses ann&#195;&#169;es, hussards en Hongrie est devenue plus lourde. Lorsque Stefan Batory est &#195;&#169;lu roi de Pologne, il a r&#195;&#169;organis&#195;&#169; le polonais-lituanien hussards de sa garde royale rendant une lourde formation et l'&#195;&#169;quipement des lanciers comme leur principale arme. Ces polonais "lourds" hussards &#195;&#169;taient connus dans leur pays comme "husaria"[PARAGRAPH:2]Avec la bataille de Lubiszew en 1577, l'&#195;&#162;ge d'or "de la hussarde a commenc&#195;&#169;. Jusqu'&#195;&#160; la bataille de Vienne, polonais-lituanien hussards rarement perdu dans la bataille. Tout au long de nombreuses batailles l'polonais-lituanien hussards se r&#195;&#169;v&#195;&#169;ler &#195;&#170;tre un important facteur &#195;&#169;crasante contre chances.[PARAGRAPH:2]La principale bataille tactique de la polonais-lituanien hussards a la charge. Ils ont &#195;&#169;galement tendance &#195;&#160; r&#195;&#169;p&#195;&#169;ter les frais jusqu'&#195;&#160; la formation ennemie a &#195;&#169;clat&#195;&#169;. Les hussards combattu avec une longue Lance, un szabla, un ou deux pistolets, et un mousqueton ou arquebuse, connue en polonais comme un "bandolet". Hussards polonais &#195;&#169;taient reconnus pour les ailes, ils portaient sur leur dos. Selon certaines th&#195;&#169;ories, mais ils ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; con&#195;&#167;us pour d&#195;&#169;jouer les attaques men&#195;&#169;es par des lassos tatare, une autre th&#195;&#169;orie est que la vibration de plumes fait une &#195;&#169;trange que le son ennemi effray&#195;&#169; les chevaux. Toutefois, les exp&#195;&#169;riences men&#195;&#169;es par la r&#195;&#169;orientation enactors et film d&#195;&#169;cideurs depuis les ann&#195;&#169;es 1970 et, plus r&#195;&#169;cemment, par les historiens polonais en 2001 contredisent de telles id&#195;&#169;es. Eventuellement les ailes ont &#195;&#169;t&#195;&#169; port&#195;&#169;es seulement pendant les parades et non pas pendant le combat, mais cette explication est &#195;&#169;galement contest&#195;&#169;.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Unter ungarischem Einfluss fanden die Husaren zunächst als leichte Kavallerie Eingang in das polnische Heer. Der Wandel zur schweren Reiterei, die das mittelalterliche Ritteraufgebot ersetzte, fand Ende des 16. Jahrhunderts unter König Stefan Batory seinen vorläufigen Abschluss. Die gepanzerten polnischen Flügelhusaren (Hussaria) trugen Brustpanzer, Armschienen und kniehohe Lederstiefel. Der Name geht auf die zwei am Rückenpanzer befestigten großen Flügelstangen zurück, die bis zu einem Meter über dem Kopf aufragten. Sie sollten die galoppierenden Husaren durch ihr Rauschen und Aussehen besonders furchteinflößend erscheinen lassen. Außerdem schützten sie den Rücken vor Säbelhieben und wehrten die von den feindlichen Tataren verwendeten Fanglassos ab. Mit der Lanze als Hauptwaffe ausgerüstet, trugen die Flügelhusaren ihre Attacken in geschlossener Formation vor. Neben dieser schweren Schlachtenkavallerie hielten sich, in Ungarn wie in Polen, leicht bewaffnete Husaren als Aufklärungstruppe. Deren Taktik und Ausrüstung wurden seit Beginn des 17. Jahrhunderts europaweit kopiert.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Husaren waren in Fähnlein (poln. Choragwie) von 210 Reitern eingeteilt. Die Aufstellung erfolgte überwiegend dreigliedrig, wobei das erste Glied von den Adligen (Towarzysz) und das zweite Glied von seinen Knappen (Pacholek), die ebenfalls aus dem niedrigen Adel stammten, besetzt war. Jede Einheit wurde von einem Rittmeister (Rotmistrz) im Range eines Oberst und seinem Stellvertreter (Porucznik) geführt. Weiter hatte jede Einheit eine Choragiew-Fahne, zwei Pauker und zwei Trompeter. Nur der König führte einen Roßschweif gekrönt von einem Falkenflügel. Hochadlige Anführer durften als Auszeichnung einen Roßschweif ohne Falkenflügel führen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La prima unit&#195;&#160; ussaro nel Regno di Polonia si sono formati dal Sejm, il parlamento polacco, nel 1503, che noleggiati tre bandiere ungheresi di mercenari. Presto, ha iniziato il reclutamento anche tra i cittadini polacchi e lituani. Il Ussari rivelato fondamentale per la Polonia perch&#195;&#169; erano pi&#195;&#185; manovrabile da quella usata in precedenza lance. Ma il regno di Stefan Batory, la ussari formata la maggior parte della cavalleria polacco e lituano. Nel corso di molti anni, ussari in Ungheria &#195;&#168; diventata pi&#195;&#185; pesante. Stefan Batory, quando &#195;&#168; stato eletto re di Polonia, ha riorganizzato il Polacco-Lituana ussari del suo Royal Guard rendendoli un pesante formazione, e di dotare le lance come loro principale arma. Questi polacco 'pesanti' ussari erano conosciuti in patria come "husaria"[PARAGRAPH:2]Con la Battaglia di Lubiszew nel 1577, il "Golden Age" del ussaro iniziato. Fino alla battaglia di Vienna, polacco - lituano ussari raramente perso in battaglia. In molti battaglie polacco - lituano ussari sarebbe rivelato un fattore importante contro la stragrande quota.[PARAGRAPH:2]La principale battaglia tattica del Polacco-Lituana ussari era l'accusa. Essi hanno anche la tendenza a ripetere la carica fino a quando il nemico formazione rotto. Il ussari combattuto con una lunga lancia, un szabla, uno o due pistole, e di una carabina o arquebus, in polacco noto come "bandolet". Ussari polacchi sono stati anche famosa per le ali che indossavano sulle loro spalle. Secondo alcune teorie, che sono stati progettati per sventare attacchi da Tataro lassos, un'altra teoria &#195;&#168; che la vibrazione di piume fatto uno strano suono che spaventati nemico cavalli. Tuttavia, gli esperimenti effettuati da ristabilire enactors movie e responsabili dal 1970 e, pi&#195;&#185; recentemente, dal polacco storici nel 2001 in contrasto con tali idee. Eventualmente, le ali sono stati indossati solo durante parate, e non durante il combattimento, ma questa spiegazione &#195;&#168; anche contestato.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La primera hussar unidades en el Reino de Polonia se formaron por el Sejm, el Parlamento polaco, en 1503, que contrat&#195;&#179; a tres pancartas h&#195;&#186;ngaro de los mercenarios. En breve, tambi&#195;&#169;n se inici&#195;&#179; la contrataci&#195;&#179;n entre los ciudadanos polacos y lituanos. El Hussars result&#195;&#179; vital para Polonia, ya que fueron m&#195;&#161;s maniobrable que los utilizados anteriormente lancers. But el reinado del rey Stefan Batory, la hussars forman el grueso de la caballer&#195;&#173;a polaco y lituano. Durante muchos a&#195;&#177;os, hussars en Hungr&#195;&#173;a se convirti&#195;&#179; en m&#195;&#161;s pesadas. Cuando Stefan Batory fue elegido rey de Polonia, se reorganiz&#195;&#179; el polaco - lituano hussars de su Guardia Real convierten en una pesada formaci&#195;&#179;n, y el equipamiento lancers como su principal arma. Estos polaco 'pesadas' hussars eran conocidos en su tierra natal como "husaria"[PARAGRAPH:2]Con la Batalla de Lubiszew en 1577, la "Edad de Oro" de la hussar comenz&#195;&#179;. Hasta la Batalla de Viena, polaco, lituano hussars rara vez perdi&#195;&#179; en la batalla. Muchas batallas en todo el polaco - lituano hussars resultar&#195;&#173;a ser un factor importante en contra de enormes dificultades.[PARAGRAPH:2]La principal batalla de la t&#195;&#161;ctica polaca y lituana hussars era el cargo. Tambi&#195;&#169;n tienden a repetir el cargo hasta que el enemigo rompi&#195;&#179; la formaci&#195;&#179;n. El hussars luch&#195;&#179; con una larga lanza, un szabla, una o dos pistolas, y una carabina o arquebus, conocido en Polonia como una "bandolet". Polish hussars tambi&#195;&#169;n famoso por las alas que llevaban en sus espaldas. Seg&#195;&#186;n algunas teor&#195;&#173;as, que estaban dise&#195;&#177;adas para frustrar los ataques de t&#195;&#161;rtaro lassos, otra teor&#195;&#173;a es que la vibraci&#195;&#179;n de plumas hizo un extra&#195;&#177;o sonido que asustados caballos enemigo. Sin embargo, los experimentos llevados a cabo por volver a enactors y de la pel&#195;&#173;cula de la formulaci&#195;&#179;n desde el decenio de 1970 y m&#195;&#161;s recientemente por historiadores de Polonia en 2001 contradice esas ideas. Posiblemente las alas se usaron s&#195;&#179;lo durante los desfiles y no durante el combate, pero esta explicaci&#195;&#179;n es tambi&#195;&#169;n controvertida.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FRENCH_HEAVY_CANNON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A culverin was a relatively simple ancestor of the musket, and later a medieval cannon, adapted for use by the French in the 15th century, and later adapted for naval use by the English in the late 16th century. The culverin was used to bombard targets from a distance. The weapon had a relatively long barrel and a light construction. The culverin fired solid round shot projectiles with a high muzzle velocity, producing a relatively long range and flat trajectory. Round shot refers to the classic solid spherical cannonball.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOORISH_CAMEL_GUNNER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Probably developed by Egyptian warriors who originally mounted large crossbows on the camels, the Camel Gunner was rapidly adopted by Arab, Afghan, Indian and especially Persian Safavid armies. Camel Gunners were one of the royal guard units in the 19th-century Persian army. A Persian Camel Gunner regiment would be accompanied by musicians with huge camel-mounted drums, in order to create even more noise and impress the enemy. Camel Gunners were used against the invading British in the Anglo-Afghan Wars and in the Anglo-Sikh Wars.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOHAWK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Mohican Rifler represents the warriors of the five nations that took up arms during the French and Indian Wars and sided with the British. Made famous in Cooper's novel "Last of the Mohicans," these warriors were legendary for there forced marches through wilderness and combat skills in North America's thick forests. Regiments of Mohawk Riflers supplemented the British garrisons at Forts Owens and William Henry during the war. </English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HULUGANNI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Hittites were renowned charioteers. They developed a new chariot design that had lighter wheels, with four spokes rather than eight. It could hold 3 warriors as the wheel was placed in the middle of the chariot and not at the back as in the Egyptian chariots. Fast, powerful and dangerous, they were used to great effect against the enemies of the Hittites. The Battle of Kadesh in 1299 BCE between Hatti and Egypt is likely to have been the largest chariot battle ever fought, involving some five thousand chariots.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEDJAY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Medjay were a nomadic desert people from the northern regions of Nubia, reknown for their skill with the bow.  Over time they were incorporated into the armies of both Nubia and Egypt as mercenaries where they served as garrison troops and patrolled the deserts as a kind of gendarmerie. By the 18th Dynasty of the New Kingdom the Medjay were an elite paramilitary police force. No longer did the term refer to an ethnic group and over time the new meaning became synonymous with the policing occupation in general.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ASVAKA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Asvakas or Asvakayanas, classically called the Assacenii/Assacani, is the Sanskrit name of a people who supposedly lived in northeastern Afghanistan and the Peshawar Valley. They are/were believed to be a sub-group of the Greater Kamboja tribe profusely referenced in ancient Sanskrit/Pali literature and were partitioned into eastern and western Asvakas. They find mention in the Puranas, Mahabharata and numerous other ancient Sanskrit and Pali texts. Today, their descendants are mostly heterogeneous people.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Sanskrit term asva, Iranian aspa and Prakrit assa means horse. The name Asvaka/Asvakan or Assaka is said to be derived from Sanskrit Asva or Prakrit Assa and it literally denotes someone connected with the horses-hence: a horseman, or a cavalryman or "breeder of horses". The Asvakas were especially engaged in the occupation of breeding, raising and training war horses, as also in providing expert cavalry services to outside nations, hence they also constituted an excellent class of Kshatriyas (warriors). Like tribal term Kamboja, the tribal term Asvaka is also interpreted as land or home of horses.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ITALY_BERSAGLIERE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Bersaglieri (Marksmen in English) are a corps of the Italian Army originally created by General Alessandro La Marmora on 18 June 1836 to serve in the Piedmontese Army, later to become the Royal Italian Army. They have always been a high-mobility light infantry unit, and can still be recognized by the distinctive wide brimmed hat that they wear (only in dress uniform in modern times), decorated with black capercaillie feathers. The feathers are usually applied to their combat helmets. Another distinctive trait of the Bersaglieri is the fast jog pace they keep on parades, instead of marching.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FARARI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>By the time Ibn Battuta visited the Mali Empire during the reign of Mansa Suleyman, an elite corps among the military was present at court. These men were an outgrowth of the ton-tigui that had fought alongside Sundjata and his immediate predecessors known as the farari ("braves"). Each farariya ("brave") was a cavalry commander with officers and warriors beneath him. However, the roles of the farariya were not all identical. Farari served as ton-tigi of the Gbara, governors of far off provinces or simply field commanders. Many forms of the farariya titles would be used by Mali's successor states such as Songhay.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LEVY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Under the feudal conditions for holding land in the medieval period, most peasants and freemen were liable to provide one man of suitable age per family for military duty when required by either the king or the local lord. The levies raised in this way fought as infantry under local superiors. Although the exact laws varied greatly depending on the country and the period, generally these levies were only obliged to fight for one to three months. Most were subsistence farmers, and it was in everyone's interest to send the men home for harvest-time.[PARAGRAPH:1]The bulk of the Anglo-Saxon English army, called the fyrd, was composed of part-time English soldiers drawn from the landowning minor nobility. These thegns were the land-holding aristocracy of the time and were required to serve with their own armour and weapons for a certain number of days each year. The historian David Sturdy has cautioned about regarding the fyrd as a precursor to a modern national army composed of all ranks of society, describing it as a "ridiculous fantasy":[PARAGRAPH:1]The persistent old belief that peasants and small farmers gathered to form a national army or fyrd is a strange delusion dreamt up by antiquarians in the late eighteenth or early nineteenth centuries to justify universal military conscription.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KONGO_POMBOS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The pombos was an elite scouting unit deployed by the Kingdom of Kongo and other surrounding kingdoms. The pombos wer so trained that they at times ran with, and kept up with, horses in the region. The pombos also performed pursuit duties. Such as most light troops of the area, the pombos would have relied more on individual skill and technicue (such as dodging spear and arrows etc.) than heavy shields and strong defensive weapons.[PARAGRAPH:1]The light and agile pombos worked well with the battle formations used by local kingdoms. Kongo region battle formations were in relatively open order. This allowed the peculiar dodging, twisting and leaping noted in Portuguese accounts as warriors tried to avoid arrows and spears delivered by their opponents. A battle generally opened with a brief volley of arrows from relatively weak bows. Indeed the bravest soldiers went into battle with only a few arrows, which were poisoned in some cases by a potent mixture called cabanzo. Once these were released, the contenders closed for a decision by hand-to-hand combat. Several thousand men could take place in these set-piece battles, and the affair was usually decided by superior skill and aggression. Basic formations were known, and three divisions were sometimes used- a center and two wings. A complex system of drums, horns and signals aided in maneuver of the warrior hosts, and distinctive battle-flags and pennants identified the location of elite troops or their commanders.[PARAGRAPH:1]In regional armies, Outflanking moves were popular, with light troops keeping the enemy busy in the center, while the wings extended. In some cases, a reserve force was kept on hand to exploit success, strike at a vulnerable point, or provide a rear guard to cover retreats. Reserve forces were also used as intimidating "stiffeners," forcing the cowardly and faltering back into the battle-line. Portuguese mercenaries sometimes excelled in this role while employed by the Kongo warlords. A Ndongo army attacked the Portuguese at Talandongo in 1583 using this 3-part division, as did the Portuguese force that confronted it. Nzinga also successfully used an outflanking gambit against the Portuguese, breaking their right wing at Cavanga, but saw defeat when her forces paused to loot, and exposed themselves to counterattack.[PARAGRAPH:1]A broken army was usually hard to rally, and often did not reform on the battlefield but melted back to their home villages, to be perhaps reconstituted days later. Once regrouped and rearmed however they could be dangerous, as a defeated Portuguese column found in 1670 at Kitombo. Siege warfare was not highly developed, and most fortified places were only designed to hold out a short period before defenders retreated. Logistical problems plagued both attacker and defender, as the region's war cycle was not set for long campaigns.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>