<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Civ4GameText>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_ATG_CIVIC_TITLE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The "Title" civic is a game mechanic that is used to track Alexander's legendary status. As the unit Alexander is attached to gains levels, Alexander will gain better "Titles." The better Alexander's "Title", the easier it will be to rule a large nation.[PARAGRAPH:1]If the unit Alexander is attached to should ever die, Alexander's "Title" will revert back the worst title until Alexander has healed from his wounds and is reattached to a unit.</English>
  <French>[TAB]La doctrine "Titre" est un m&#233;canisme du jeu utilis&#233; pour suivre l'&#233;volution l&#233;gendaire d'Alexandre. A mesure que l'unit&#233; &#224; laquelle est rattach&#233; Alexandre monte de niveau, Alexandre obtient de nouveaux "titres". Plus ce "titre" est prestigieux, plus il lui sera facile de r&#233;gner sur une grande nation.[PARAGRAPH:1]Si l'unit&#233; &#224; laquelle est rattach&#233; Alexandre meurt, le "titre" d'Alexandre redevient alors le moins prestigieux de tous jusqu'&#224; ce qu'Alexandre se remette de ses blessures et soit rattach&#233; &#224; une unit&#233;.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Die Staatsform "Titel" dient zur &#220;berpr&#252;fung des aktuellen geschichtlichen Status von Alexander. Mit jedem Stufenanstieg erwirbt die Einheit Alexander einen h&#246;herwertigen "Titel". Und je h&#246;her Alexanders "Titel" ist, desto leichter f&#228;llt ihm die Regentschaft &#252;ber ein gro&#223;es Reich.[PARAGRAPH:1]Sollte die mit Alexander verkn&#252;pfte Einheit sterben, erh&#228;lt Alexander zun&#228;chst wieder den geringsten Titel, bis er von seinen Verwundungen genesen ist und mit einer anderen Einheit verkn&#252;pft wird.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il "titolo" &#232; una meccanica di gioco che viene utilizzata per ricreare la leggenda di Alessandro. L'unit&#224; di supporto continua a conquistare esperienza, mentre Alessandro ricever&#224; "titoli" pi&#249; importanti. Migliore &#232; il "titolo" di Alessandro, pi&#249; facile sar&#224; governare una grande nazione.[PARAGRAPH:1]Se l'unit&#224; alla quale &#232; unito Alessandro viene completamente distrutta, il "titolo" verr&#224; retrocesso al peggiore fino a quando non si sar&#224; curato le ferite e unito a un'altra unit&#224;.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El principio "T&#237;tulo" es una mec&#225;nica de juego que se utiliza para indicar la posici&#243;n alcanzada por el legendario Alejandro. A medida que la unidad a la que acompa&#241;e obtenga niveles, Alejandro alcanzar&#225; un mejor "T&#237;tulo" y le resultar&#225; m&#225;s f&#225;cil gobernar una gran naci&#243;n.[PARAGRAPH:1]Si la unidad a la que acompa&#241;a muere, el "T&#237;tulo" de Alejandro volver&#225; a ser el peor posible hasta que se recupere de sus heridas y vuelva a unirse a una unidad.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ABSOLUTISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Absolute monarchy (or simply absolutism) is a monarchical form of government where the monarch has the power to rule his or her land or country and its citizens freely, with no laws or legally-organized direct opposition in force. Although some religious authority may be able to discourage the monarch from some acts and the sovereign is expected to act according to custom, in an absolute monarchy there is no constitution or body of law above what is decreed by the sovereign (king or queen). As a theory of civics, absolute monarchy puts total trust in well-bred and well-trained monarchs raised for the role from birth.[PARAGRAPH:2]The theory of absolute monarchy developed in the late Middle Ages from feudalism, during which a monarch was still very much the "first among equals" (primes inter pares) among the nobility. With the creation of centralized administrations and standing armies backed by expensive artillery, the power of the monarch gradually increased relative to that of the nobles (whose military power had declined with the effectiveness of heavy cavalry), and from this was created the theory of absolute monarchy.[PARAGRAPH:2]In theory, an absolute monarch has total power over his or her people and land, including the aristocracy and sometimes the clergy (see caesaropapism). In practice, absolute monarchs have often found their power limited - generally by one or other of those groups.[PARAGRAPH:2]Some monarchies (for example the German Empire, 1871-1918) have powerless or symbolic parliaments and other governmental bodies that the monarch can alter or dissolve at will. Despite effectively being absolute monarchies, they are technically constitutional monarchies due to the existence of a constitution and national canon of law.[PARAGRAPH:2]The popularity of the notion of absolute monarchy declined substantially after the French Revolution and American Revolution, which promoted theories of government based on popular sovereignty. Among the few states that retain a rather absolute monarchy are Bhutan, Brunei, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Swaziland, and the Vatican City (the papal city-state, a theocractic elective monarchy).</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_AGRARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Agrarianism has two common meanings. The first meaning refers to a social philosophy or political philosophy which values rural society as superior to urban society, the independent farmer as superior to the paid worker, and sees farming as a way of life that can shape the ideal social values. It stresses the superiority of a simpler rural life as opposed to the complexity of city life, with its banks and factories. The American Thomas Jefferson was a representative agrarian who built Jeffersonian Democracy around the notion that farmers are "the most valuable citizens" and the truest republicans.[PARAGRAPH:2]The philosophical roots of agrarianism include European and Chinese philosophers. The Chinese School of Agrarianism was a philosophy that advocated peasant utopian communalism and egalitarianism. This influenced European intellectuals like Fran&#231;ois Quesnay, an avid Confucianist and advocate of China's agrarian policies, forming the French agrarian philosophy of Physiocracy. The Physiocrats, along with the ideas of John Locke and the Romantic Era, formed the basis of modern European and American agrarianism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Secondly, the term "agrarianism" means political proposals for land redistribution, specifically the distribution of land from the rich to the poor or landless. This terminology is common in many countries, and originated from the "Lex Sempronia Agraria" or "agrarian laws" of Rome in 133 BC, imposed by Tiberius Gracchus, that seized the lands of the rich and distributed them to the poor. This definition of agrarianism is commonly known as "agrarian reform".[PARAGRAPH:2]In societies influenced by Confucianism, the farmer was considered an esteemed productive member of society, whereas merchants who made money were looked down upon. In eighteenth- and nineteenth-century England, the word identified any land reform movement that sought to redistribute cultivated lands equally. Today, the word has largely shed this radical political meaning. Instead, agrarianism points to a collection of political, philosophical, and literary ideas that together tend to describe farm life in ideal terms.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ANIMISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Animism (from Latin anima "soul, life") is a set of beliefs based on the existence of non-human "spiritual beings" or similar kinds of embodied principles.[PARAGRAPH:2]Animism encompasses the beliefs that there is no separation between the spiritual and physical (or material) world, and souls or spirits exist, not only in humans, but also in all other animals, plants, rocks, geographic features such as mountains or rivers, or other entities of the natural environment. Animism may further attribute souls to abstract concepts such as words, true names, or metaphors in mythology. Examples of Animism can be found in forms of Shinto, Serer, Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, Pantheism, Paganism, and Neopaganism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Throughout European history, philosophers such as Aristotle and Thomas Aquinas, among others, contemplated the possibility that souls exist in animals, plants, and people; however, the currently accepted definition of animism was only developed in the 19th century by Sir Edward Tylor, who created it as "one of anthropology's earliest concepts, if not the first".[PARAGRAPH:2]According to the anthropologist Tim Ingold, animism shares similarities to totemism but differs in its focus on individual spirit beings which help to perpetuate life, whereas totemism more typically holds that there is a primary source, such as the land itself or the ancestors, who provide the basis to life. Certain indigenous religious groups such as the Australian Aborigines are more typically totemic, whereas others like the Inuit are more typically animistic in their worldview.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_AUTOCRACY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]An Autocracy is a system of government in which a supreme political power is concentrated in the hands of one person, whose decisions are subject to neither external legal restraints nor regularized mechanisms of popular control (except perhaps for the implicit threat of coup d'&#233;tat or mass insurrection).[PARAGRAPH:2]Autocracy is any form of government in which one person is the supreme power within the state. It is derived from the Greek "auto" ("self") and "kratos" ("rule"), and may be translated as "one who rules by himself". It is distinct from oligarchy ("rule by the few") and democracy ("rule by the people"). Like "despot", "tyrant", "strongman" and "dictator", "autocrat" has become a loaded word with a negative value judgment in contemporary English usage.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term autokrator is employed in antiquity to translate the Latin imperator into Greek. It was the primary word used by grecophones to the Roman Emperor during the later Roman Empire through the seventh century AD and continued to be used in the Byzantine period, although it lost favor to Sebastos ("augustus") and Basileus (obscure: prob. "chieftain;" later "king") as synonyms for "emperor". This use remains current in the modern Greek language, where the term is used for anyone holding the title "emperor," regardless of the actual power of the monarch.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_BARBARISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Barbarism is the most primitive legal system. Under barbarism, the strong take what they want from the weak: their money, possessions, even spouses and children. Disputes are settled by combat; might is right.[PARAGRAPH:2]There is little positive to say about barbarism, except perhaps that it cuts way back on red tape. It does not support a legal class that can complicate and obfuscate the law to ensure job security.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le barbarisme est le syst&#232;me judiciaire le plus primitif. Avec le barbarisme, le plus fort prend ce qu'il veut aux plus faibles : leur argent, leurs biens et m&#234;me leur &#233;pouse et leurs enfants. Les disputes se r&#232;glent avec les mains, c'est la loi du plus fort.[PARAGRAPH:2]Les points positifs du barbarisme sont plut&#244;t rares, si ce n'est peut-&#234;tre l'absence de bureaucratie. Il ne supporte pas l'existence d'une classe judiciaire qui complique et trafique la loi pour s'assurer la s&#233;curit&#233; de l'emploi.</French>
  <German>[TAB]In primitiven Rechtssystemen, wie der Barbarei, herrscht das Recht des St&#228;rkeren. Dieser nimmt dem Schwachen dessen Geld, seinen Besitz, ja sogar Frau und Kinder. Streitigkeiten werden gewaltsam beigelegt.[PARAGRAPH:2]&#220;ber die Barbarei l&#228;sst sich nur wenig Positives sagen. Sie kennt weder eine B&#252;rokratie noch eine unabh&#228;ngige Gerichtsbarkeit.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il barbarismo &#232; il sistema legale pi&#249; primitivo. Nel barbarismo, il pi&#249; forte prende ci&#242; che vuole dal pi&#249; debole: soldi, possedimenti, persino spose e figli. Le dispute sono risolte con il combattimento, la ragione &#232; dalla parte del pi&#249; forte.[PARAGRAPH:2]Non ci sono molti aspetti positivi nel barbarismo, se non che la burocrazia &#232; azzerata, poich&#233; non &#232; contemplata una classe di legislatori che possano complicare e offuscare la sicurezza del lavoro.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La barbarie es el sistema legal m&#225;s primitivo. En ella, el fuerte le arrebata lo que desea al d&#233;bil: su dinero, sus posesiones e incluso sus esposas e hijos. Las disputas se resuelven con combates; poder equivale a derecho.[PARAGRAPH:2]No se pueden decir demasiadas cosas buenas sobre la barbarie, salvo quiz&#225; que limita la burocracia. No requiere de una clase legal, cuya tendencia natural es complicar y oscurecer la ley para asegurarse el puesto de trabajo.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_BUREAUCRACY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Bureaucracy is a form of government in which a professional class manages the day to day operations of the government. They collect the taxes. They build the roads. They turn the ruler's wishes into actuality. The Chinese mandarins are an early example of a bureaucracy; the motor vehicle agency of your local government is a later example.[PARAGRAPH:2]Bureaucracies provide a certain amount of stability and competence to a government, ensuring that the government will continue to operate efficiently even if the old ruler is thrown out and a new and totally inexperienced ruler takes his or her place. Over time, though, a bureaucracy may become "entrenched" - growing in size and inefficiency to the point where it is extremely difficult for a leader to accomplish anything - good or ill.</English>
  <French>[TAB]La bureaucratie est une forme de gouvernement par laquelle une classe de professionnels dirige les op&#233;rations quotidiennes du gouvernement. Ils collectent les imp&#244;ts, construisent les routes et mettent en oeuvre les souhaits des dirigeants. Les mandarins chinois sont un des premiers exemples de bureaucratie. Les Directions R&#233;gionales du Commerce Ext&#233;rieur en sont un autre, plus r&#233;cent.[PARAGRAPH:2]La bureaucratie assure une certaine stabilit&#233; du pouvoir et met des comp&#233;tences au service des gouvernements. Ainsi, m&#234;me lorsqu'un dirigeant inexp&#233;riment&#233; arrive au pouvoir, le gouvernement continue de fonctionner avec une certaine efficacit&#233;. Cependant, la bureaucratie a tendance &#224; prolif&#233;rer et &#224; perdre en efficacit&#233;, au point de paralyser quelque peu le pouvoir et de l'emp&#234;cher de r&#233;aliser quoi que ce soit.</French>
  <German>[TAB]In einer B&#252;rokratie lenken Beamte im Namen eines Herrschers die Geschicke der Regierung. Sie erheben Steuern, bauen Stra&#223;en und setzen die Vorstellungen des Herrschers in die Tat um. Der chinesische Mandarin ist ebenso ein typischer Vertreter einer B&#252;rokratie, wie das Verkehrsamt einer Kommunalregierung.[PARAGRAPH:2]Eine B&#252;rokratie garantiert die Stabilit&#228;t und Kontinuit&#228;t einer Regierung und erm&#246;glicht auch nach deren Absetzung eine Fortsetzung der Regierungsgesch&#228;fte. Wird der b&#252;rokratische Apparat eines Landes zu gro&#223;, kann dies im Extremfall die v&#246;llige Handlungsunf&#228;higkeit des Staatsoberhauptes nach sich ziehen.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La burocrazia &#232; una forma di gestione politica nella quale una classe di professionisti gestisce le operazioni quotidiane di un governo: si possono costruire strade, riscuotere le tasse, realizzare i desideri del proprio governante. I Mandarini Cinesi sono uno dei primi esempi di burocrazia; la motorizzazione civile delle nostre nazioni &#232; l'esempio della burocrazia odierna.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le burocrazie garantiscono la stabilit&#224; e la competenza di un governo, assicurandone il funzionamento efficiente persino nella successione tra un vecchio leader in favore di uno nuovo totalmente inesperto. Nel corso del tempo, la burocrazia pu&#242; trasformarsi in una "trincea": con l'espansione della burocrazia, infatti, aumenta di conseguenza l'inefficienza del sistema al punto che, per un leader, diventa impossibile compiere qualsiasi azione, nel bene e nel male.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La burocracia es una forma de gobierno en la que una clase profesional administra las tareas cotidianas del gobierno. Recauda los impuestos. Construye las carreteras. Convierte los deseos del gobernante en realidad. Los mandarines chinos representan un ejemplo antiguo de burocracia; el departamento de tr&#225;fico de cualquier municipio es un ejemplo m&#225;s moderno.[PARAGRAPH:2]La burocracia proporciona ciertas dosis de estabilidad y competencia a los gobiernos, y garantiza que contin&#250;en funcionando con eficacia aun cuando el gobernante es expulsado y reemplazado por alguien totalmente inexperto en las tareas de gobierno. Con el tiempo, tiende a "atrincherarse", esto es, a crecer y atrofiarse, hasta el punto de que los gobernantes acaban por tener dificultades para implantar cualquier medida, sea buena o mala.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CAPITALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Capitalism is an economic system that is based on private ownership of the means of production and the creation of goods or services for profit. Competitive markets, wage labor, capital accumulation, voluntary exchange, and personal finance are also considered capitalistic. Competitive markets, capital accumulation, voluntary exchange, and personal finance may be parts of capitalism, however in practice there are never pure capitalist economies. Often, other non-capitalist systems such as market socialism and worker cooperatives retain aspects of capitalism. There are multiple variants of capitalism, including laissez-faire and state capitalism. Capitalism is considered to have been applied in a variety of historical cases, varying in time, geography, politics, and culture. There is general agreement that capitalism became dominant in the Western world following the demise of feudalism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Economists, political economists and historians have taken different perspectives on the analysis of capitalism. Economists usually emphasize the degree to which government does not have control over markets (laissez faire), as well as the importance of property rights. Most political economists emphasize private property as well, in addition to power relations, wage labor, class, and the uniqueness of capitalism as a historical formation. The extent to which different markets are free, as well as the rules defining private property, is a matter of politics and policy. Many states have what are termed mixed economies, referring to the varying degree of planned and market-driven elements in a state's economic system. A number of political ideologies have emerged in support of various types of capitalism, the most prominent being economic liberalism.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term capitalism gradually spread throughout the Western world in the 19th and 20th centuries largely through the writings of Karl Marx. However, it is the default economic system and it has its roots tracing back to the beginning of recorded history.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CASTE_SYSTEM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The caste system is one where one's parentage determines one's place in society. If your parents are street-cleaners, then so are you. If your parents are merchants, that's what you are. If your parents are nobility, then you are as well. Your status is determined at birth, and there's nothing you can do to better it. One may advance within one's caste, but that's as far as it goes. Marriages between castes are taboo.[PARAGRAPH:2]There is little advantage to the caste system, except to the people whose parents are on the top of the heap. Merit and initiative are useless: if the most intelligent and wise person in the culture happens to be born a street-cleaner, then he'll be an intelligent and wise street-cleaner. He'll never have a chance to become a priest, philosopher, or leader.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Dans un syst&#232;me de castes, la parent&#233; d&#233;termine la position de chacun au sein de la soci&#233;t&#233;. Si vos parents &#233;taient des &#233;boueurs, vous serez donc &#233;boueur, s'ils &#233;taient marchands, vous le serez aussi. Votre position sociale est d&#233;termin&#233;e &#224; la naissance, et vous ne pouvez absolument rien y changer. Vous pourrez progresser au sein de votre caste, mais jamais passer dans une caste sup&#233;rieure. Les mariages inter-castes sont tabous.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le syst&#232;me des castes n'a que peu d'avantages, si ce n'est pour les gens dont les parents sont en haut de la hi&#233;rarchie sociale. Le m&#233;rite et l'initiative ne sont pas r&#233;compens&#233;s : une personne intelligente et sage qui est n&#233;e &#233;boueur, ne sera jamais qu'un &#233;boueur intelligent et sage. Il ne deviendra jamais pr&#234;tre, philosophe ou dirigeant politique.</French>
  <German>[TAB]In Kastensystemen bestimmt die Herkunft den Platz eines Menschen innerhalb der Gesellschaft. Sind die Eltern eines Kindes Stra&#223;enkehrer, wird auch das Kind ein Stra&#223;enkehrer. Sind sie Mechaniker, wird auch das Kind Mechaniker. Da der Status eines Menschen bereits bei dessen Geburt festgelegt wird, kann er nichts tun, um diesen zu verbessern. Lediglich Fortschritte innerhalb der eigenen Kaste sind m&#246;glich. Die Ehe mit einem Mitglied einer anderen Kaste ist tabu.[PARAGRAPH:2]Das Kastensystem ist nur f&#252;r Angeh&#246;rige der oberen Kasten von Vorteil. Leistung und Eigeninitiative sind ohne Bedeutung. Wird der kl&#252;gste und weiseste Mensch des Landes als Stra&#223;enkehrer geboren, wird aus ihm ein kluger und weiser Stra&#223;enkehrer, niemals aber ein Priester, Philosoph oder Staatsoberhaupt. </German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La casta &#232; un sistema nel quale la propria posizione sociale &#232; determinata dalla discendenza. Se i tuoi genitori sono degli spazzini, mercanti o nobili, lo sei anche tu. Il tuo stato sociale &#232; determinato alla nascita e non c'&#232; nulla che si possa fare per cambiarlo; si pu&#242; migliorare la propria posizione all'interno della casta e i matrimoni tra caste differenti sono vietati.[PARAGRAPH:2]Non ci sono molti vantaggi in un sistema a caste, tranne per coloro i cui genitori sono in cima alla piramide. Il merito e l'iniziativa sono inutili: se una persona intelligente e saggia nasce spazzino, sar&#224; uno spazzino saggio e intelligente; non avr&#224; mai la possibilit&#224; di diventare un sacerdote, un filosofo o un leader.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]En el sistema de castas, lo que determina el lugar que uno ocupa en la sociedad es su nacimiento.  Si tus padres son barrenderos, t&#250; tambi&#233;n. Si tus padres son mercaderes, eso ser&#225;s t&#250;. Si tus padres son nobles, noble eres t&#250; tambi&#233;n. El estatus personal se determina en el momento del nacimiento y no se puede hacer nada por modificarlo. Uno puede avanzar en el seno de su propia casta, pero nada m&#225;s. Los matrimonios entre diferentes castas est&#225;n prohibidos.[PARAGRAPH:2]Este sistema no posee apenas ventajas, salvo para los que pertenecen a la casta superior. Los m&#233;ritos y la capacidad no sirven de nada: si la persona m&#225;s inteligente y sabia del mundo tiene la desgracia de nacer en una familia de barrenderos, ser&#225; un inteligente y sabio barrendero. Nunca podr&#225; llegar a ser sacerdote, fil&#243;sofo o gobernante.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CENTRAL_PLANING_PRODUCTION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>+1[ICON_PRODUCTION]</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CENTRAL_PLANNING_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Central planning represents an economy completely controlled, owned and planned by the government, otherwise known as state capitalism. Under a centrally planned economy, all labor, capital, production, agriculture, utilities, and finances are run by the government, and all service businesses are owned by the government. Because there are no private companies, no trade exists. Centrally planned economies are able to concentrate their resources on major projects such as world wonders and world projects, but are very costly to maintain.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CITY_STATES_HELP_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>+1[ICON_FOOD]</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_CITY_STATES_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A city-state is an independent or autonomous entity whose territory consists of a city which is not administered as a part of another local government. A city-state can also be defined as a central city and its surrounding villages, which together follow the same law, have one form of government, and share languages, religious beliefs, and ways of life. Today, only three independent, sovereign city-states exist: Monaco, Singapore, and the Vatican City.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_COMMONWEALTH_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The English noun "Commonwealth" originally dates from the fifteenth century. The term literally meant "common well-being". Thus commonwealth originally meant a state governed for the common good as opposed to an authoritarian state governed for the benefit of a given class of owners.[PARAGRAPH:2]Today the term is more general and means a political community. When capitalised, "Commonwealth" normally refers to the 53 member Commonwealth of Nations - formerly the "British Commonwealth" - a loose confederation of nations formerly members of the British Empire.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le terme anglais "Commonwealth" remonte au quinzi&#232;me si&#232;cle. Il signifie litt&#233;ralement "bien-&#234;tre de tous". Commonwealth voulait donc d&#233;signer un &#233;tat gouvern&#233; pour le bien de tous, par opposition &#224; un &#233;tat autoritaire gouvern&#233; pour le b&#233;n&#233;fice d'une certaine classe poss&#233;dante.[PARAGRAPH:2]Aujourd'hui, le terme est plus g&#233;n&#233;ral et d&#233;signe une communaut&#233; politique. Le Commonwealth fait normalement r&#233;f&#233;rence aux 53 nations qui faisaient &#224; l'origine partie du Commonwealth britannique, une conf&#233;d&#233;ration disparate de pays issus de l'ancien empire britannique.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der englische Begriff "Commonwealth" datiert urspr&#252;nglich aus dem 15. Jahrhundert und bedeutet w&#246;rtlich &#252;bersetzt etwa "Gemeinwohl". Er bezeichnete urspr&#252;nglich einen Staat, dessen Regierung vornehmlich auf das Wohl der Gemeinschaft abzielt, im Gegensatz zum autorit&#228;ren Staat, dessen Regierung vor allem auf das Wohlergehen einer bestimmten Klasse von Grundbesitzern und sonstigen Eigent&#252;mern hinarbeitet.[PARAGRAPH:2]Heute wird der Begriff allgemeiner verwendet und beschreibt eine politische Staatengemeinschaft. Wenn man vom "Commonwealth" spricht, ist damit nun normalerweise das aus 53 Mitgliedsstaaten gebildete "Commonwealth of Nations" - ehemals "British Commonwealth" genannt - gemeint, ein freiwilliger Bund unabh&#228;ngiger Staaten, die fr&#252;her zum British Empire geh&#246;rten.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La parola inglese &amp;quot;Commonwealth&amp;quot; risale al quindicesimo secolo. Il termine significava letteralmente &amp;quot;benessere comune&amp;quot;. Quindi originariamente commonwealth stava a indicare uno stato governato per il bene comune, in opposizione a uno stato autoritario governato per il benessere di una data classe.[PARAGRAPH:2]Oggi il termine &#232; pi&#249; generico e indica una comunit&#224; politica. Quando &#232; maiuscolo, &amp;quot;Commonwealth&amp;quot; di solito si riferisce al Commonwealth delle Nazioni, composto da 53 membri e una volta conosciuto come Commonwealth britannico: una confederazione di nazioni che facevano precedentemente parte dell'impero britannico.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El t&#233;rmino ingl&#233;s &amp;quot;Commonwealth&amp;quot;, que tiene su origen en el siglo XV, significa literalmente &amp;quot;bienestar com&#250;n&amp;quot;, y en sus or&#237;genes hac&#237;a referencia a un tipo de estado cuyo gobierno persigue el bien com&#250;n, frente a un estado autoritario que persigue el beneficio de una determinada clase social.[PARAGRAPH:2]Hoy el t&#233;rmino es m&#225;s general y alude a una comunidad pol&#237;tica. Cuando se escribe con may&#250;sculas, &amp;quot;Commonwealth&amp;quot; hace referencia a la &amp;quot;Commonwealth of Nations&amp;quot; de 53 miembros, antes denominada &amp;quot;British Commonwealth of Nations&amp;quot;, una confederaci&#243;n laxa que engloba a las naciones que pertenecieron al Imperio Brit&#225;nico.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_DECENTRALIZATION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Decentralization describes an economy in which the central government doesn't attempt to manage every aspect of a nation's production. The government doesn't set quotas, doesn't determine exactly what the nation's farms, factories, theatres and schools will output. Each farmer determines what his or her farm will produce; each factory owner decides what to build, whether to modernize or not, and so forth.[PARAGRAPH:2]This kind of a totally freewheeling economy may seriously increase a nation's productivity. However, it may also lead to disaster - if all of the farmers decide to produce cotton then the nation's people will be very hungry - well-dressed, perhaps, but still very hungry. </English>
  <French>[TAB]La d&#233;centralisation est un syst&#232;me au sein duquel le gouvernement central ne tente pas de g&#233;rer tous les aspects &#233;conomiques de la nation. Le gouvernement n'&#233;tablit pas de quotas, et ne fixe pas d'objectifs pour les fermes, les usines, les th&#233;&#226;tres, ou les &#233;coles de la nation. Chaque fermier d&#233;termine seul ce que produira sa ferme. Les propri&#233;taires d'usines d&#233;cident de ce qu'ils vont fabriquer, et des investissements qu'ils vont r&#233;aliser, etc.[PARAGRAPH:2]Ce genre d'&#233;conomie totalement libre peut augmenter consid&#233;rablement la productivit&#233; d'une nation. Elle peut aussi conduire au d&#233;sastre : si tous les fermiers d&#233;cident de produire du coton, les gens seront peut-&#234;tre bien habill&#233;s, mais ils risquent d'avoir faim. </French>
  <German>[TAB]In einer dezentralisierten Volkswirtschaft &#252;berwacht bzw. reguliert die Regierung nicht mehr alle Wirtschaftsbereiche. Sie setzt keine Quoten fest und verzichtet auf eine exakte Festlegung der Arbeitsweise von Bauernh&#246;fen, Fabriken, Theatern und Schulen. Jeder Bauer bestimmt selbst, was er produziert. Jeder Fabrikant entscheidet selbst, welche Produkte er herstellt, wann er seine Anlagen modernisiert, usw.[PARAGRAPH:2]Diese Art der freien Wirtschaft kann die Produktivit&#228;t eines Landes deutlich steigern ... oder in einer Katastrophe m&#252;nden. Beschlie&#223;en n&#228;mlich alle Bauern eines Landes, Baumwolle anzupflanzen, treten fr&#252;her oder sp&#228;ter Nahrungsengp&#228;sse auf.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]In un sistema decentralizzato, esiste un'economia nella quale il governo centrale non tenta di gestire tutti gli aspetti della produzione di una nazione. Il governo non stabilisce delle aliquote, non determina quante scuole, fabbriche o teatri debbano essere realizzati. Ciascun lavoratore agricolo determina cosa e quanto produrr&#224; nel proprio terreno, ciascuna fabbrica decide cosa costruire, se modernizzarsi o meno e via dicendo.[PARAGRAPH:2]Questo tipo di economia completamente libera pu&#242; aumentare notevolmente la produttivit&#224; di una nazione. Tuttavia, pu&#242; anche portare al disastro: se tutti gli agricoltori decidessero di produrre cotone, presto la popolazione si ritroverebbe alla fame; tutti sarebbero ben vestiti, ma decisamente affamati.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El t&#233;rmino descentralizaci&#243;n describe a aquellas econom&#237;as en las que el gobierno central no trata de controlar todos los aspectos de la producci&#243;n nacional. El gobierno no establece cuotas, ni determina exactamente lo que van a producir las granjas, f&#225;bricas, teatros y escuelas del pa&#237;s. Cada granjero decide lo que va a producir su granja, cada due&#241;o de f&#225;brica decide lo que quiere fabricar, si quiere modernizar sus instalaciones, etc.[PARAGRAPH:2]La libertad econ&#243;mica total puede incrementar de forma notable la productividad de un pa&#237;s. Sin embargo, tambi&#233;n puede ser desastrosa: si todos los granjeros deciden producir algod&#243;n, el pueblo se morir&#225; de hambre... aunque muy bien vestido, eso s&#237;.  </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_DESPOTISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Despotism is a form of government characterized by a ruler who wields absolute power over his people. Despite the word's negative connotations, a leader doesn't necessarily have to be a corrupt, evil megalomaniac to be a despot; it is possible to be a benevolent despot, though history records few cases of such.[PARAGRAPH:2]The strength of this form of government is that the ruler can easily implement his decisions; he does not need to compromise, cajole, or bribe anyone to get the job done. The weakness of this form of government is that the ruler can implement bad decisions just as easily as good ones; with no checks and balances, how can he be stopped? Also, there is a lot of truth in the old saying, "Power corrupts; absolute power corrupts absolutely." And though as said before, despots don't need to be corrupt, evil megalomaniacs, many of them end up that way.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le despotisme est une forme de gouvernement au sein duquel le dirigeant d&#233;tient le pouvoir absolu sur son peuple. Contrairement &#224; ce que l'on pense, un despote n'est pas forc&#233;ment un m&#233;galomane corrompu et mauvais. Le monde a connu des despotes bienveillants, m&#234;me s'il y en a eu peu.[PARAGRAPH:2]La force de ce type de gouvernement r&#233;side dans le fait que le dirigeant peut imposer facilement ses d&#233;cisions, sans passer par des compromis, des cajoleries ou des pots de vins. La faiblesse de ces r&#233;gimes r&#233;side dans le fait que le dirigeant peut aussi facilement imposer ses mauvaises d&#233;cisions puisqu'il n'y a pas de contre-pouvoirs. De plus, il y a une certaine v&#233;rit&#233; dans l'expression : "le pouvoir corrompt, le pouvoir absolu corrompt absolument." Et m&#234;me si les despotes ne sont pas n&#233;cessairement corrompus, beaucoup d'entre eux finissent par le devenir t&#244;t ou tard.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Despotismus ist eine Willk&#252;rherrschaft, bei der ein Herrscher absolute Macht &#252;ber sein Volk aus&#252;bt. Trotz der eher negativen Belegung des Wortes ist dieser Herrscher allerdings nicht zwingend korrupt, b&#246;se und gr&#246;&#223;enwahnsinnig. Es hat im Laufe der Menschheitsgeschichte durchaus (wenn auch nur wenige) g&#252;tige Despoten gegeben.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Vorteil dieser Regierungsform ist die einfache Umsetzbarkeit der Vorstellungen des Herrschers. Dieser muss keine Kompromisse eingehen und mit niemandem verhandeln, um seinen Willen durchzusetzen. Allerdings gilt dies f&#252;r segensreiche UND schlechte Entscheidungen, da diese von keiner gleichberechtigten oder &#252;bergeordneten Instanz in Frage gestellt werden. Daher ist das alte Sprichwort: "Macht korrumpiert, absolute Macht korrumpiert absolut" leider in aller Regel zutreffend. Fr&#252;her oder sp&#228;ter verliert auch der g&#252;tigste Despot seinen Sinn f&#252;r die Realit&#228;t.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il dispotismo &#232; una forma di governo nella quale un sovrano esercita un potere assoluto sul proprio popolo. Malgrado le connotazioni negative della parola, un despota non deve essere necessariamente corrotto o agire da pazzo megalomane; sono esistiti anche despoti benevoli, malgrado nel corso della storia non se ne siano visti molti.[PARAGRAPH:2]La forza di questa forma di governo &#232; che il sovrano pu&#242; mettere in pratica facilmente le proprie decisioni: non ha bisogno di corrompere, lusingare o scendere a compromessi con nessuno. La debolezza di questo tipo di governo, invece, &#232; che il sovrano pu&#242; rischiare di agire in modo errato quanto giusto e senza contrappesi, chi &#232; in grado di fermarlo? Inoltre, c'&#232; del vero nel vecchio detto "il potere corrompe; il potere assoluto ti corrompe assolutamente". E, come detto in precedenza, sebbene un sovrano non debba per forza essere malvagio o megalomane, molti sono finiti cos&#236;.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El despotismo es una forma de gobierno caracterizada por la presencia de un gobernante que ejerce un poder absoluto sobre su pueblo. A pesar de las connotaciones negativas de la palabra, el l&#237;der no tiene por qu&#233; ser necesariamente un megal&#243;mano corrupto y malvado. Es posible ser un d&#233;spota benevolente, aunque la historia no ha registrado demasiados casos.[PARAGRAPH:2]La principal ventaja de esta forma de gobierno radica en que el gobernante puede poner en pr&#225;ctica sus decisiones con facilidad. No necesita convencer, seducir o sobornar a nadie para conseguirlo. Su debilidad estriba en que las malas decisiones son igualmente f&#225;ciles de impulsar. Sin equilibrios ni contrapoderes, nadie puede detener al d&#233;spota. Adem&#225;s, hay mucha verdad en el antiguo dicho que asegura, "el poder corrompe, y el poder absoluto corrompe absolutamente". Y, aunque tal como se ha dicho antes, los d&#233;spotas no tienen por qu&#233; ser megal&#243;manos corruptos y malvados, muchos de ellos acaban si&#233;ndolo.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_DIRECT_RULE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Direct Rule is a state in which a single individual wields all the power and authority embodying the state, and everyone else is a subsidiary person. This form of despotism was common in the first forms of statehood and civilization.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_DYNASTICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A dynasty is a sequence of rulers considered as members of the same family. Historians traditionally consider many sovereign states' history within a framework of successive dynasties, e.g., Ancient Egypt, Persian Empire, and Imperial China. Much of European political history is dominated by dynasties such as the Carolingians, the Capetians, the Bourbons, the Habsburgs, the Stuarts, the Hohenzollerns and the Romanovs. Until the 19th century, it was taken for granted that a legitimate function of a monarch was to aggrandize his dynasty: that is, to increase the territory, wealth and power of family members.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EGALITARIANISM_HELP_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>No Slaves, [ICON_UNHAPPY] Penalty all civs</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EGALITARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Egalitarianism (from French &#233;gal, meaning "equal") is a trend of thought that favors equality among living entities. Egalitarian doctrines maintain that all humans are equal in fundamental worth or social status, according to The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. The Cultural theory of risk holds egalitarianism as defined by (1) a negative attitude towards rules and principles, and (2) a positive attitude towards group decision-making, with fatalism termed as its opposite. According to the Merriam-Webster Dictionary, the term has two distinct definitions in modern English. It is defined either as a political doctrine that all people should be treated as equals and have the same political, economic, social, and civil rights or as a social philosophy advocating the removal of economic inequalities among people or the decentralization of power. Some sources define egalitarianism as the point of view that equality reflects the natural state of humanity.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_EMANCIPATION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Emancipation refers to the abolition of slavery, serfdom, and caste system. Members of the society are on an equal footing: you may be rich and I poor, but if I'm smarter or more cunning than you, I can end up as your boss or even your ruler. Merit and experience and initiative are fully rewarded; each member of a nation can reach his or her potential, to the benefit of all.[PARAGRAPH:2]The previous paragraph describes a somewhat utopian society. In reality, one's situation at birth will have an effect upon one's progress in society. If your parents are rich, you are likely to be healthier, better educated and better connected than a person whose parents are poor. But at least it isn't illegal for the poor person to succeed: his innate qualities can overcome the disadvantages of his parentage. </English>
  <French>[TAB]L'&#233;mancipation fait r&#233;f&#233;rence &#224; l'abolition de l'esclavage, du servage et du syst&#232;me de castes. Les citoyens sont donc &#233;gaux : il y a des pauvres et des riches, mais les plus intelligents et les plus malins grimpent les &#233;chelons sociaux. Le m&#233;rite, l'exp&#233;rience et l'initiative sont r&#233;compens&#233;s ; chaque citoyen peut r&#233;aliser tout son potentiel, au plus grand b&#233;n&#233;fice de tous.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le paragraphe pr&#233;c&#233;dent d&#233;crit une soci&#233;t&#233; utopique. Dans la r&#233;alit&#233;, la naissance joue un r&#244;le sur l'&#233;volution de chacun dans la soci&#233;t&#233;. Si vos parents sont riches, vous avez toutes les chances d'&#234;tre en meilleure sant&#233;, mieux form&#233; et mieux int&#233;gr&#233; qu'une personne dont les parents sont pauvres. Les pauvres ont au moins techniquement le droit de r&#233;ussir : leurs qualit&#233;s individuelles peuvent venir compenser leur naissance. </French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Emanzipation" umfasst die Abschaffung der Sklaverei, der Leibeigenschaft und des Kastensystems. Alle Mitglieder einer Gesellschaft sind gleichgestellt (egal, ob sie arm oder reich sind). Leistung, Erfahrung und Eigeninitiative werden belohnt. Jedes Mitglied der Gesellschaft kann sein volles Potenzial aussch&#246;pfen. Davon profitiert wiederum die ganze Gesellschaft.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der vorherige Abschnitt beschreibt eine ideale (aber unrealistische) Gesellschaft. Tats&#228;chlich wird ein Mensch von den Lebensumst&#228;nden, in die er hineingeboren wird, nachhaltig gepr&#228;gt. Kinder wohlhabender Eltern sind in der Regel ges&#252;nder und haben bessere Aufstiegsm&#246;glichkeiten als Kinder armer Eltern. Allerdings hindert niemand einen armen Menschen daran, sein Potenzial auszusch&#246;pfen und gesellschaftliche Schranken zu &#252;berwinden.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Con la parola "emancipazione" si fa riferimento all'abolizione di schiavit&#249;, servit&#249; e caste. I membri della societ&#224; sono tutti uguali: se una persona &#232; ricca e una &#232; povera e quest'ultima si dimostra pi&#249; scaltra, pu&#242; accadere che si invertano i ruoli. Merito, esperienza e iniziativa vengono ricompensati: ciascun membro di ogni nazione pu&#242; raggiungere il suo massimo potenziale, con benefici per l'individuo e per la societ&#224;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il paragrafo precedente descrive una societ&#224; utopistica: in realt&#224;, la propria condizione alla nascita potrebbe influenzare i progressi nella societ&#224;. Se si &#232; figli di genitori ricchi, probabilmente si avr&#224; una vita benestante, con pi&#249; possibilit&#224; di educazione e di inserimento nella societ&#224;. Tuttavia, non &#232; illegale che una persona povera riesca a raggiungere qualche traguardo: grazie alle proprie qualit&#224; innate, potr&#224; superare gli svantaggi di essere nato da genitori non benestanti.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La emancipaci&#243;n es la abolici&#243;n del esclavismo, la servidumbre y el sistema de castas. Todos los miembros de la sociedad quedan en posici&#243;n de igualdad: puede que t&#250; seas rico y yo pobre, pero si soy m&#225;s listo o m&#225;s astuto, tal vez acabe siendo tu jefe, o incluso tu gobernante. El m&#233;rito, la experiencia y la iniciativa tienen su recompensa: todos los ciudadanos pueden desarrollar su potencial, lo que redunda en beneficio del colectivo.[PARAGRAPH:2]El p&#225;rrafo anterior describe una sociedad ut&#243;pica. En la realidad, la posici&#243;n que uno ocupa al nacer tiene notable influencia sobre su capacidad de progresar. Una persona con padres ricos tiene m&#225;s posibilidades de gozar de buena salud, recibir una buena educaci&#243;n y tener contactos que una persona de familia humilde. Pero al menos para &#233;sta no es ilegal tener &#233;xito: sus cualidades innatas pueden permitirle sobreponerse a las desventajas derivadas de su nacimiento. </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ENVIRONMENTALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Environmentalism is the civic which describes a society in which every effort is made to remain in balance with nature. Emphasis is placed upon renewable resources and energy, and every possible item is recycled. This of course describes the ideal; no modern society on earth of any size can as yet achieve perfect harmony with the world around it.[PARAGRAPH:2]There are many benefits to environmentalism, not the least of which is that it would ensure that mankind will not suffocate under the weight of its own greed and pollution. The population of a fully "green" society would live longer and healthier lives, secure in the knowledge that their children and grandchildren would enjoy the same beautiful world that they did.[PARAGRAPH:2]Unfortunately, such changes will come slowly, if at all. Rich and powerful nations are extremely reluctant to cut back on the resources they consume, and loathe to implement the kind of political and market reforms that such an economy would require. Meanwhile the poorer countries wish to attain all of the power and wealth currently enjoyed by the rich: to them a smokestack is a symbol of progress, not of the ongoing destruction of the earth. Radical change will have to wait for the time when the magnitude and imminence of disaster is visible to everyone.</English>
  <French>[TAB]L'environnementalisme est le r&#233;gime qui d&#233;crit une soci&#233;t&#233; visant &#224; maintenir l'&#233;quilibre entre l'homme et la nature. L'accent est mis sur les ressources et les &#233;nergies renouvelables et le recyclage est une priorit&#233;. Il s'agit bien s&#251;r d'une soci&#233;t&#233; id&#233;alis&#233;e : aucun Etat contemporain, quel qu'il soit, ne vit en harmonie avec le monde qui l'entoure.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'environnementalisme a de nombreux avantages : Le premier, et pas des moindres, est qu'il assure &#224; l'homme qu'il ne suffoquera pas sous le poids de ses d&#233;chets et de sa pollution. La population d'un Etat "&#233;cologique" vivra plus longtemps et en meilleure sant&#233;, et ne redoutera pas que les g&#233;n&#233;rations futures ne puissent pas profiter du monde tel qu'on l'a connu.[PARAGRAPH:2]Malheureusement, ces changements se produiront lentement, dans le meilleur des cas. Certaines nations riches et puissantes r&#233;pugnent &#224; r&#233;duire leur consommation de ressources naturelles et se refusent &#224; mettre en oeuvre les r&#233;formes politiques et &#233;conomiques n&#233;cessaires pour atteindre cet id&#233;al. Dans le m&#234;me temps, les nations pauvres cherchent &#224; acqu&#233;rir la m&#234;me puissance et la m&#234;me richesse que les pays riches, et consid&#232;rent les fum&#233;es industrielles comme des signes de progr&#232;s, pas comme des pollutions nocives d&#233;truisant la Terre. Un changement radical ne sera probablement possible que le jour o&#249; tout le monde percevra l'&#233;tendue du d&#233;sastre en cours.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Umweltschutz" umfasst die Bem&#252;hungen eines Staates, das &#246;kologische Gleichgewicht zu wahren. Wichtige Schlagw&#246;rter in diesem Zusammenhang sind "erneuerbare Energien" und "Recycling". Da keine moderne Gesellschaft einen perfekten Umweltschutz gew&#228;hrleisten kann, bleibt der Umweltschutzgedanke meist eine Idealvorstellung.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Umweltschutz hat viele Vorteile. Immerhin ist er der Garant daf&#252;r, dass die Menschheit nicht mittelfristig in ihrem eigenen M&#252;ll erstickt. Die Bev&#246;lkerung einer "gr&#252;nen" Welt w&#252;rde deutlich l&#228;nger und ges&#252;nder leben und k&#246;nnte sicher sein, dass auch ihre Kinder und Enkel noch in den Genuss einer intakten Umwelt kommen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Leider sind umweltpolitische &#196;nderungen (wenn &#252;berhaupt) nur sehr langsam zu bewerkstelligen, da einflussreiche Industrienationen nicht bereit sind, ihren Energieverbrauch zu senken oder entsprechende wirtschaftliche und politische Reformen einzuleiten. Dar&#252;ber hinaus gelten in vielen armen L&#228;ndern die Schornsteine der Industrienationen als Symbole des Fortschritts ... und nicht der fortschreitenden Zerst&#246;rung der Erde. Radikale Ver&#228;nderungen werden wohl erst m&#246;glich sein, wenn Ausma&#223; und Folgen der Umweltzerst&#246;rung offensichtlich sind.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]L'ambientalismo rappresenta una societ&#224; che si sforza costantemente di mantenere un equilibrio con la natura e nella quale viene posta l'enfasi sulle risorse energetiche rinnovabili e sulla possibilit&#224; di riciclare tutto. Naturalmente questo &#232; un ideale: nessuna societ&#224; moderna &#232; ancora riuscita a vivere in perfetta armonia con il mondo che la circonda.[PARAGRAPH:2]I benefici dell'ambientalismo sono molteplici, non ultimo quello di impedire che l'umanit&#224; venga soffocata dal proprio inquinamento e dalla propria avidit&#224;. La popolazione di una societ&#224; "ecologica" vivrebbe pi&#249; a lungo e in salute, con la sicurezza che figli e pronipoti possano vivere nel mondo pulito che i loro antenati hanno contribuito a creare.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sfortunatamente, alcuni cambiamenti avvengono lentamente: le nazioni ricche e potenti sono estremamente riluttanti a tagliare il proprio consumo di risorse e vogliono evitare gli sconvolgimenti economici che una manovra del genere potrebbe causare. Nel frattempo, le nazioni pi&#249; povere ambiscono a conquistare il potere e la ricchezza dei benestanti, inconsapevoli del fatto che un camino non &#232; un simbolo di progresso, ma rappresenta la distruzione del pianeta. Per i cambi radicali si dovr&#224; aspettare il momento in cui il pericolo sar&#224; enorme e visibile a tutti.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El "ecologismo" se da en aquellas sociedades cuyo objetivo principal es mantenerse en equilibrio con la naturaleza. La renovaci&#243;n de recursos y de energ&#237;as es uno de los pilares de estas sociedades, as&#237; como el reciclaje. Naturalmente, &#233;sta es una descripci&#243;n ideal. En nuestros tiempos no existe ninguna sociedad, del tama&#241;o que sea, capaz de existir en perfecta armon&#237;a con el mundo que la rodea.[PARAGRAPH:2]El ecologismo cuenta con muchas ventajas, entre ellas que garantiza que la humanidad no sucumba al peso de su propia codicia y capacidad de poluci&#243;n. La poblaci&#243;n de una sociedad totalmente ecol&#243;gica tendr&#237;a una vida m&#225;s larga y saludable, con la seguridad de que sus hijos y nietos gozar&#237;an del mismo y maravilloso mundo que ella.[PARAGRAPH:2]Por desgracia, los pasos encaminados a llegar a una sociedad como &#233;sta son siempre muy lentos, si es que se dan. Las naciones ricas y poderosas son extremadamente remisas a limitar el consumo de recursos y se muestran reacias a implantar las reformas pol&#237;ticas y econ&#243;micas que una sociedad semejante requerir&#237;a. Al mismo tiempo, las naciones pobres envidian el poder y la riqueza de las ricas: para ellas, una chimenea industrial es un s&#237;mbolo de progreso, no el anuncio de la destrucci&#243;n de la Tierra. Los cambios radicales tendr&#225;n que esperar a que la magnitud e inminencia del desastre sean evidentes para todos.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_FANATICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Fanaticism is strict adherence to a specific set of theological doctrines. These doctrines are usually considered to be of much greater importance and relevance than any man-made laws; in many cases a fanatical state adopts them as state law and strives to impose them on other civilizations as well. Other religions are regarded with disdain or even open hostility. Alternatively, some fanatical states prefer to isolate themselves from the heathens and secularism of the world.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_FREE_MARKET_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A free market system is similar to a decentralized system, in that the government doesn't try to impose price controls, quotas or other artificial limits on production. The market - what people want and what they are willing to pay for it - determines production. Unlike in decentralization the state maintains some controls over the system, attempting to ensure that the markets remain truly free and is not distorted by monopolies or corruption.[PARAGRAPH:2]A state may have some free markets while maintaining more control over others that it considers critical to the state's survival; in modern times these usually include the production and dispersion of energy and the production of weapons.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Un syst&#232;me d'&#233;conomie de march&#233; est proche d'un syst&#232;me d&#233;centralis&#233;, dans la mesure o&#249; le gouvernement n'essaie pas d'imposer un contr&#244;le des prix ou des quotas de production. Le march&#233;, ce que les gens veulent et ce qu'ils sont pr&#234;ts &#224; payer pour l'avoir, d&#233;termine la production. Contrairement &#224; la d&#233;centralisation, l'Etat conserve des moyens de surveillance et de contr&#244;le et veille &#224; ce que le march&#233; ne soit pas fauss&#233; par des monopoles ou par la corruption.[PARAGRAPH:2]Un Etat peut fonctionner sur le principe de l'&#233;conomie de march&#233; tout en maintenant un contr&#244;le appuy&#233; sur certains secteurs de l'&#233;conomie qu'il consid&#232;re comme cruciaux pour la survie de la nation. Cela concerne g&#233;n&#233;ralement les secteurs de l'&#233;nergie et de l'armement.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Die freie Marktwirtschaft ist ein dezentrales System, bei dem sich die Regierung nicht in die Preisgestaltung einmischt und die Produktion in keiner Weise einschr&#228;nkt. Der Markt, also Angebot und Nachfrage, bestimmt die Produktion. Anders als im Dezentralismus verhindert der Staat jedoch als Kontrollorgan die Entstehung von Monopolen und geht gezielt gegen Korruption und Marktmanipulationen vor.[PARAGRAPH:2]In einem Staat kann es mehrere freie M&#228;rkte geben, die (abh&#228;ngig von ihrer Bedeutung) mehr oder weniger unter staatlicher Aufsicht stehen. Typische M&#228;rkte sind in diesem Zusammenhang die Energiegewinnung und die R&#252;stungsindustrie.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Un sistema di libero mercato &#232; simile a quello decentralizzato, nel quale un governo non tenta di imporre controlli su prezzi, aliquote o altri limiti artificiali sulla produzione; il mercato, ovvero la domanda-offerta da parte della gente, determina la produzione. Al contrario della decentralizzazione, lo stato mantiene il controllo sul sistema, cercando di assicurare il libero mercato senza corruzione e monopoli.[PARAGRAPH:2]Uno stato pu&#242; avere alcuni liberi mercati e mantenere il controllo su altri che ritiene essenziali per la propria sopravvivenza. Al giorno d'oggi, questi mercati in genere comprendono la produzione di armi ed energia.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El sistema de mercado libre se parece al descentralizado en que, en ambos, el gobierno renuncia a imponer controles de precios, cuotas u otros l&#237;mites artificiales a la producci&#243;n. Es el mercado (lo que la gente quiere y lo que est&#225; dispuesta a pagar por ello) quien determina la producci&#243;n. A diferencia de la descentralizaci&#243;n, el estado conserva cierto control, a fin de garantizar que el mercado es realmente libre y no sufre las distorsiones inducidas por los monopolios o la corrupci&#243;n.[PARAGRAPH:2]Un estado puede emplear el mercado libre en ciertas &#225;reas de la econom&#237;a y mantener mayor grado de control sobre otras, que considera vitales para su supervivencia. En la actualidad, &#233;stas son la producci&#243;n y distribuci&#243;n de la energ&#237;a y la producci&#243;n armament&#237;stica.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_FREE_RELIGION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Free religion refers to a society in which no single religion is dominant, in which people are free to worship or not worship as they please. There is no state religion; the government is totally secular.[PARAGRAPH:2]Such states allow all to express their religious beliefs. This encourages immigration by people whose religions are suppressed elsewhere, and the general society benefits from the multitude of experiences and beliefs of its members. However, such freedom and tolerance of religions may weaken a nation's people's beliefs in any religion, which could cause the people to become morally lax and decadent. Further, members of the more militant and expansionist religions may seek to destroy the competition, causing a good deal of stress and conflict within a country. A good deal of maturity is required on the part of a government and its people to successfully sustain free religion.</English>
  <French>[TAB]La libert&#233; de culte fait r&#233;f&#233;rence &#224; une soci&#233;t&#233; dans laquelle il n'y a pas de religion dominante, et qui laisse ses citoyens libres de croire ou de ne pas croire. Il n'y a pas de religion d'Etat. Le gouvernement est totalement la&#239;c.[PARAGRAPH:2]De tels Etats permettent que l'on exprime ses croyances religieuses. Ceci encourage l'immigration de populations dont la religion est ailleurs r&#233;prim&#233;e, et toute la soci&#233;t&#233; b&#233;n&#233;ficie de la diversit&#233; des cultures de sa population. Cependant, une telle libert&#233; et tol&#233;rance religieuse risque d'affaiblir le sentiment religieux de toute la nation. Ceci peut provoquer un rel&#226;chement de la morale. De m&#234;me, les croyants des religions les plus militantes peuvent essayer d'en profiter pour assurer leur domination, provoquant alors des conflits &#224; l'int&#233;rieur du pays. Pour r&#233;ussir, la libert&#233; de culte demande donc une grande maturit&#233; de la part du gouvernement et du peuple.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Herrscht in einer Gesellschaft Religionsfreiheit, darf jeder B&#252;rger und Besucher des Landes seine Religion ungest&#246;rt aus&#252;ben. Es gibt keine Staatsreligion und eine strenge Trennung von Kirche und Staat.[PARAGRAPH:2]Da in L&#228;ndern mit Religionsfreiheit das Recht der freien Religionsaus&#252;bung gilt, ist die Zuwanderungsrate von Menschen, die in ihrer Heimat aufgrund ihres Glaubens verfolgt werden, sehr hoch. In der Regel profitiert die Gesellschaft von der religi&#246;sen Vielschichtigkeit ihrer Mitglieder. Allerdings k&#246;nnen Religionsfreiheit und Toleranz im Extremfall auch zum Niedergang des Glaubens f&#252;hren. Dar&#252;ber hinaus wird die Religionsfreiheit immer wieder von militanten Gruppierungen missbraucht. Die Erhaltung der Religionsfreiheit in offenen Gesellschaften ist daher eine der gr&#246;&#223;ten Herausforderungen der Zukunft.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La libert&#224; religiosa si ha nelle nazioni in cui non esiste una singola religione dominante e le persone sono libere di fare ci&#242; che vogliono. Non esiste una religione di stato: il governo &#232; assolutamente laico.[PARAGRAPH:2]In questi stati &#232; permesso esprimere i propri credo religiosi: in tal modo, si incoraggia l'immigrazione di persone di una religione che &#232; stata magari vietata nella nazione di origine; la societ&#224; migliora con le esperienze e le fedi di ogni individuo. Malgrado ci&#242;, questo tipo di libert&#224; e tolleranza verso le altre religioni potrebbe indebolire la fede della popolazione, facendo crollare il morale. Inoltre, i membri delle religioni pi&#249; battagliere ed espansioniste potrebbero tentare di eliminare i "rivali", provocando tensioni e conflitti all'interno del paese. Perch&#233; sia possibile la libert&#224; di religione, ci vuole buon senso da parte del governo e della popolazione.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La libertad religiosa caracteriza a aquellas sociedades en las que no existe una &#250;nica religi&#243;n dominante y la gente tiene derecho a profesar la religi&#243;n que desee. No existe religi&#243;n oficial; el gobierno es totalmente secular.[PARAGRAPH:2]Estos estados permiten que todos expresen sus creencias religiosas. Esto atrae la inmigraci&#243;n de las minor&#237;as religiosas perseguidas en otras partes del mundo, y la sociedad en su conjunto se beneficia de la multitud de experiencias y creencias de sus miembros. Sin embargo, la libertad y tolerancia religiosas pueden debilitar el esp&#237;ritu religioso de la naci&#243;n, lo que puede desembocar en una poblaci&#243;n carente de principios morales y decadente. Adem&#225;s, los seguidores de las religiones m&#225;s militantes y proselitistas pueden tratar de destruir a sus competidores, atizando el fuego del descontento y el desorden civil. Para que exista aut&#233;ntica libertad religiosa, la sociedad y el gobierno deben hacer gala de una notable madurez.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_FREE_SPEECH_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The term "free speech" describes a legal system in which a person cannot be stopped from saying anything he or she wants, as long as the speech doesn't cause immediate harm to those around him or her - even in the freest society, it is still illegal to shout "Fire!" in a crowded movie theatre.[PARAGRAPH:2]The benefits of free speech are many. The citizens may debate their government's policies and actions fully, without fear of punishment. A free press allows the citizens great access to news and information, allowing them to more accurately judge the events taking place in the world around them. Tyrants and despots rightly fear free speech more than almost anything else. On the other hand, free speech may be hate speech; it may be lies. Such speech must be allowed: once a government is allowed to determine which speech is to be allowed and which is to be suppressed, the temptation to abuse that power is overwhelming, and speech isn't free any more.</English>
  <French>[TAB]La "libert&#233; d'expression" est un syst&#232;me juridique au sein duquel les individus ont le droit de dire tout ce qu'ils veulent, du moment qu'ils ne nuisent pas directement &#224; ceux qui les entourent (m&#234;me dans les soci&#233;t&#233;s les plus libres, il est interdit de crier "au feu !" dans un cin&#233;ma bond&#233;).[PARAGRAPH:2]Les b&#233;n&#233;fices de la libert&#233; d'expression sont nombreux : les citoyens peuvent d&#233;battre de la politique de leur gouvernement sans craindre d'&#234;tre r&#233;primand&#233;s. La presse ind&#233;pendante permet de diffuser largement les informations, et donc d'aider les gens &#224; avoir pleinement connaissance des &#233;v&#232;nements du monde. Les tyrans et les despotes craignent plus que tout la libert&#233; d'expression. D'un autre c&#244;t&#233;, la libert&#233; d'expression autorise aussi les discours de haine, et les mensonges. On ne peut les interdire, car une fois que le gouvernement a le pouvoir de d&#233;terminer ce qui peut ou ne peut pas &#234;tre dit, la tentation d'abuser de ce pouvoir est trop forte, et la libert&#233; d'expression dispara&#238;t.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Meinungsfreiheit" bezeichnet das Recht des Einzelnen, seine Meinung frei zu &#228;u&#223;ern, solange er damit niemandem schadet. Allerdings ist es auch in einer freien Gesellschaft nicht erlaubt, in einem voll besetzten Kinosaal "Feuer!" zu rufen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Meinungsfreiheit hat viele Vorteile. Die B&#252;rger k&#246;nnen &#252;ber die Politik ihrer Regierung debattieren, ohne Strafen bef&#252;rchten zu m&#252;ssen. Dank der freien Presse haben die B&#252;rger dar&#252;ber hinaus Zugang zu Nachrichten und Informationen, die ihnen die Beurteilung der innen- und weltpolitischen Lage erm&#246;glichen. Tyrannen und Despoten f&#252;rchten die Meinungsfreiheit mehr als alles andere. Allerdings muss im Zuge der Meinungsfreiheit jede Meinung (also auch Hassreden und L&#252;gen) toleriert werden, da jedes Verbot unerw&#252;nschter &#196;u&#223;erungen die Meinungsfreiheit ad absurdum f&#252;hren w&#252;rde.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il termine "libert&#224; di parola" descrive un sistema legale nel quale a una persona non pu&#242; essere impedito di dire ci&#242; che vuole, almeno finch&#233; ci&#242; non finisce per nuocere ad altre persone. Anche nella societ&#224; pi&#249; libera, &#232; illegale urlare "al fuoco!" in un cinema affollato.[PARAGRAPH:2]I benefici della libert&#224; di parola sono molteplici: i cittadini possono dibattere sulle politiche del governo e comportarsi liberamente, senza timore di una punizione. La stampa indipendente consente al cittadino di avvicinarsi a fonti di informazione, permettendogli di farsi un'idea non faziosa del mondo che lo circonda. Tiranni e despoti temono la libert&#224; di parola pi&#249; di ogni altra cosa; per contro, per&#242;, le parole possono trasformarsi in menzogne. Quando un governo ha la possibilit&#224; di stabilire cosa si pu&#242; dire e cosa no, la tentazione di abusare del potere &#232; grande e si rischia di perdere la libert&#224; di parola.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El t&#233;rmino "libertad de expresi&#243;n" describe un sistema legal en el que todo el mundo puede decir lo que piensa mientras sus palabras no representen un peligro inmediato para quienes lo rodean: hasta en la sociedad m&#225;s liberal es ilegal gritar "&#161;fuego!" en medio de una multitud.[PARAGRAPH:2]Los beneficios de la libertad de expresi&#243;n son numerosos. Los ciudadanos pueden debatir libremente y sin miedo a sufrir represalias sobre la pol&#237;tica y las acciones de su gobierno. La prensa libre permite a la poblaci&#243;n acceder a las noticias y la informaci&#243;n, lo que les proporciona la capacidad de juzgar con mayor precisi&#243;n cuanto sucede a su alrededor. Los tiranos y d&#233;spotas temen (y con raz&#243;n) la libertad de expresi&#243;n m&#225;s que ninguna otra cosa. Por otro lado, permite la propagaci&#243;n de discursos violentos o mentiras, pero se trata de un mal menor: cuando un gobierno se arroga la capacidad de decidir qu&#233; cosas pueden decirse y cu&#225;les no, la tentaci&#243;n de abusar de esta prerrogativa se vuelve demasiado grande y la libertad de expresi&#243;n deja de existir.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_HEREDITARY_RULE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Hereditary Rule is a form of government wherein the rulership is passed down from one member of the family to the next. This kind of succession is most often associated with monarchical rulers, but it occasionally appears in despotisms or even purportedly communist regimes - North Korea, for example. There is often a religious justification for hereditary rule; kings are said to rule by "divine right" or "the mandate of Heaven."[PARAGRAPH:2]The strength of hereditary rule is that there is usually a clear line of succession, and thus perhaps less squabbling for power when the current monarch dies. (There are plenty of exceptions to this rule throughout history, of course.) Further, there may be a certain amount of familial pressure on the ruler to not mess things up too badly for the next generation. However, hereditary rule suffers the same kind of weaknesses as do all unelected rulers; the leader is not answerable to the people, and it can be extremely difficult to get rid of a bad one.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le droit h&#233;r&#233;ditaire est une forme de gouvernement par lequel le pouvoir est transmis d'un membre de la famille r&#233;gnante &#224; un autre. Ce genre de successions est souvent associ&#233; &#224; la monarchie, mais elles sont aussi parfois appliqu&#233;es dans les r&#233;gimes despotiques, voire dans les soi-disant r&#233;gimes communistes, comme la Cor&#233;e du Nord, par exemple. Le droit h&#233;r&#233;ditaire est souvent justifi&#233; par la religion. Les rois sont ainsi de "droit divin" ou "mandat&#233; par le ciel".[PARAGRAPH:2]La force du droit h&#233;r&#233;ditaire r&#233;side dans une relative tranquillit&#233; lors des successions, l'h&#233;ritier &#233;tant connu d'avance. L'histoire, cependant, est riche d'exceptions &#224; cette r&#232;gle. De plus, la personne r&#233;gnante est plus ou moins surveill&#233;e par sa famille, qui ne tient pas &#224; ce qu'il laisse &#224; ses successeurs une situation chaotique. Cependant, le droit h&#233;r&#233;ditaire souffre des faiblesses propres aux r&#233;gimes dans lesquels le dirigeant n'est pas &#233;lu. Le dirigeant n'a pas &#224; r&#233;pondre devant le peuple, et aussi mauvais qu'il puisse &#234;tre, il est tr&#232;s difficile de s'en d&#233;barrasser.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Das Erbrecht ist eine Regierungsform, bei der die Regentschaft von einem Familienmitglied an das n&#228;chste weitergegeben wird. Diese Art der Nachfolge wird h&#228;ufig in Monarchien praktiziert. Gelegentlich wird aber auch im Despotismus oder Kommunismus (Nordkorea) darauf zur&#252;ckgegriffen. Das Erbrecht st&#252;tzt sich nicht selten auf eine religi&#246;se Rechtfertigung in Form eines "Gottesgnadentums" des Monarchen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Vorteil des Erbrechts ist die im Regelfall klar geregelte Erbfolge. Dadurch halten sich Streitigkeiten nach dem Tod des Monarchen meist in Grenzen. Dar&#252;ber hinaus kann die Familie betr&#228;chtlichen Druck auf den Herrscher aus&#252;ben. Allerdings ist ein nach dem Erbrecht eingesetzter Herrscher seinem Volk keinerlei Rechenschaft schuldig und es ist relativ schwierig, einen ungeliebten Regenten abzusetzen.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Quello ereditario &#232; una forma di governo nel quale il potere del sovrano passa da un membro della famiglia a un altro. Questo tipo di successione viene spesso attribuito ai sovrani monarchici, ma si &#232; verificato anche in despotismi e regimi comunisti, dei quali la Corea del Nord ne &#232; un esempio. C'&#232; sempre una giustificazione religiosa dietro un governo ereditario: si dice che i re goverino per "diritto divino" o per "mandato del Cielo".[PARAGRAPH:2]La forza di un governo ereditario &#232; che spesso la successione &#232; ben delineata e, alla morte del sovrano, i litigi sono ridotti al minimo. (Naturalmente, esistono molte eccezioni alla regola nel corso della storia). Inoltre, c'&#232; molta pressione sul sovrano da parte della famiglia per non rovinare il futuro delle generazioni successive. Tuttavia, il governo ereditario soffre dello stesso problema di altre situazioni: il sovrano non viene eletto dal popolo ed &#232; estremamente difficile disfarsi di uno particolarmente incapace.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El gobierno hereditario es una forma de gobierno en la que la autoridad se transmite de un miembro a otro de la familia. Esta clase de sucesi&#243;n suele asociarse a gobernantes mon&#225;rquicos, pero en ocasiones aparece tambi&#233;n en despotados o en reg&#237;menes te&#243;ricamente comunistas, como por ejemplo Corea del Norte. En el gobierno hereditario casi siempre existe una justificaci&#243;n religiosa. Se dice que los reyes gobiernan por "derecho divino" o por "mandato del cielo".[PARAGRAPH:2]La solidez del gobierno hereditario radica en que suele existir una l&#237;nea clara de sucesi&#243;n, lo que tiende a limitar las luchas de poder a la muerte del monarca (naturalmente, la historia est&#225; llena de excepciones a esta regla). Adem&#225;s, el gobernante suele enfrentarse a una cierta dosis de presi&#243;n familiar que le obliga a cuidar su legado para la generaci&#243;n siguiente. Sin embargo, los gobernantes hereditarios adolecen de las mismas debilidades que todos los l&#237;deres no electos; no son responsables ante el pueblo y, cuando son malos, puede ser extremadamente complicado librarse de ellos.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_LEVY_ARMIES_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Under the feudal conditions for holding land in the medieval period, most peasants and freemen were liable to provide one man of suitable age per family for military duty when required by either the king or the local lord. The levies raised in this way fought as infantry under local superiors. Although the exact laws varied greatly depending on the country and the period, generally these levies were only obliged to fight for one to three months. Most were subsistence farmers, and it was in everyone's interest to send the men home for harvest-time.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MERCANTILISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Mercantilism refers to government policy that strictly manages the nation's production. The government determines which farmers produce which crops, decides who will be allowed to sew pants and who will have a monopoly on shirts, and so on. The nation may ban all foreign imports.[PARAGRAPH:2]The advantages of mercantilism are that it ensures that a nation's wealth remains within the nation itself, and that its people are not put out of business by cheap foreign imports. On the other hand, the success or the failure of the entire economy is in the hands of just a few men or even one, and if they make foolish or unlucky decisions, the nation as a whole suffers. Further, the ban on foreign imports limits the nation's exposure to new products and new ideas. And if someone has a monopoly on an item, there is little pressure for that person to improve the item or make it cheaper.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le mercantilisme fait r&#233;f&#233;rence &#224; un gouvernement qui r&#233;glemente d'une mani&#232;re stricte la production de la nation. Le gouvernement d&#233;termine la production de chaque ferme, il d&#233;cide qui peut coudre des pantalons et qui vendra les chemises, etc. La nation peut interdire toute importation.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'avantage du mercantilisme est qu'il assure que toutes les richesses de la nation demeurent dans les fronti&#232;res de la nation, et que les gens ne seront pas mis au ch&#244;mage par les produits bon march&#233; import&#233;s de l'&#233;tranger. D'un autre c&#244;t&#233;, la r&#233;ussite ou l'&#233;chec de toute l'&#233;conomie est entre les mains de quelques individus voire d'un seul, et si ces derniers se trompent, c'est toute la nation qui en p&#226;tit. De plus, l'interdiction des importations limite l'acc&#232;s de la nation aux nouveaux produits et aux nouvelles id&#233;es. Enfin, si quelqu'un obtient un monopole, rien ou presque ne peut l'obliger &#224; am&#233;liorer son produit ou &#224; le vendre meilleur march&#233;.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Merkantilismus ist ein Wirtschaftssystem, das die gesamte Produktion eines Landes reglementiert. Die Regierung allein bestimmt, was die Bauern des Landes anbauen, wer Hosen n&#228;hen und wer mit Hemden handeln darf. Au&#223;erdem kann die Einfuhr ausl&#228;ndischer Waren verboten werden.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Merkantilismus gew&#228;hrleistet, dass keine Gelder ins Ausland abflie&#223;en und niemand aufgrund der Einfuhr von Waren finanzielle Einbu&#223;en hinnehmen muss. Allerdings liegt der Erfolg bzw. das Scheitern der Volkswirtschaft in den H&#228;nden einiger weniger Menschen. Treffen diese t&#246;richte oder falsche Entscheidungen, leidet das ganze Volk darunter. Dar&#252;ber hinaus gelangen aufgrund des Importverbots keine neuen Waren oder Ideen in das Land. Und hat ein Handwerker oder Fabrikant ein Monopol auf ein bestimmtes Produkt, gibt es f&#252;r ihn keinen Grund, das Produkt zu verbessern oder preiswerter anzubieten.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Con la parola mercantilismo ci si riferisce alle politiche di un governo che gestisce strettamente la produzione di una nazione. Il governo determina quali agricoltori debbano produrre raccolti, chi debba realizzare i vestiti e chi invece abbia il monopolio delle magliette. Una nazione pu&#242; anche bandire tutte le importazioni dall'estero.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il mercantilismo assicura che il benessere di una nazione rimanga all'interno dei propri confini, impedendo alla gente di venire tagliata fuori da importazioni economiche. Per contro, il successo o il fallimento dell'intera economia &#232; nelle mani di pochi uomini, se non addirittura di uno solo: l'intera nazione pu&#242; pagare il peso di decisioni avventate o sbagliate. Inoltre, il bando delle importazioni limita l'esposizione di nuove idee e di nuovi prodotti della nazione e se qualcuno detiene il monopolio su un oggetto, ci sono poche pressioni per migliorarlo o renderlo pi&#249; economico.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El mercantilismo es una teor&#237;a pol&#237;tica que aboga por el control estricto de la producci&#243;n del estado. El gobierno determina qu&#233; cosecha cada granjero, qui&#233;n va a plantar nuevos cultivos, qui&#233;n disfrutar&#225; de un monopolio sobre las camisas, etc. La naci&#243;n puede llegar a prohibir las importaciones.[PARAGRAPH:2]La ventaja principal del mercantilismo es que garantiza que la riqueza del pa&#237;s permanece dentro de &#233;l y que los productores no sufren la competencia de productos baratos de importaci&#243;n. Por otro lado, el &#233;xito o fracaso de la econom&#237;a queda en manos de unos pocos hombres (o incluso uno solo) y si &#233;stos toman decisiones equivocadas o desafortunadas, la naci&#243;n entera lo paga. Adem&#225;s, cuando se proh&#237;ben las importaciones, se limita el acceso de la ciudadan&#237;a a productos e ideas nuevos. Y si alguien ejerce un monopolio sobre un producto, carece de incentivos para mejorarlo o abaratarlo.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MERCENARIES_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A mercenary is a person who takes part in an armed conflict, who is not a national or a party to the conflict and is "motivated to take part in the hostilities by the desire for private gain." The term "mercenary" is also used to describe the army itself.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MILITIA_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The most basic method of organizing an armed defense for the community is that of the militia. In primitive societies, every adult male is expected to fight (with varying competence) to either protect the village or to raid and harass neighbors. In more settled and organized societies, the duty of forming a militia tends to fall on volunteers armed and trained at community expense, or on elite classes of citizens who can afford their own weapons.[PARAGRAPH:2]Militia have the strategic advantages of being numerous, cheap to maintain from the central government's perspective, and of having reliable local loyalties that make them difficult to suborn. The large, corresponding disadvantages are that they are often less competent than more professional forces, difficult to keep in the field for long periods, and reluctant to fight far from their homes.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_MULTILATERALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]In international relations, multilateralism is multiple countries working in concert on a given issue. Multilateralism was defined by Miles Kahler as "international governance of the 'many,'" and its central principle was "opposition [of] bilateral discriminatory arrangements that were believed to enhance the leverage of the powerful over the weak and to increase international conflict." In 1990, Robert Keohane defined multilateralism as "the practice of coordinating national policies in groups of three or more states.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_NATIONHOOD_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A "nation" is a group of people sharing some kind of common identity. Nations may be united by language, custom, history, or religion (or any combination of them).[PARAGRAPH:2]Sharing languages, customs, histories and so forth provides strength to a nation - the sense of identity and commonality reduces internal strife, civil and religious wars, and so forth. Unfortunately, citizens with different languages, customs, and backgrounds may be looked upon with suspicion, distrust, and contempt, promoting unhappiness and unrest from the minority and limiting their ability to fully contribute to the society.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Une "nation" est un groupe de gens ayant une forme d'identit&#233; commune. Les nations sont fond&#233;es sur une unit&#233; de langue, de coutume, d'histoire ou de religion (ou d'une combinaison de tous ces &#233;l&#233;ments).[PARAGRAPH:2]Partager une langue, des coutumes, une histoire, et ainsi de suite, renforce la nation : le sentiment identitaire et communautaire r&#233;duit les dissensions internes, les conflits religieux ou politiques, etc. Malheureusement, la population qui ne partage pas la m&#234;me langue, les m&#234;mes coutumes et la m&#234;me histoire est souvent regard&#233;e avec d&#233;fiance, voire avec m&#233;pris, ce qui provoque le m&#233;contentement des minorit&#233;s et limite leur capacit&#233; &#224; contribuer &#224; la r&#233;ussite de la nation.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Eine Nation ist eine Gruppe von Menschen mit einer gemeinsamen Identit&#228;t. B&#252;rger einer Nation verbindet eine gemeinsame Sprache, die Geschichte, eine Religion oder eine Kombination verschiedener Aspekte.[PARAGRAPH:2]Haben die Mitglieder einer Nation eine gemeinsame Sprache und Kultur, entwickelt das Volk eine gemeinsame Identit&#228;t, die hilft, innere Unruhen oder religi&#246;se Auseinandersetzungen zu verhindern. Gleichzeitig treten die Menschen Angeh&#246;rigen anderer Kulturkreise allerdings oft mit Misstrauen und Geringsch&#228;tzung gegen&#252;ber. Dies f&#252;hrt nicht selten zur Isolierung von Minderheiten und zu Unruhen innerhalb der Bev&#246;lkerung.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Una "nazione" &#232; formata da persone che condividono una forma di identit&#224; comune. Una nazione pu&#242; essere legata dalla lingua, dai costumi, dalla storia o dalle credenze religiose (o da diverse combinazioni di questi elementi).[PARAGRAPH:2]La condivisione di lingue, costumi e storia fornisce a una nazione un grande senso di identit&#224; nella gente comune riducendo i conflitti interni, guerre civili o religiose. Sfortunatamente, i cittadini di lingua e costumi diversi, possono essere guardata con sospetto, diffidenza e disprezzo, suscitando infelicit&#224; e irrequietezza nelle minoranze e limitando la loro abilit&#224; di dare il proprio contributo alla societ&#224;.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]Una "naci&#243;n" es un grupo de gente unida por alguna identidad en com&#250;n. Las naciones pueden estar unidas por el idioma, las costumbres, la historia o la religi&#243;n (o por cualquier combinaci&#243;n de &#233;stos).[PARAGRAPH:2]La lengua, las costumbres, la historia y todos los elementos colectivos refuerzan a la naci&#243;n y le otorgan un sentido de unidad que reduce el descontento, las guerras civiles y religiosas, etc. Por desgracia, los ciudadanos con diferentes idiomas, costumbres y procedencias pueden ser objeto de desconfianza, sospecha y menosprecio, lo que alimenta el descontento de las minor&#237;as y limita su capacidad de contribuir en plenitud al desarrollo de la sociedad.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_NAVAL_SUPREMACY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]In the modern western countries, the European "Age of Sail" is the period in which international trade and naval warfare were both dominated by sailing ships. The age of sail mostly coincided with the age of discovery, from the 15th to the 18th century. After the 17th century, English naval maps stopped using the term of British Sea for the English Channel. From 15th to the 18th centuries, the period saw square rigged sailing ships carry European settlers to many parts of the world in one of the most important human migrations in recorded history. This period was marked by extensive exploration and colonization efforts on the part of European kingdoms. The sextant, developed in the 18th century, made more accurate charting of nautical position possible.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_OCCUPATION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Belligerent military occupation occurs when one nation's military occupies all or part of the territory of another nation or recognized belligerent.[PARAGRAPH:2]In most wars some territory of the losing side is placed under the authority of the hostile army. Most military occupations end with the cessation of hostilities. In some cases the occupied territory is returned and in others the land remains under the control of the occupying power but usually not as militarily occupied territory. The latter was the case of Germany after WWII, which ended up being split into two different nations.</English>
  <French>[TAB]L'occupation militaire d&#233;signe la pr&#233;sence d'une arm&#233;e &#233;trang&#232;re sur tout ou partie du territoire d'une autre nation ou d'un bellig&#233;rant reconnu.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dans la plupart des guerres, certains territoires du pays vaincu sont plac&#233;s sous l'autorit&#233; d'une arm&#233;e ennemie. La plupart des occupations militaires se terminent avec la cessation des hostilit&#233;s. Dans certains cas, le territoire occup&#233; est rendu et dans d'autres, il reste sous le contr&#244;le de la puissance occupante, mais plus en tant que territoire occup&#233; militairement. La derni&#232;re occupation fut celle de l'Allemagne apr&#232;s la Seconde Guerre mondiale, qui se termina par sa division en deux pays distincts.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Eine kriegerische milit&#228;rische Besatzung tritt dann ein, wenn die milit&#228;rischen Streitkr&#228;fte einer Nation das Territorium einer anderen Nation oder eines Kriegsgegners vollst&#228;ndig oder teilweise besetzen.[PARAGRAPH:2]In den meisten Kriegen wurde ein Teil des Territoriums der Verliererseite der Befehlsgewalt der feindlichen Milit&#228;rs unterstellt. Dabei beendeten die milit&#228;rischen Besatzungen in der Regel gleichzeitig auch die Feindseligkeiten zwischen den Kriegsparteien. In manchen F&#228;llen wurde das Besatzungsgebiet sp&#228;ter wieder zur&#252;ckgegeben, in anderen verblieb es in der Hand der Besatzungsmacht, normalerweise aber nicht mehr als milit&#228;risch besetztes Territorium. Letzteres ereignete sich nach dem 2. Weltkrieg in Deutschland und endete damit, dass Deutschland bis zur Wiedervereinigung im Jahr 1990 in zwei verschiedene Staaten aufgeteilt war.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]L'occupazione militare si ha quando l'esercito di una nazione occupa tutto o parte del territorio di un'altra nazione o fazione ostile.[PARAGRAPH:2]In molte guerre parte del territorio della fazione perdente viene posto sotto l'autorit&#224; dell'esercito ostile. La maggior parte delle occupazioni militari terminano con la cessazione delle ostilit&#224;. In alcuni casi il territorio occupato viene restituito, mentre in altri rimane sotto il controllo della potenza occupante, anche se solitamente non come territorio occupato militarmente. Questo fu il caso della Germania dopo la Seconda Guerra Mondiale, che fin&#236; con l'essere divisa in due diverse nazioni.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La ocupaci&#243;n militar se produce cuando un ej&#233;rcito beligerante de una naci&#243;n ocupa todo o parte del territorio de otra naci&#243;n.[PARAGRAPH:2]En muchas guerras, parte del territorio del bando derrotado es sometido a la autoridad del ej&#233;rcito hostil. La mayor parte de las ocupaciones militares finalizan con el cese de las hostilidades. En algunos casos, el territorio ocupado es devuelto, pero en otros la zona permanece bajo control de la potencia enemiga, aunque ya no como territorio ocupado militarmente. El &#250;ltimo fue el caso de Alemania tras la II Guerra Mundial, que acab&#243; siendo divida entre dos naciones diferentes.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_ORGANIZED_RELIGION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]An organized religion is one in which there is a central authority which interprets or determines theology, which decides which ceremonies are to be performed at which times, and which appoints priests or holy men to keep worshipers on the correct path. The central authority may be a rigid and powerful hierarchy with great religious and secular power, or it may be a group of elders who meet periodically to discuss matters of importance to their members.[PARAGRAPH:2]An organized religion can be a mighty thing, more powerful than kings or despots. Its followers may provide it with great wealth, and may construct mighty edifices in their gods' honor. Usually, however, organized religions are less powerful than that and must live in uneasy harmony with the local secular governments. </English>
  <French>[TAB]Une religion organis&#233;e dispose d'une autorit&#233; centralis&#233;e qui interpr&#232;te et d&#233;termine la th&#233;ologie, qui d&#233;cide quand et comment sont organis&#233;es les c&#233;r&#233;monies du culte et qui se charge de nommer les pr&#234;tres et autres hommes d'&#233;glise qui dirigeront les fid&#232;les. L'autorit&#233; centrale peut prendre la forme d'une hi&#233;rarchie rigide et puissante ayant un pouvoir &#224; la fois religieux et la&#239;c. Elle peut aussi &#234;tre compos&#233;e d'un groupe d'anciens qui se r&#233;unissent r&#233;guli&#232;rement pour discuter des probl&#232;mes que rencontre leur communaut&#233;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Une religion organis&#233;e peut &#234;tre puissante et avoir davantage de pouvoir qu'un roi ou qu'un despote. Ses fid&#232;les peuvent la rendre riche et b&#226;tir des &#233;difices majestueux en l'honneur de leur Dieu. Cependant, les religions organis&#233;es sont rarement aussi puissantes et doivent g&#233;n&#233;ralement vivre tant bien que mal en harmonie avec un v&#233;ritable pouvoir la&#239;que. </French>
  <German>[TAB]Eine organisierte Religion hat eine zentrale Autorit&#228;t, die f&#252;r die Interpretation der Theologie, die Liturgie, die Priesterweihe und Heiligsprechungen verantwortlich ist. Diese zentrale Autorit&#228;t ist nicht selten eine einflussreiche Beh&#246;rde mit betr&#228;chtlicher geistlicher und weltlicher Macht.[PARAGRAPH:2]Organisierte Religionen konnten sehr m&#228;chtig werden, m&#228;chtiger noch als K&#246;nige oder Despoten. Oft h&#228;uften ihre Gl&#228;ubigen gro&#223;e Reicht&#252;mer an und errichteten zu Ehren ihres Gottes pr&#228;chtige Geb&#228;ude. Heute ist der politische und religi&#246;se Einfluss organisierter Religionen allerdings eher gering.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]In una organizzazione religiosa esiste un'autorit&#224; centrale che interpreta o determina la teologia, che decide quando e quali cerimonie devono essere eseguite, che nomina i sacerdoti o gli uomini santi per mantenere i fedeli sulla retta via. L'autorit&#224; centrale pu&#242; essere una gerarchia potente e rigida di grandi religioni e potere secolare, oppure pu&#242; essere rappresentata da un gruppo di anziani che si incontrano periodicamente per discutere questioni importanti.[PARAGRAPH:2]Una organizzazione religiosa pu&#242; rappresentare un grande potere, pi&#249; di quello di un re o un despota: i seguaci possono fornire ricchezze e finanziare la realizzazione di grandi edifici in onore degli dei. Tuttavia, le organizzazioni religiose sono meno potenti e devono vivere in una difficile armonia con i governi locali laici.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]Una religi&#243;n organizada es una en la que existe una autoridad central que interpreta o establece la teolog&#237;a, decide qu&#233; ceremonias se llevan a cabo y nombra a los sacerdotes u hombres santos encargados de mantener al reba&#241;o en el recto camino. La autoridad central puede ser una jerarqu&#237;a r&#237;gida y poderosa dotada de gran poder religioso y secular o puede estar formada por un consejo de ancianos que se re&#250;ne peri&#243;dicamente para debatir todos los asuntos concernientes a sus fieles.[PARAGRAPH:2]Las religiones organizadas pueden ser muy poderosas, m&#225;s incluso que los reyes o los d&#233;spotas. Sus seguidores pueden proporcionarle enormes riquezas y erigir impresionantes edificios en honor a sus dioses.  Sin embargo, lo normal es que no sean tan poderosas y se vean obligadas a convivir en un estado de complicada armon&#237;a con los poderes seculares. </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PACIFISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Pacifism is the religious belief that all conflict is against the will of God. Man must not fight against his fellow man. If a person slaps your face, simply turn the other cheek. Basically, what happens to a person in this world really doesn't matter much at all: if a bully takes your stuff or kills you and you don't fight back, you will gain your reward in heaven (or in your next incarnation). The bully may enjoy his ill-gotten gains for a few paltry years in this world, but he will suffer tenfold in the next.[PARAGRAPH:2]Pacifism seems to enjoy popularity among people or nations who have little power of their own, people who cannot physically resist their oppressors with any hope of success. Once such people gain power and gain some measure of control over their destinies, however, they often discard their pacifism for more militant beliefs.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le pacifisme est la croyance religieuse selon laquelle tout conflit va &#224; l'encontre de la volont&#233; de Dieu. Les hommes ne doivent pas se battre entre eux. Si quelqu'un vous frappe, tendez l'autre joue. En r&#233;sum&#233;, ce qu'un homme subit dans ce monde importe peu : si une brute vous vole ou vous assassine et que vous ne vous d&#233;fendez pas, vous acc&#233;derez au paradis (ou &#224; votre prochaine r&#233;incarnation). La brute, elle, profitera de ses crimes pendant quelques ann&#233;es, mais conna&#238;tra mille souffrances apr&#232;s sa mort.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le pacifisme est tr&#232;s populaire au sein des peuples et des nations qui ont peu de pouvoir et ne peuvent pas r&#233;sister physiquement &#224; leurs agresseurs. Bien souvent, ces peuples, une fois qu'ils ont acquis un certain pouvoir et qu'ils ma&#238;trisent quelque peu leur destin&#233;e, renoncent au pacifisme.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Pazifismus lehrt, dass jeder Streit gegen den Willen Gottes verst&#246;&#223;t, und verbietet den Menschen, gegeneinander zu k&#228;mpfen. "Wenn dich jemand schl&#228;gt, halte ihm auch die andere Wange hin" ist ein typisches Konzept des Pazifismus: Wird ein Mensch get&#246;tet, kann er sicher sein, dass er im Himmel (oder in seiner n&#228;chsten Inkarnation) f&#252;r alles entsch&#228;digt wird. Der M&#246;rder hingegen kann sein armseliges Leben zwar noch einige Jahre genie&#223;en, muss nach seinem Tod aber zehnfach f&#252;r seine Taten b&#252;&#223;en.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Pazifismus ist vor allem in schwachen oder unterdr&#252;ckten L&#228;ndern weit verbreitet. Gewinnt eine Gesellschaft aber an Einfluss, weicht der Pazifismus nicht selten militanteren Konzepten.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il pacifismo &#232; il credo religioso secondo il quale tutti i conflitti sono contrari al volere di Dio. Gli uomini non devono combattere tra loro; se una persona ti d&#224; uno schiaffo, porgi l'altra guancia. Fondamentalmente, ci&#242; che accade a una persona in questo mondo non conta molto: se si viene derubati o uccisi e non si reagisce, si conquister&#224; il Paradiso (magari nella successiva incarnazione). Il ladro o l'assassino potranno godersi i risultati del loro operato in questa vita, ma soffriranno dieci volte tanto in quella successiva.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il pacifismo gode di molta popolarit&#224; nelle nazioni deboli, i cui abitanti non potrebbero opporsi fisicamente agli oppressori. Quando queste persone conquistano il potere e il controllo sui propri destini, tuttavia, spesso abbandonano il pacifismo in cambio di un credo pi&#249; battagliero.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El pacifismo es la creencia religiosa en que todo conflicto contradice la voluntad de Dios. El hombre no debe luchar contra el hombre. Si alguien te abofetea, ofr&#233;cele la otra mejilla. B&#225;sicamente, lo que le ocurre en el mundo real a la persona que lo practica no tiene demasiada importancia: si alguien te roba o te asesina sin que te defiendas, recibir&#225;s tu recompensa en el cielo (o en tu pr&#243;xima encarnaci&#243;n). El otro puede disfrutar de lo robado durante unos pocos a&#241;os, pero al final acabar&#225; pag&#225;ndolo con creces en la otra vida.[PARAGRAPH:2]El pacifismo goza de gran predicamento entre aquellos pueblos o naciones que no poseen mucho poder y que son incapaces de ofrecer resistencia a sus opresores. Sin embargo, en cuanto su poder aumenta y obtienen alg&#250;n control sobre su destino, suelen renunciar al pacifismo para abrazar creencias m&#225;s belicosas.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PAGANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]"Paganism" describes religions that believe in the holiness of all things around them - rocks, trees, animals, clouds and so forth - rather than in specific concepts or beings. Pagans believe in multitudes of gods, that the gods are all around them, causing the sunset, the rising of bread, and the success of the hunt.[PARAGRAPH:2]A pagan seeks to remain in harmony with the natural world around him or her. The pagan doesn't look to appease a distant deity or hierarchy of deities who control his or her destiny. To a pagan, the gods are all around him or her, in plain sight every day. </English>
  <French>[TAB]On parle de "Paganisme" pour les religions qui croient au caract&#232;re sacr&#233; de tout ce qui nous entoure : les rochers, les arbres, les animaux, les nuages, etc. Les pa&#239;ens ont de nombreuses divinit&#233;s. Ils croient que les dieux vivent parmi nous, et sont la cause du coucher du soleil, de la pousse des plantes ou du succ&#232;s de la chasse.[PARAGRAPH:2]Un pa&#239;en cherche &#224; rester en harmonie avec le monde naturel. Le pa&#239;en ne cherche pas &#224; apaiser une divinit&#233; distante qui contr&#244;lerait sa destin&#233;e, il est convaincu que les dieux nous entourent et vivent parmi nous. </French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Heidentum" umfasst Religionen, die an die Heiligkeit aller Dinge (Steine, B&#228;ume, Tiere, Wolken) und nicht an abstrakte Gottheiten glauben. Im heidnischen Polytheismus sind verschiedene G&#246;tter f&#252;r den Sonnenaufgang, die Ernte, die Jagd usw. verantwortlich.[PARAGRAPH:2]Heiden leben meist in Einklang mit der Natur und verehren (wie bereits erw&#228;hnt) keine abstrakten Gottheiten. In den Augen eines Heiden ist der Mensch st&#228;ndig von - jederzeit sichtbaren - G&#246;ttern umgeben.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il "paganesimo" racchiude tutte le religioni che credono nella santit&#224; delle cose che ci circondano (un sasso, un albero, gli animali, le nuvole), piuttosto che in identit&#224; o concetti specifici. I pagani credono in una moltitudine di divinit&#224;, che li circondano e che sono responsabili dei tramonti, della lievitazione del pane e del successo nella caccia.[PARAGRAPH:2]Un pagano tenta di vivere in armonia con la natura circostante, senza cercare di soddisfare divinit&#224; che controllino il proprio destino. Agli occhi di un pagano, le divinit&#224; sono nelle cose tangibili di tutti i giorni.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El t&#233;rmino "paganismo" describe a aquellas religiones que creen en la divinidad de todas las cosas (rocas, &#225;rboles, animales, nubes, etc.) en lugar de en conceptos o criaturas espec&#237;ficas. Sus seguidores creen en la existencia de multitud de dioses, cuya presencia a su alrededor es la causa de la puesta del sol, el crecimiento del trigo y el &#233;xito en la caza.[PARAGRAPH:2]Los paganos procuran mantenerse en armon&#237;a con el mundo natural que los rodea. No se preocupan por complacer a lejanas deidades o panteones supuestamente due&#241;os de su destino. Consideran que los dioses est&#225;n en todo momento a su alrededor, a la vista. </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PANTHEON_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A pantheon (literally "a temple of all gods", "of or common to all gods") is a set of all the gods of a particular polytheistic religion or mythology.[PARAGRAPH:2]Max Weber's 1922 opus, Economy and Society, discusses the link between a pantheon of gods and the development of monotheism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Pantheon can also refer to a temple or sacred building explicitly dedicated to "all deities", avoiding the difficulty of giving an exhaustive list. The most known such structure is the Pantheon of Rome, built in the year 27 BC. The building was dedicated to "all gods" as a gesture embracing the religious syncretism in the increasingly multicultural Roman Empire, with subjects worshipping gods from many cultures and traditions. The building was later renovated for use as a Christian church in 609 under Pope Boniface IV.[PARAGRAPH:2]Since the 16th century "pantheon" also refers in a secular sense to the set of a society's exalted persons. For example "Mick Jagger was exalted into the pantheon of rock megastars".</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_POLICE_STATE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Under a police state the government maintains strict control over its populace by means of a police force (and often a "secret" police force). Civil liberties are denied and those who voice opinions contrary to the government are subject to punishments ranging from imprisonment to death.[PARAGRAPH:2]The strength of police states lies in their ability to control the population in bad times, forcing them to do what's necessary no matter what their personal opinions of the matter may be. It has been argued, for example, that Stalin's Soviet Union would not have survived the German assault in World War II if he didn't have the entire power of the state under his dictatorial control. The weakness of the police state comes from its tendency to crush individual initiative and inventiveness. Police states are often subject to excesses of paranoia; they see everyone as against them and constantly implement more repressive policies to remain in power.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Au sein d'un Etat policier, le gouvernement exerce un contr&#244;le important sur la population par le biais des forces de police (souvent aid&#233;es par une police "secr&#232;te"). Les libert&#233;s civiques n'existent plus et les opposants au r&#233;gime sont s&#233;v&#232;rement punis par des peines de prison ou des ex&#233;cutions sommaires.[PARAGRAPH:2]La force d'un Etat policier repose dans sa capacit&#233; &#224; ma&#238;triser la population m&#234;me dans les p&#233;riodes difficiles et &#224; l'obliger &#224; faire ce qui doit &#234;tre fait, quelle que soit l'opinion des gens. Certains pensent, par exemple, que l'Union Sovi&#233;tique n'aurait pas pu r&#233;sister aux arm&#233;es de Hitler si Staline n'avait pas exerc&#233; un pouvoir total sur l'&#233;tat. La faiblesse de l'Etat policier vient de sa tendance &#224; &#233;touffer l'esprit d'initiative et la cr&#233;ativit&#233;. Les Etats policiers sont souvent victimes de parano&#239;a excessive. Ils voient des ennemis partout et doivent sans cesse renforcer la r&#233;pression polici&#232;re pour conserver le pouvoir.</French>
  <German>[TAB]In einem Polizeistaat h&#228;lt die Regierung das Volk mit starken Polizeikr&#228;ften (und/oder einer Geheimpolizei) unter Kontrolle. Es gibt keine zivilen Freiheiten. Jede Kritik der Regierung wird mit Gef&#228;ngnis oder dem Tode bestraft.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die St&#228;rke eines Polizeistaats ist die absolute Kontrolle der Bev&#246;lkerung in schlechten Zeiten und die M&#246;glichkeit, den B&#252;rgern alle erforderlichen Ma&#223;nahmen (unabh&#228;ngig von der Meinung des Einzelnen) aufzuzwingen. Vermutlich h&#228;tte die Sowjetunion dem Angriff der Deutschen w&#228;hrend des 2. Weltkriegs nicht standgehalten, wenn Stalin nicht den gesamten Staatsapparat kontrolliert h&#228;tte. Hauptkritikpunkt des Polizeistaats ist die Unterdr&#252;ckung jeglicher Eigeninitiative der B&#252;rger. Zudem neigen Polizeistaaten dazu, ihre Macht mit immer brutaleren Repressalien zu festigen.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]In uno stato di polizia, il governo esercita uno stretto controllo sulla popolazione, mediante l'impiego di forze di polizia (spesso reparti "segreti"). I diritti civili sono negati e coloro che si esprimono contro il governo sono soggetti a punizioni che vanno dalla prigione alla morte.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il punto di forza degli stati di polizia &#232; il controllo sulla popolazione durante i periodi avversi, che costringe i cittadini a fare ci&#242; di cui c'&#232; bisogno, indipendentemente dalla propria opinione. Si presume che l'Unione Sovietica non avrebbe potuto reggere all'assalto tedesco durante la Seconda Guerra Mondiale se il potere non fosse stato saldamente nelle mani del dittatore Stalin. Il punto debole di un governo di questo genere &#232; la tendenza a censurare l'iniziativa e l'inventiva individuale. Gli stati di polizia sono spesso soggetti a eccessi di paranoia: viene visto tutto come un pericolo e vengono quindi applicate politiche ancora pi&#249; repressive per rimanere al potere.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]En un estado policial, el gobierno mantiene un control estricto de la poblaci&#243;n por medio de un cuerpo de polic&#237;a (normalmente secreta). Las libertades civiles se recortan y aqu&#233;llos que expresan voces contrarias a la posici&#243;n del gobierno pueden ser encarcelados o incluso ejecutados.[PARAGRAPH:2]La principal ventaja de los estados policiales es su capacidad de controlar a la poblaci&#243;n en los malos tiempos, oblig&#225;ndola a cumplir con su deber al margen de sus opiniones personales. Por ejemplo, se ha dicho que la Uni&#243;n Sovi&#233;tica no hubiese soportado el ataque alem&#225;n en la Segunda Guerra Mundial de no haber sido porque Stalin ten&#237;a todo el poder del estado en su mano. La principal debilidad de esta forma de gobierno radica en su tendencia a aplastar la iniciativa personal y la inventiva. Los estados policiales suelen adolecer de excesos de paranoia; creen que todo el mundo est&#225; contra ellos e imponen constantes medidas represivas para mantenerse en el poder.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PUBLIC_WELFARE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]An early version of the welfare state appeared in China during the Song Dynasty in the 11th century. Prime Minister Wang Anshi believed that the state was responsible for providing its citizens the essentials for a decent living standard. Accordingly, under his direction the state initiated agricultural loans to relieve the farming peasants. He appointed boards to regulate wages and plan pensions for the aged and unemployed. These reforms were known as the "new laws," New Policies, or xin fa.[PARAGRAPH:2]Modern welfare states developed through a gradual process beginning in the late 19th century and continuing through the 20th. They differed from previous schemes of poverty relief due to their relatively universal coverage. The development of social insurance in Germany under Bismarck was particularly influential. Some schemes, like those in Scandinavia, were based largely in the development of autonomous, mutualist provision of benefits. Others were founded on state provision. The term was not, however, applied to all states offering social protection. The sociologist T.H. Marshall identified the welfare state as a distinctive combination of democracy, welfare and capitalism.[PARAGRAPH:2]Examples of early welfare states in the modern world are Sweden (Folkhemmet), Germany, the Netherlands, and New Zealand in the 1930s. Germany is generally held to be the first social welfare state. Changed attitudes in reaction to the Great Depression were instrumental in the move to the welfare state in many countries, a harbinger of new times where "cradle-to-grave" services became a reality after the poverty of the Depression. During the Great Depression, it was seen as an alternative "middle way" between communism and fascism. In the period following the Second World War, many countries in Europe moved from partial or selective provision of social services to relatively comprehensive coverage of the population.[PARAGRAPH:2]The activities of present-day welfare states extend to the provision of both cash welfare benefits (such as old-age pensions or unemployment benefits) and in-kind welfare services (such as health or childcare services). Through these provisions, welfare states can affect the distribution of wellbeing and personal autonomy among their citizens, as well as influencing how their citizens consume and how they spend their time.[PARAGRAPH:2]After the discovery and inflow of the oil revenue, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, and United Arab Emirates all became welfare states. However, the services are strictly for citizens and these countries do not accept immigrants; even those born in these countries do not qualify for citizenship unless they are of the parentage belonging to their respective countries.[PARAGRAPH:2]The beginning of the modern welfare state was in 1911 when David Lloyd George suggested everyone in work should pay national insurance contribution for unemployment and health benefits from work.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1942, the 'Social Insurance and Allied Services' was created by Sir William Beveridge in order to aid those who were in need of help, or in poverty. Beverage worked as a volunteer for the poor, and set up national insurance. He stated that 'All people of working age should pay a weekly national insurance contribution. In return, benefits would be paid to people who were sick, unemployed, retired or widowed.' The basic assumptions of the report were the National Health Service, which provided free health care to the UK. The Universal Child Benefit was a scheme to to give child benefits, which encouraged people to have children so they could afford to keep them alive and not for them to starve to death. This was particularly useful after the second world war, where the population in England declined, so encouragement for new babies was encouraged, which sparked the baby boom. The impact of the report was huge and 600,000 copies were made. He recommended to the government that they should find ways of tackling the five giants, being Want, Disease, Ignorance, Squalor and Idleness. He argued to cure these problems, the government should provide adequate income to people, adequate health care, adequate education, adequate housing and adequate employment. Before 1939, health care had to be paid for, this was done through a vast network of friendly societies, trade unions and other insurance companies which counted the vast majority of the UK working population as members. These friendly societies provided insurance for sickness, unemployment and invalidity, therefore providing people with an income when they were unable to work. But because of the 1942 Berveridge Report, in 5th July 1948, the National Insurance Act, National Assistance Act and National Health Service Act came into force, thus this is the day that the modern UK welfare state was founded.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_REPRESENTATION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]In a representative government the population elects a number of "representatives" to run the government on their behalf. The representatives serve for a limited time and then must stand for reelection. These representatives form a group (council, parliament, senate, etc.) that determines and implements government policy. In some cases the government may have a monarch at its head, while in other cases there may be a separately elected ruler (as in the United States), or the representatives themselves may elect one or more of their members to be the executive power.[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
  <French>[TAB]Avec un gouvernement repr&#233;sentatif, le peuple &#233;lit un certain nombre de "repr&#233;sentants" qui dirigent l'&#233;tat en leur nom. Les repr&#233;sentants sont nomm&#233;s pour une dur&#233;e limit&#233;e, et doivent donc r&#233;guli&#232;rement faire face &#224; des &#233;lections. Ces repr&#233;sentants forment des groupes (conseil, parlement, s&#233;nat, etc.) qui d&#233;terminent et ex&#233;cutent la politique du gouvernement. Dans certains cas, le gouvernement peut &#234;tre plac&#233; sous l'autorit&#233; d'un roi. Dans d'autres, le dirigeant est &#233;lu s&#233;par&#233;ment (comme en France), ou alors, ce sont les repr&#233;sentants qui &#233;lisent un ou plusieurs de leurs membres pour former le pouvoir ex&#233;cutif.[PARAGRAPH:2]</French>
  <German>[TAB]In einer repr&#228;sentativen Demokratie w&#228;hlt das Volk so genannte "Volksvertreter", die dann in seinem Namen die Regierungsgesch&#228;fte leiten. Die Vertreter werden f&#252;r eine bestimmte Amtszeit gew&#228;hlt und m&#252;ssen sich anschlie&#223;end der Wiederwahl stellen. Die Volksvertreter bilden einen Rat, ein Parlament oder einen Senat und setzen innerhalb dieser Gruppe die Regierungspolitik um. Der Vorsitzende der Volksvertreter kann ein Monarch oder (wie in den USA) ein ebenfalls vom Volk gew&#228;hltes Staatsoberhaupt sein. In einigen L&#228;ndern bestimmen die Volksvertreter selbst ein Staatsoberhaupt.[PARAGRAPH:2]</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]In un governo rappresentativo, il popolo elegge un numero di "rappresentanti", destinati a governare per un periodo di tempo definito, scaduto il quale sar&#224; necessario ricorrere nuovamente alle elezioni. Questi rappresentanti formano dei gruppi: consiglio, parlamento, senato, eccetera, che determinano e applicano la politica del governo. In alcuni casi, il governo pu&#242; sottostare a un monarca, mentre in altri casi pu&#242; esserci un singolo eletto (come negli Stati Uniti), oppure gli altri rappresentanti possono a loro volta eleggere ulteriori membri del gruppo, che esercitino il potere esecutivo.[PARAGRAPH:2]</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]En el gobierno representativo, la poblaci&#243;n elige a una serie de "representantes" para que gobiernen en su nombre. Estos representantes desempe&#241;an su labor durante un tiempo limitado y luego deben presentarse a la reelecci&#243;n. Conforman un colegio (consejo, parlamento, senado, etc.) que planifica y ejecuta la pol&#237;tica gubernamental. En algunos casos, el gobierno puede estar encabezado por un monarca, mientras que en otros hay un cabeza de estado electo (como en Estados Unidos), o los representantes eligen a uno de ellos para ostentar el poder ejecutivo.[PARAGRAPH:2]</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_REPUBLIC_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]In a republic, the head of state is not a monarch and there are no legal privileges for the nobility. The exact form of government can vary widely, from absolute despotism to direct democracy, but the most important difference between a republic and any form of monarchy is the much-diminished role of family and lineage in government.[PARAGRAPH:2]Before the French Revolution, a republic in Europe was an aberration. The state enjoyed none of the external security provided by royal family ties. Internally, the succession was decided to some extent by merit, even if this often meant merely that the man with the best ability to take power would do so.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_RESETTLEMENT_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]"Resettlement" literally means the transportation of a group of people to a new settlement and the populating of a new area. Although migration has featured throughout human history and prehistory, the word settler (synonymous with terms like pioneers and colonists) is often used in relation to modern or early modern history.[PARAGRAPH:2]The reason for emigration of settlers varies, but often includes one or more factors such as: personal economic hardship; social, cultural, ethnic, or religious persecution; political oppression; or policies aimed at encouraging foreign settlement.</English>
  <French>[TAB]"Repeuplement" signifie litt&#233;ralement amener un groupe de personnes dans une nouvelle implantation pour peupler une zone. Bien que la migration soit une constante de la pr&#233;histoire et de l'histoire de l'humanit&#233;, le mot colon (synonyme de pionnier) est souvent utilis&#233; en relation avec l'histoire moderne ou contemporaine.[PARAGRAPH:2]Les raisons qui poussent &#224; &#233;migrer sont nombreuses, mais on retrouve souvent les difficult&#233;s &#233;conomiques personnelles, les pers&#233;cutions sociales, ethniques ou religieuses, l'oppression politique, ou des politiques encourageant la colonisation.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Umsiedlung" beschreibt den Umzug einer Gruppe von Menschen in ein neues Siedlungsgebiet bzw. die Bev&#246;lkerung neuer Gebiete. W&#228;hrend es derartige "V&#246;lkerwanderungen" in der gesamten Menschheitsgeschichte gegeben hat, wird der davon abgeleitete Begriff "Siedler" (Synonym f&#252;r Pionier und Kolonist) h&#228;ufig in Bezug auf die moderne bzw. fr&#252;hmoderne Geschichte verwendet.[PARAGRAPH:2]Es gibt unterschiedliche Gr&#252;nde f&#252;r die Ab- bzw. Auswanderung von Siedlern, meist spielen dabei jedoch folgende Faktoren eine Rolle: pers&#246;nliches bzw. wirtschaftliches Elend, soziale, kulturelle, ethnische oder religi&#246;se Verfolgung, politische Unterdr&#252;ckung oder die politische F&#246;rderung fremder Siedlungen.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]&amp;quot;Risistemazione&amp;quot; sta a indicare il trasporto di un gruppo di persone in un nuovo insediamento e il popolamento di una nuova zona. Anche se le migrazioni hanno avuto luogo in tutta la storia e preistoria umana, la parola colonizzatore (o anche pioniere o colono) &#232; spesso utilizzata in relazione alla storia moderna.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le ragioni per l'emigrazione dei coloni sono diverse, ma spesso includono uno o pi&#249; fattori come: forti problemi economici; persecuzione sociale, culturale, etnica o religiosa; oppressione politica, oppure politiche che incoraggiano l'insediamento all'estero.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El &amp;quot;reasentamiento&amp;quot; consiste en el traslado de un grupo de personas a un nuevo enclave para poblar una nueva zona. Aunque la migraci&#243;n ha existido en toda la historia, e incluso en la prehistoria, el t&#233;rmino colono, en ocasiones sin&#243;nimo de pionero, se suele utilizar en contextos de la historia moderna o contempor&#225;nea.[PARAGRAPH:2]Los motivos de la migraci&#243;n colonial son variados, pero a menudo incluyen dos o m&#225;s factores, como penurias econ&#243;micas, persecuci&#243;n social, cultural, &#233;tnica o religiosa, opresi&#243;n pol&#237;tica o pol&#237;ticas potenciadoras de la emigraci&#243;n o la inmigraci&#243;n.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SCHOLASTICISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Scholasticism is a method of critical thought which dominated teaching by the academics (scholastics, or schoolmen) of medieval universities in Europe from about 1100-1500, and a program of employing that method in articulating and defending orthodoxy in an increasingly pluralistic context. It originated as an outgrowth of, and a departure from, Christian monastic schools.[PARAGRAPH:2]Not so much a philosophy or a theology as a method of learning, scholasticism places a strong emphasis on dialectical reasoning to extend knowledge by inference, and to resolve contradictions. Scholastic thought is also known for rigorous conceptual analysis and the careful drawing of distinctions. In the classroom and in writing, it often takes the form of explicit disputation: a topic drawn from the tradition is broached in the form of a question, opponents' responses are given, a counterproposal is argued and opponent's arguments rebutted. Because of its emphasis on rigorous dialectical method, scholasticism was eventually applied to many other fields of study.[PARAGRAPH:2]As a program, scholasticism began as an attempt at harmonization on the part of medieval Christian thinkers: to harmonize the various authorities of their own tradition, and to reconcile Christian theology with classical and late antiquity philosophy, especially that of Aristotle but also of Neoplatonism.[PARAGRAPH:2]The main figures of scholasticism historically are Anselm of Canterbury, Peter Abelard, Alexander of Hales, Albertus Magnus, Duns Scotus, William of Ockham, Bonaventure and Thomas Aquinas. Thomas Aquinas's masterwork, the Summa Theologica, is often seen as the highest fruit of Scholasticism. Important work in the scholastic tradition has been carried on, however, well past Aquinas' time, for instance by Francisco Su&#225;rez and Molina, and also among Lutheran and Reformed thinkers.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SECULARISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Secularism is the principle of separation between government institutions and the persons mandated to represent the State from religious institutions and religious dignitaries. In one sense, secularism may assert the right to be free from religious rule and teachings, and the right to freedom from governmental imposition of religion upon the people within a state that is neutral on matters of belief. (See also separation of church and state and La&#239;cit&#233;.) In another sense, it refers to the view that human activities and decisions, especially political ones, should be unbiased by religious influence. Some scholars are now arguing that the very idea of secularism will change.[PARAGRAPH:2]Secularism draws its intellectual roots from Greek and Roman philosophers such as Marcus Aurelius and Epicurus; medieval Muslim polymaths such as Ibn Rushd; Enlightenment thinkers such as Denis Diderot, Voltaire, Baruch Spinoza, John Locke, James Madison, Thomas Jefferson, and Thomas Paine; and more recent freethinkers, agnostics, and atheists such as Robert Ingersoll and Bertrand Russell.[PARAGRAPH:2]The purposes and arguments in support of secularism vary widely. In European laicism, it has been argued that secularism is a movement toward modernization, and away from traditional religious values (also known as secularization). This type of secularism, on a social or philosophical level, has often occurred while maintaining an official state church or other state support of religion. In the United States, some argue that state secularism has served to a greater extent to protect religion and the religious from governmental interference, while secularism on a social level is less prevalent. Within countries as well, differing political movements support secularism for varying reasons.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SERFDOM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Serfdom is a more "enlightened" form of slavery in that the power of the master is not absolute and the serfs are accorded a certain number of rights. The specific rights and obligations of masters and serfs vary significantly over time and from place to place. In some societies, the master had the right to control every aspect of a serf's life except that he couldn't kill the serf without just cause; in others, the serfs had the rights to marry and to inherit wealth and to a certain amount of self-government, but they could not leave the land without their lord's permission.[PARAGRAPH:2]The basic premise of serfdom is that one group of people are superior to another, and that they have the political and god-given right to control the other group's destiny. Thus serfdom only makes sense if one agrees with the group currently in power about who is superior to whom. </English>
  <French>[TAB]Le servage est une forme plus "&#233;clair&#233;e" d'esclavage, dans laquelle le ma&#238;tre n'a pas un pouvoir absolu, et le serf dispose de certains droits. Les droits et obligations du ma&#238;tre et de l'esclave varient de mani&#232;re significative selon l'&#233;poque et le lieu. Dans certaines soci&#233;t&#233;s, le ma&#238;tre avait le droit de contr&#244;ler tous les aspects de la vie du serf, mais ne pouvait pas le tuer sans raison. Ailleurs, les serfs avaient le droit de se marier, de transmettre leur patrimoine et disposaient d'une certaine autonomie, mais ils ne pouvaient pas quitter leur terre sans l'accord de leur seigneur.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le principe de base du servage est qu'il existe un groupe d'individus sup&#233;rieurs aux autres. Ils ont politiquement et id&#233;ologiquement le droit de contr&#244;ler la destin&#233;e des autres. Ainsi, le servage n'a de sens que si la sup&#233;riorit&#233; des uns est accept&#233;e par les autres. </French>
  <German>[TAB]Die Leibeigenschaft ist eine Form der Sklaverei. Allerdings hat der Meister keine absolute Macht &#252;ber den Leibeigenen, zumal diesem gewisse Rechte zugestanden werden. Die Rechte und Verpflichtungen von Meister und Leibeigenem sind im Allgemeinen sehr verschieden. In einigen L&#228;ndern kontrolliert der Meister jeden Aspekt im Leben seines Leibeigenen. Lediglich dessen grundlose Ermordung ist dem Meister untersagt. In anderen L&#228;ndern darf der Leibeigene heiraten, ist erbberechtigt und in vielerlei Hinsicht sein eigener Herr. Allerdings darf er das Land ohne die Zustimmung seines Herrn nicht verlassen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Voraussetzung der Leibeigenschaft ist eine Gesellschaftsschicht, die das politische bzw. gottgegebene Recht hat, &#252;ber das Schicksal einer untergeordneten Schicht zu bestimmen. Daher ist die Leibeigenschaft nur praktikabel, wenn &#252;ber die herrschenden Machtverh&#228;ltnisse Klarheit besteht.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La servit&#249; &#232; una forma di schiavit&#249; pi&#249; "illuminata": il potere del padrone non &#232; assoluto e al servo vengono accordati un certo numero di diritti. Obblighi e rapporti tra padrone e servo sono mutati nel corso del tempo, a seconda delle epoche e delle necessit&#224;. In alcune societ&#224;, il padrone aveva il diritto di controllare qualsiasi aspetto della vita di un servo, tranne per il fatto che non poteva ucciderlo senza una giusta causa; da altre parti invece, i servi potevano sposarsi e tentare di prosperare, senza per&#242; poter abbandonare la terra, se non con il permesso del padrone.[PARAGRAPH:2]Secondo i principi della servit&#249;, un gruppo &#232; superiore a un altro poich&#233; ha il diritto divino di controllare il destino degli altri. Questo principio &#232; valido solo se un gruppo acconsente di essere inferiore a un altro attualmente in potere.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La servidumbre es una forma "m&#225;s humanitaria" de esclavitud, en la que el poder del amo no es tan absoluto y los siervos conservan determinados derechos. Los derechos y obligaciones de amos y siervos variaban significativamente en funci&#243;n del tiempo y el lugar. En algunas sociedades, el amo ten&#237;a derecho a controlar todos los aspectos de la vida de sus siervos (aunque no pod&#237;a quitarles la vida sin una causa justificada), mientras que en otras los siervos ten&#237;an derecho a contraer matrimonio y heredar, y pose&#237;an un cierto grado de autogobierno, si bien no pod&#237;an abandonar la tierra sin el permiso de su amo.[PARAGRAPH:2]La premisa b&#225;sica que sustenta el sistema de servidumbre es que un grupo es superior a otro y por tanto le asiste el derecho, tanto pol&#237;tico como divino, a controlar el destino de &#233;ste. Por consiguiente, la servidumbre solo tiene sentido en caso de que todos est&#233;n de acuerdo en qui&#233;n es superior a qui&#233;n. </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SLAVERY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Slavery is a system whereby some people are judged far inferior to others and are treated as objects or possessions, with no more rights than those afforded to chairs or cattle. Slavery has existed as long as human history, from the earliest primitive times to the enlightened days of Greece and Rome and right up until today. Sometimes convicted criminals were made into slaves. Sometimes captured enemies of the state were enslaved. Sometimes people of a specific race or coloration were enslaved. In some civilizations a person could purchase their freedom or were allotted it after being enslaved for a specific period of time.[PARAGRAPH:2]The advantage of slavery is that it allows people to be forced to do jobs that they would otherwise refuse to do without adequate compensation. Cheap labor results in concentration of wealth and thus the creation of great buildings and temples or the maintenance of large professional armies. Aside from its basic moral repugnance, the disadvantages of slavery are numerous: it corrupts both slave and master, it badly underutilizes the intelligence and creativity of the subject people, and it almost inevitably leads to revolts and internal strife. </English>
  <French>[TAB]L'esclavagisme est un syst&#232;me par lequel une cat&#233;gorie de gens est consid&#233;r&#233;e comme tr&#232;s inf&#233;rieure. Ces derniers sont trait&#233;s comme des objets ou des biens, et n'ont aucun droit si ce n'est ceux accord&#233;s aux chaises ou au b&#233;tail. L'esclavage est aussi vieux que l'humanit&#233; ; il &#233;tait d&#233;j&#224; pr&#233;sent dans les civilisations primitives, &#233;tait pratiqu&#233; dans la Gr&#232;ce et la Rome antiques, et perdure encore aujourd'hui. Les gens r&#233;duits en esclavage &#233;taient les criminels, les ennemis vaincus, ou les gens de telle ou telle origine. Dans certaines civilisations, les individus pouvaient racheter leur libert&#233;, ou la r&#233;cup&#233;raient automatiquement apr&#232;s un certain de temps.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'avantage de l'esclavage est qu'il permet de forcer des gens &#224; accomplir certaines t&#226;ches qu'ils auraient sinon refus&#233;es de faire sans &#234;tre correctement r&#233;mun&#233;r&#233;s. Cette main-d'oeuvre bon march&#233; permet de concentrer la richesse et de cr&#233;er de somptueux b&#226;timents et lieux de culte ou d'entretenir de vastes arm&#233;es. En plus d'&#234;tre moralement r&#233;pugnant, l'esclavage a de nombreux inconv&#233;nients : il corrompt autant le ma&#238;tre que l'esclave, il sous-exploite l'intelligence et la cr&#233;ativit&#233; des individus soumis, et conduit presque in&#233;vitablement &#224; la r&#233;volte et aux conflits internes. </French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Sklaverei" beschreibt ein System, in dem Menschen als minderwertig betrachtet werden und kaum mehr Rechte als ein Stuhl oder ein St&#252;ck Vieh genie&#223;en. Die Sklaverei ist so alt wie die Menschheit selbst. Hielten sich zun&#228;chst primitive St&#228;mme Sklaven, bl&#252;hte bald auch im aufgekl&#228;rten Griechenland und im antiken Rom der Sklavenhandel. Sklaven waren in der Regel verurteilte Verbrecher, Kriegsgefangene, Angeh&#246;rige anderer V&#246;lker oder Menschen einer bestimmten Hautfarbe. In einigen Kulturen konnte sich ein Sklave freikaufen oder wurde von seinem Herrn freigelassen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Vorteil der Sklaverei liegt auf der Hand: Sklaven sind billige Arbeitskr&#228;fte, die entscheidend zum Wohlstand ihrer Herren beitrugen. Letztere waren dadurch in der Lage, gewaltige Tempel zu errichten oder stehende Heere zu unterhalten. Abgesehen vom moralischen Aspekt hat die Sklaverei allerdings einen entscheidenden Nachteil: Sie f&#252;hrt fast immer zu inneren Spannungen und Aufst&#228;nden.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La schiavit&#249; &#232; un sistema nel quale certe persone vengono giudicate inferiori ad altre e vengono trattate come oggetti o propriet&#224;, con gli stessi diritti di una sedia o di un capo di bestiame: nessuno. La schiavit&#249; &#232; esistita sin dall'antichit&#224;, dalle epoche d'oro di Roma e Grecia fino ai giorni nostri. Gli schiavi potevano essere criminali oppure nemici catturati, persino gente semplicemente di razza diversa. In alcune civilt&#224;, una persona poteva comprarsi la libert&#224; oppure rimanere schiavo per un periodo di tempo predeterminato.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il vantaggio della schiavit&#249; &#232; che la gente &#232; forzata a compiere dei lavori che si rifiuterebbe di fare se non dietro un adeguato compenso. La manodopera economica sfocia nell'accumulo di grandi ricchezze e nella creazione di grandi edifici e templi destinati al mantenimento di grandi eserciti di professionisti. Al di l&#224; della ripugnanza morale, gli svantaggi di una schiavit&#249; sono molteplici: rovina schiavi e padroni, viene utilizzato malamente il potenziale di un individuo e, cosa inevitabile, spesso porta a rivolte e lotte intestine.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El esclavismo es un sistema en el que parte de la poblaci&#243;n, considerada inferior al resto y despojada de sus derechos, recibe un tratamiento equiparable al del ganado o las posesiones materiales. La esclavitud ha existido durante toda la historia: desde los tiempos m&#225;s primitivos hasta nuestros d&#237;as, pasando por la luminosa &#233;poca de Roma y Grecia.  A veces, los criminales convictos eran condenados a la esclavitud. Otras, los enemigos del estado capturados sufr&#237;an este destino. Y otras, lo sufr&#237;a la gente de una raza o un color concretos. En algunas civilizaciones, una persona pod&#237;a comprar su libertad, o la recib&#237;a tras un periodo de esclavitud estipulado.[PARAGRAPH:2]La ventaja del sistema esclavista es que a los esclavos se les pueden imponer trabajos que cualquier persona se negar&#237;a a hacer sin recibir una compensaci&#243;n adecuada. La mano de obra barata permite la concentraci&#243;n de capital y, consecuentemente, la creaci&#243;n de grandes edificios y templos, o el mantenimiento de grandes ej&#233;rcitos profesionales. Aparte de los m&#225;s evidentes aspectos morales, las desventajas del esclavismo son numerosas: corrompe al esclavo y al amo, derrocha terriblemente la inteligencia y creatividad de los esclavos y acaba desembocando casi inevitablemente en revueltas y conflictos civiles. </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_STANDING_ARMY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]As nations grow large and prosperous, it is natural for them to expand their permanent cadre of armed forces into a professional organization that exists through times of both war and peace. Soldiers in these standing armies are paid for service on much the same basis as civilian employees would be. The rise of a professional military is usually accompanied by the rise of a dedicated bureaucracy or staff, which makes management of manpower and the military-industrial complex more efficient. Easy access into a volunteer military from citizens of all classes also makes the military an organ of social cohesion.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The state property civic describes an economy in which the citizens have no private property: everything belongs to the State. The State owns the factories, the farms, the universities, the grocery stores and virtually everything else. A citizen may own his or her clothing, furniture, and vehicle, but everything else he has is given to him by the State, and may be taken away any time the State sees fit.[PARAGRAPH:2]In a utopian society there would be no need for private property. Each person would contribute his or her best to the State; in return the State would distribute its largess according to each citizen's needs. Unfortunately, state property is quite a bit less fair when applied in real life. The State determines what each person gets, but often those decisions are based upon the citizen's political orthodoxy, family connections, or ability to pay bribes. The citizens feel that they are not rewarded for the quality of their efforts, and thus they see no point in achieving excellence. Innovation is pointless if one doesn't personally benefit from the innovation.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le r&#233;gime de la nationalisation d&#233;crit une &#233;conomie dans laquelle la propri&#233;t&#233; priv&#233;e n'existe pas : tout appartient &#224; l'Etat. L'Etat poss&#232;de les usines, les fermes, les universit&#233;s, les &#233;piceries, etc. Un citoyen peut poss&#233;der ses v&#234;tements, ses meubles et son v&#233;hicule, et tout le reste lui est fourni par l'Etat, et peut lui &#234;tre repris n'importe quand si le gouvernement le juge utile.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dans une soci&#233;t&#233; utopique, la propri&#233;t&#233; priv&#233;e serait inutile. Chaque individu contribuerait de son mieux &#224; la vie de la soci&#233;t&#233;. En retour, l'Etat dispenserait les biens en fonction des besoins de chacun. Malheureusement, la nationalisation appliqu&#233;e &#224; la vraie vie est beaucoup moins &#233;quitable. L'Etat d&#233;termine ce que chaque individu poss&#232;de, mais il le fait bien souvent en fonction de crit&#232;res politiques, et est sujet au client&#233;lisme et &#224; la corruption. Les citoyens ne se sentent pas r&#233;compens&#233;s pour leur travail et leurs qualit&#233;s, et ne cherchent donc pas &#224; atteindre l'excellence. Innover ne sert &#224; rien si on ne peut pas en tirer le moindre b&#233;n&#233;fice.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Staatseigentum" beschreibt ein System, in dem die B&#252;rger eines Landes keinerlei Privatbesitz haben. Fabriken, Bauernh&#246;fe, Universit&#228;ten und nahezu alle Einrichtungen des t&#228;glichen Lebens sind Eigentum des Staates. Jeder B&#252;rger besitzt seine Kleidung, M&#246;bel und ein Fahrzeug. Alles andere wird ihm von staatlicher Seite zugeteilt bzw. entzogen.[PARAGRAPH:2]In einer utopischen Gesellschaft ist kein Privatbesitz n&#246;tig, da sich alle B&#252;rger f&#252;r den Staat einsetzen und von diesem (sozusagen als Gegenleistung) versorgt und abgesichert werden. Leider sieht es in der Realit&#228;t etwas anders aus. Da allein der Staat die Verteilung der G&#252;ter kontrolliert, wird dieser Verteilungsprozess nicht selten durch politische Beziehungen und Bestechungsgelder unterlaufen. F&#252;hlen sich die B&#252;rger des Landes nicht angemessen entlohnt, sehen sie keinen Grund f&#252;r ein &#252;berm&#228;&#223;iges Engagement ihrerseits. Dar&#252;ber hinaus halten sie Innovationen f&#252;r &#252;berfl&#252;ssig, da sie von diesen nicht profitieren.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La propriet&#224; statale rappresenta un'economia nella quale i cittadini non posseggono propriet&#224; e tutto appartiene allo stato. Lo stato possiede le fabbriche, le fattorie, le universit&#224;, i negozi di alimentari e quant'altro. Un cittadino pu&#242; possedere solamente i suoi abiti, mobili, veicolo, mentre qualsiasi altra cosa viene fornita dallo stato, che pu&#242; riprendersela qualora ne vedesse la necessit&#224;.[PARAGRAPH:2]In una societ&#224; utopistica non dovrebbe esserci bisogno della propriet&#224; privata: ogni persona contribuisce a dare del proprio meglio allo stato, il quale ricambia soddisfando i bisogni del cittadino. Sfortunatamente, la propriet&#224; statale &#232; meno equa quando viene applicata alla vita reale: gli stati determinano ci&#242; che spetta a ogni persona, ma spesso queste decisioni sono condizionate da simpatie politiche, legami familiari o addirittura "bustarelle". Il cittadino capisce di non essere ripagato per i suoi sforzi e non si applica per raggiungere l'eccellenza. L'innovazione &#232; inutile se gli individui non ne possono trarre vantaggi.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La propiedad estatal es caracter&#237;stica de un sistema econ&#243;mico en el que los ciudadanos no tienen acceso a la propiedad privada. Todo pertenece al estado. Posee las f&#225;bricas, las granjas, las universidades, las fruter&#237;as y virtualmente todo lo dem&#225;s. Los ciudadanos pueden poseer su ropa, sus muebles y su veh&#237;culo, pero todo lo dem&#225;s les es entregado por el estado, y puede serles retirado cuando &#233;ste lo considere conveniente.[PARAGRAPH:2]En una sociedad ut&#243;pica, la propiedad privada no ser&#237;a necesaria. Todo el mundo contribuir&#237;a en la medida de su capacidad al estado, quien a cambio distribuir&#237;a la riqueza en funci&#243;n de las necesidades de cada uno. Por desgracia, el sistema de propiedad estatal resulta poco justo cuando se aplica a la vida real. El estado determina lo que recibe cada uno, pero a menudo sus decisiones se basan en el grado de ortodoxia pol&#237;tica, las conexiones familiares o la capacidad para pagar sobornos de los ciudadanos. &#201;stos tienen la impresi&#243;n de que sus esfuerzos no reciben contraprestaciones igualitarias, de modo que no se sienten vinculados al sistema. La innovaci&#243;n carece de aliciente si uno no puede beneficiarse personalmente de ella.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SUBJUGATION_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]The term "subjugation" is used to describe the policy of a nation's dominance over other lands. This doctrine has been frequently employed for economic exploitation in which an imperialist power makes use of other countries as sources of raw materials and cheap labor, shaping their economies to suit its own interests and keeping their people in poverty.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sometimes subjugation even refers to the acceptance, by the colonised, of the culture or doctrines of the coloniser as intrinsically more worthy or superior.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le terme d'Assujettissement fait r&#233;f&#233;rence &#224; la politique de dominance d'une nation. Cette doctrine a souvent &#233;t&#233; employ&#233;e pour l'exploitation &#233;conomique d'un pays par un autre : un pouvoir imp&#233;rialiste utilise d'autres pays en tant que sources de mati&#232;res premi&#232;res et de main-d'oeuvre bon march&#233;, ajuste leur &#233;conomie selon ses propres int&#233;r&#234;ts et maintient les gens dans la pauvret&#233;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Parfois, l'Assujettissement fait r&#233;f&#233;rence &#224; l'acceptation par les peuples colonis&#233;s de la culture ou des doctrines des colonisateurs, consid&#233;r&#233;es comme meilleures ou sup&#233;rieures.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff "Unterwerfung" beschreibt die politischen Bestrebungen einer Nation, andere L&#228;nder beherrschen zu wollen. Diese Doktrin wurde h&#228;ufig zur Realisierung wirtschaftlicher Ausbeutung eingesetzt, wobei die Kolonialmacht andere L&#228;nder als Quellen f&#252;r seltene Rohstoffe und billige Arbeitskr&#228;fte missbrauchte, deren Wirtschaft sie dann so gestaltete, dass sie zu den eigenen Interessen passte und schlussendlich die Einheimischen in ihrer Armut belie&#223;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Manchmal wird mit "Unterwerfung" allerdings auch der Umstand bezeichnet, dass die Kolonisierten die Kultur oder Lehren der Kolonialmacht als "wertvoller" oder "besser" akzeptieren und w&#252;rdigen.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il termine &amp;quot;sottomissione&amp;quot; viene usato per descrivere il dominio di una nazione su altre terre. Questa dottrina &#232; stata spesso usata per lo sfruttamento economico: una potenza imperialista sfrutta altri paesi come fonti di materie prime e lavoro a basso costo, modellando le loro economie a favore dei propri interessei e mantenendone le popolazioni in povert&#224;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Alle volte la sottomissione fa addirittura riferimento all'accettazione, da parte dei colonizzati, di una presunta e intrinseca superiorit&#224; della cultura dei colonizzatori.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El t&#233;rmino &amp;quot;subyugaci&#243;n&amp;quot; se utiliza para describir la pol&#237;tica de dominio de una naci&#243;n sobre otros territorios. Esta doctrina se ha empleado frecuentemente para describir la explotaci&#243;n econ&#243;mica que realiza una potencia imperialista cuando utiliza a otros pa&#237;ses como fuentes de materias primas y mano de obra barata, modelando sus econom&#237;as seg&#250;n sus propios intereses y manteniendo a sus gentes en la pobreza.[PARAGRAPH:2]A veces la subyugaci&#243;n tambi&#233;n alude a la aceptaci&#243;n por parte de la colonia de la cultura o las doctrinas de la potencia colonial como intr&#237;nsecamente superiores.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_SUBSISTENCE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A subsistence economy is a non-monetary economy which relies on natural resources to provide for basic needs, through hunting, gathering, and subsistence agriculture. "Subsistence" means supporting oneself at a minimum level; in a subsistence economy, economic surplus is minimal and only used to trade for basic goods, and there is no industrialization.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_THEOCRACY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A theocracy is a form of government where priests or holy men are in charge of the government. The government is run to benefit the people, but, more importantly, in accord with the wishes of the almighty, as interpreted by the holy men and priests. According to the theory, it is the will of God that such men be in charge of running things, and political dissent is sinful and wrong-headed, if not outright heresy.[PARAGRAPH:2]In the modern world, theocracies tend to be backward-looking, seeking to return their country to some usually mythical past state of grace and away from the evil and corrupt modern world. Diplomacy tends to be extremely difficult for such countries, since countries who act against their interests are doing so at the urging of the devil, rather than because the other countries have their own points of view and objectives. How can a holy leader compromise with an imp of Satan?</English>
  <French>[TAB]Une th&#233;ocratie est une forme de gouvernement dirig&#233;e par les pr&#234;tres et les hommes d'&#233;glise. Le gouvernement a pour but le bien-&#234;tre de la population, mais, et c'est le plus important, en accord avec la volont&#233; du tout-puissant, telle qu'elle est interpr&#233;t&#233;e par les religieux. En th&#233;orie, c'est Dieu qui a voulu que les religieux gouvernent la destin&#233;e des hommes. La dissidence politique est donc un p&#233;ch&#233;, une aberration, voire une h&#233;r&#233;sie.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dans le monde moderne, les th&#233;ocraties tendent &#224; &#234;tre r&#233;trogrades et &#224; restaurer une sorte de pass&#233; mythique, un &#233;tat de gr&#226;ce, &#224; l'&#233;cart du monde moderne corrompu. La diplomatie est rendue extr&#234;mement difficile pour ces nations : un pays qui agit contre l'int&#233;r&#234;t d'une th&#233;ocratie agit de la sorte car il y est incit&#233; par le diable, et non parce qu'il d&#233;fend ses propres int&#233;r&#234;ts ou points de vue. Comment un homme d'&#233;glise pourrait-il accepter un compromis avec un envoy&#233; de Satan ?</French>
  <German>[TAB]Die Theokratie ist eine Regierungsform, bei der Priester und heilige M&#228;nner die Regierungsgesch&#228;fte leiten. Die Regierung wird so gef&#252;hrt, dass das Volk davon profitiert, aber in erster Linie bestimmen die W&#252;nsche des Allm&#228;chtigen, die von den heiligen M&#228;nnern und Priestern ausgelegt werden, die Regierungspolitik. Laut dieser Theorie ist es Gottes Wille, dass diese M&#228;nner die Regierung leiten, und eine andere politische Meinung ist eine S&#252;nde und Starrk&#246;pfigkeit, wenn nicht sogar Ketzerei.[PARAGRAPH:2]In der modernen Welt sind Theokratien meist r&#252;ckw&#228;rts gerichtete Gesellschaften, die ihr Land zur&#252;ck in den &#252;blicherweise mystischen Zustand der Vergangenheit und fort von der b&#246;sen und korrupten modernen Welt bringen wollen. Die Diplomatie gestaltet sich f&#252;r diese L&#228;nder meist ausgesprochen schwierig, da die L&#228;nder, die gegen ihre Interessen handeln, dies ihrer Meinung nach tun, weil sie sich vom B&#246;sen leiten lassen und nicht, weil diese anderen L&#228;nder eigene Ansichten und Ziele haben. Wie kann ein heiliger Anf&#252;hrer auch einen Kompromiss mit einem Schergen des Satans eingehen?</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]La teocrazia &#232; una forma di governo dominata da sacerdoti e uomini santi. Il governo lavora in funzione del popolo, ma soprattutto in linea con i desideri dell'Onnipotente, i cui segni vengono interpretati dai sacerdoti. In teoria, questi uomini sono gli unici portavoce del volere di Dio, il dissenso politico &#232; un peccato e pu&#242; essere considerato addirittura eresia.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nel mondo moderno, le teocrazie tendono a guardare indietro, nel tentativo di riportare la propria nazione in qualche mitico stato di grazia appartenente al passato, lontano dal male e dalla corruzione. Per alcune nazioni, la diplomazia tende ad essere molto difficoltosa: se un paese agisce contro gli interessi di una teocrazia viene visto come un gesto del diavolo, piuttosto che una necessit&#224; e un differente punto di vista. Come pu&#242; un leader santo scendere a patti con un servo di Satana?</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La teocracia es la forma de gobierno en la que la autoridad secular est&#225; en manos de sacerdotes u hombres santos. &#201;stos gobiernan en beneficio de la comunidad, pero sobre todo de acuerdo a los deseos del todopoderoso, interpretados por el sacerdocio. En teor&#237;a, es voluntad de Dios que el gobierno est&#233; en sus manos, y el disenso pol&#237;tico es pecaminoso y moralmente condenable, cuando no directamente her&#233;tico.[PARAGRAPH:2]En nuestros tiempos, las teocracias son sistemas caracterizados por una noci&#243;n nost&#225;lgica de la historia, que aspiran a devolver la tierra a un pasado de gracia (normalmente m&#237;tico) y apartarla de la maldad y corrupci&#243;n del mundo moderno. Los pa&#237;ses que la practican tienen grandes dificultades diplom&#225;ticas, puesto que consideran que los estados que se les oponen act&#250;an impulsados por una voluntad diab&#243;lica en lugar de por sus propios puntos de vista e intereses. &#191;C&#243;mo va a llegar a un acuerdo un l&#237;der santo con un siervo de Sat&#225;n?</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_TOTALITARIANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Totalitarianism (or totalitarian rule) is a political system where the state recognizes no limits to its authority and strives to regulate every aspect of public and private life wherever feasible. Totalitarian regimes stay in political power through an all-encompassing propaganda campaign, which is disseminated through the state-controlled mass media, a single party that is often marked by political repression, personality cultism, control over the economy, regulation and restriction of speech, mass surveillance, and widespread use of terror. It is not synonymous with dictatorship, as authoritarian regimes also exhibit dictatorial features, but do not create an all-controlling, all-politicised society. Furthermore, non-dictatorial governments and societies are sometimes denounced as having totalitarian features, including democratic socialism, capitalism and liberal democracy.[PARAGRAPH:2]The concept of totalitarianism was first developed in a positive sense in the 1920s by the Italian fascists. The concept became prominent in Western anti-communist political discourse during the Cold War era in order to highlight perceived similarities between Nazi Germany and other fascist regimes on the one hand, and Soviet communism on the other.[PARAGRAPH:2]Aside from fascist and Stalinist movements that are totalitarian, there have been other movements that are totalitarian. The leader of the historic Spanish reactionary conservative movement called the Spanish Confederation of the Autonomous Right declared his intention to "give Spain a true unity, a new spirit, a totalitarian polity..." and went on to say "Democracy is not an end but a means to the conquest of the new state. When the time comes, either parliament submits or we will eliminate it." Baathist Iraq was distinctly ultra-nationalist and totalitarian, and has been dubbed by historian Stanley G. Payne as "the closest" reproduction of the Third Reich. Several revolutionary fundamentalist regimes have been pointed out as totalitarian, including post-revolutionary Iran.</English>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_TRIBALISM_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Tribalism is a form of organization which emphasizes the tribe as the sole unit of importance. Individuals have no rights; each man, woman and child exists only to support the tribe.  Tribalism is a fairly useful form of government for a small group of people who exist on the edge of catastrophe. In a tribe everyone knows everybody else; who is strong and who is weak, who is intelligent and who is not, who is skilled and who is unskilled.[PARAGRAPH:2]Leadership in the tribe is usually determined by merit, according to the tribe's needs: if the tribe is hungry, the best hunter becomes the leader. If the tribe is surrounded by enemies, the best warrior is chosen. And so forth. A tribe must quickly learn how to pick successful leaders; otherwise it will perish.[PARAGRAPH:2]Tribalism tends to break down when the tribe becomes overly large. People no longer know everyone in their tribe. Groups (or factions) appear, and everyone no longer share the same objectives. The tribe must find a more sophisticated system of government or fracture into smaller squabbling units.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Le tribalisme est une forme d'organisation qui place au-dessus de tout le bien-&#234;tre de la tribu. Les individus n'ont pas de droits, les hommes et les femmes n'existent que pour le bien de la tribu. Le tribalisme est une forme de gouvernement assez efficace pour de petits groupes de gens dont la survie est pr&#233;caire. Dans la tribu, tout le monde se conna&#238;t. On sait parfaitement qui est fort, intelligent ou habile.[PARAGRAPH:2]Les dirigeants sont g&#233;n&#233;ralement d&#233;sign&#233;s au m&#233;rite, selon les besoins de la tribu : si la tribu a faim, le chef sera le meilleur chasseur, si elle est attaqu&#233;e, le meilleur guerrier prend les commandes, et ainsi de suite. Une tribu doit savoir d&#233;signer les bons dirigeants, sinon elle dispara&#238;t.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le tribalisme ne survit pas &#224; l'accroissement de la population. Les gens de la m&#234;me tribu ne se connaissent plus, des groupes (ou factions) se forment, et la population ne partage plus les m&#234;mes aspirations. La tribu doit alors se trouver une autre forme de gouvernement, ou se fractionner en petits groupes.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Innerhalb eines Stammessystems ist allein der Stamm von Bedeutung. Der Einzelne genie&#223;t keinerlei Rechte. Jedes Stammesmitglied (ob Mann, Frau oder Kind) ist verpflichtet, den Stamm zu unterst&#252;tzen. F&#252;r eine sehr kleine Gruppe von Menschen kann das Stammessystem eine praktikable Regierungsform sein, da jeder die St&#228;rken und Schw&#228;chen des anderen kennt und dessen individuelle F&#228;higkeiten einzusch&#228;tzen wei&#223;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Das Stammesoberhaupt wird meist aufgrund seiner Verdienste bestimmt, die sich wiederum an den Bed&#252;rfnissen des Stammes orientieren. Hungert der Stamm, wird der beste J&#228;ger zum Stammesoberhaupt ernannt. Ist der Stamm von Feinden umgeben, w&#228;hlt man den besten Krieger als Stammesoberhaupt aus. Gelingt es einem Stamm nicht, ein Stammesoberhaupt zu bestimmen, ist er meist dem Untergang geweiht.[PARAGRAPH:2]Das Stammessystem bricht im Allgemeinen auseinander, wenn der Stamm zu gro&#223; wird und pl&#246;tzlich Einzelgruppen pers&#246;nliche Ziele verfolgen. Ist dies der Fall, muss der Stamm ein komplexeres Regierungssystem finden oder sich in verschiedene Gruppen aufspalten.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]L'organizzazione tribale &#232; una forma di ordinamento che enfatizza l'importanza totale della trib&#249;. Gli individui non hanno diritti: uomini, donne e bambini esistono unicamente per sostentare la trib&#249;. L'organizzazione tribale &#232; un tipo di governo adatto a piccoli gruppi di persone che vivono sull'orlo del baratro. In una trib&#249;, tutti si conoscono, chi &#232; forte e chi &#232; debole, chi &#232; intelligente e chi no, chi &#232; abile e chi &#232; inesperto.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il comando di una trib&#249; viene in genere determinato per merito, a seconda dei bisogni del gruppo: se la trib&#249; &#232; affamata, il miglior cacciatore diventa il capo, se la trib&#249; &#232; assediata dal nemico, viene scelto il miglior guerriero, e via discorrendo. Una trib&#249; deve imparare velocemente a saper riconoscere il leader pi&#249; adatto, altrimenti rischia di perire.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'organizzazione tribale tende a disgregarsi quando aumentano gli individui del gruppo e non tutti si conoscono pi&#249; tra loro; appaiono cos&#236; gruppi (o fazioni) e la gente non condivide pi&#249; gli stessi obiettivi. La trib&#249; deve a quel punto trovare un nuovo sistema di governo pi&#249; sofisticato oppure divedersi in piccoli gruppi in perenne disputa.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El tribalismo es una forma de sociedad en la que la tribu es el &#250;nico elemento importante. Los individuos carecen de derechos; los hombres, mujeres y ni&#241;os solo existen para apoyar a la tribu.  Se trata de una forma de gobierno muy &#250;til para un grupo peque&#241;o de gente que vive bajo la constante amenaza de la extinci&#243;n. En una tribu todos se conocen: se sabe qui&#233;n es fuerte y qui&#233;n es d&#233;bil, qui&#233;n es inteligente y qui&#233;n no lo es, qui&#233;n es h&#225;bil y qui&#233;n no.[PARAGRAPH:2]El liderazgo suele determinarse por un sistema de m&#233;ritos adaptado a las necesidades de la tribu; si el hambre es un problema, el mejor cazador se convierte en l&#237;der. Si la tribu est&#225; rodeada de enemigos, se elige al mejor guerrero. Y as&#237; sucesivamente. La tribu debe aprender a elegir buenos l&#237;deres; de lo contrario, est&#225; condenada a la desaparici&#243;n.[PARAGRAPH:2]El tribalismo suele dejar de funcionar cuando la tribu crece en exceso. Los miembros de la tribu ya no se conocen. Aparecen grupos (o facciones) y todos dejan de compartir los mismos objetivos. Entonces la tribu debe encontrar un sistema de gobierno m&#225;s sofisticado o fraccionarse en unidades m&#225;s peque&#241;as y hostiles entre s&#237;.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_TYRANNY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]In classical politics, a tyrant (Greek, tyrannos) is one who illegally seizes and controls a governmental power in a polis. Tyrants were a group of individuals who took over many Greek poleis during the uprising of the middle classes in the sixth and seventh centuries BC, ousting the aristocratic governments. Plato and Aristotle define a tyrant as, "one who rules without law, looks to his own advantage rather than that of his subjects, and uses extreme and cruel tactics -- against his own people as well as others". During the sixth and seventh centuries BC, tyranny was often looked upon as an intermediate stage between narrow oligarchy and more democratic forms of polity. However, in the late fifth and fourth centuries, a new kind of tyrant, the military dictator arose, specifically in Sicily. In ancient Greece, tyrants were influential opportunists that came to power by securing the support of different factions of a deme. The word "tyrannos", possibly pre-Greek, Pelasgian or eastern in origin, then carried no ethical censure; it simply referred to anyone, good or bad, who obtained executive power in a polis by unconventional means. Support for the tyrants came from the growing middle class and from the peasants who had no land or were in debt to the wealthy land owners. It is true that they had no legal right to rule, but the people preferred them over kings or the aristocracy. The Greek tyrants stayed in power by using mercenary soldiers from outside of their respective city-state. To mock tyranny, Thales wrote that the strangest thing to see is "an aged tyrant" meaning that tyrants do not have the public support to survive for long. In Corinth, growing wealth from colonial enterprises, and the wider horizons brought about by the export of wine and oil, together with the new experiences of the Eastern Mediterranean brought back by returning mercenary hoplites employed overseas allowed Cypselus, the first tyrant of Corinth in the 7th century BC, to overthrow the aristocratic power of the dominant but unpopular Bacchiadae, who were killed, executed, driven out and exiled in 657 BC. Corinth prospered economically under his rule and Cypselus manages to rule without a bodyguard but when he managed to bequeath his position to his son, Periander, whose position was less secure, his son required a bodyguard of mercenary soldiers personally loyal to himself. Nevertheless, under Cypselus and Periander, Corinth extended and tightened her control over her colonial enterprises, and exports of Corinthian pottery flourished. However, tyrants seldom succeeded in establishing an untroubled line of succession. Perianders successor was less fortunate and was expelled, Corinth was ruled by a lack-lustre oligarchy, and was exclipsed by the rising powers of Athens and Sparta. In Athens, the inhabitants first gave the title of tyrant to Peisistratus, a relative of Solon, the Athenian lawgiver, who succeeded in 546 BC, after 2 failed attempts, to install himself as tyrant. Supported by prosperity of the pesantry and landowning interests of the plain (prospering from the rise of olive exports), and his clients from Marathon, he managed to achieve supreme power. Through an ambitious program of public works, by fostering the state cult of Athena, by encouraging the creation of festivals and supporting the Panathenaean games, in which prizes were jars of olive oil, and in his support of the Dionosia (leading to the development of Athenian drama) Peisistratus managed to maintain his personal popularity. He was followed by his sons, and with the subsequent growth of Athenian democracy, the title "tyrant" took on its familiar negative connotations. The murder of his son, the tyrant Hipparchus by Aristogeiton and Harmodios in Athens in 514 BC marked the beginning of the so-called "cult of the tyrannicides" (i.e., of killers of tyrants). Contempt for tyranny characterised this cult movement. Despite financial help from Persia, in 510 the Peisistratids were expelled by a combination of intrigue, exile and Spartan arms. The anti-tyrannical attitude became especially prevalent in Athens after 508 BC, when Cleisthenes reformed the political system so that it resembled demokratia (ancient participant democracy as opposed to the modern representative democracy).</English>
  <German>[TAB]Der Begriff der Tyrannis umschreibt eine Herrschaftsform der griechischen Antike, die besonders im Zeitraum zwischen 600 v. Chr. und 200 v. Chr. vorkam. Es handelte sich um eine Art von Alleinherrschaft, wobei man in der Regel zwei Phasen unterscheidet: die &#196;ltere (oder Archaische) Tyrannis, die im 7. Jahrhundert v. Chr. aufkam und sp&#228;testens 461 v. Chr. endete, sowie die J&#252;ngere Tyrannis, die gegen Ende des 5. Jahrhunderts v. Chr. aufkam und vor allem au&#223;erhalb des griechischen Mutterlandes (vor allem auf Sizilien) verbreitet war. Im Gegensatz zur Basileia (K&#246;nigtum) bezeichnete der Begriff Tyrannis dabei in der Regel eine illegitime Form der Alleinherrschaft &#252;ber eine Polis, in der eine monarchische Staatsform eigentlich nicht vorgesehen und mit den nomoi (Gesetzen) schwer oder gar nicht vereinbar war.</German>
  <Spanish>[TAB]La tiran&#237;a (del griego tyrannos), en el sentido que se dio al t&#233;rmino en la Grecia antigua, era el r&#233;gimen de poder absoluto, de ordinario unipersonal, que con frecuencia instauraba el tirano, aquel o aquellos que hab&#237;an derrocado el gobierno de una ciudad-estado, normalmente gracias al apoyo popular, pero tambi&#233;n mediante un golpe de estado militar o una intervenci&#243;n extranjera.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Parece que el t&#233;rmino "tirano" se aplic&#243; por primera vez a Fid&#243;n de Argos y a C&#237;pselo de Corinto. El periodo de esplendor de los reg&#237;menes de tiran&#237;a fue el siglo VI a. C., cuando muchos gobiernos del Egeo fueron derribados y Persia tuvo ocasi&#243;n de hacer sus primeras incursiones en Grecia, al buscar diversos tiranos su apoyo para consolidarse en el poder. Pis&#237;strato y sus descendientes, los pisistr&#225;tidas (Hipias e Hiparco), son el ejemplo de estos gobernantes para Atenas; Pol&#237;crates para Samos, y muchos otros.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]La tiran&#237;a griega fue fruto de la lucha de las clases populares contra los abusos de la aristocracia y los reyes-sacerdotes, cuyo derecho a gobernar ven&#237;a sancionado por las tradiciones ancestrales y la mitolog&#237;a. Los tiranos llegaron con frecuencia al poder a trav&#233;s de revueltas populares y gozaron de la simpat&#237;a p&#250;blica como gobernantes, al menos en sus primeros a&#241;os en el poder. De Pis&#237;strato, por ejemplo, cuenta Arist&#243;teles que eximi&#243; de impuestos a un agricultor a causa de lo particularmente inf&#233;rtiles que eran sus tierras, y se dice que Cipselo pod&#237;a pasear por las calles de Corinto sin escolta de ninguna clase.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_UNIVERSAL_SUFFRAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Universal suffrage means extending the vote to everyone, regardless of race, creed, or gender. Note however that even the most universal suffrage is usually less than totally universal; in the United States, for example, one must be 18 years of age to vote, and being convicted of certain criminal offenses results in permanent loss of suffrage.[PARAGRAPH:2]The positive side of universal suffrage is that everyone is allowed an equal say in electing those who will run the country. The negative side is that this includes everyone, regardless of intelligence, honesty, or any other characteristic. As someone once said, "I reject any form of government in which the opinion of the village idiot is given the same weight as the opinion of Aristotle." </English>
  <French>[TAB]Le suffrage universel est le droit de vote pour tous, sans distinction de race, de sexe ou de religion. Notez n&#233;anmoins que le suffrage universel n'est jamais r&#233;ellement totalement universel. En France, il faut avoir 18 ans pour pouvoir voter et certains crimes valent &#224; leurs auteurs une annulation d&#233;finitive de leur droit de vote.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'aspect positif du suffrage universel est qu'il permet &#224; tout le monde d'avoir un poids &#233;gal dans l'&#233;lection des dirigeants. L'aspect n&#233;gatif est que cela inclut aussi les imb&#233;ciles et les personnes malhonn&#234;tes. Comme quelqu'un l'a dit : "Je rejette toute forme de gouvernement par laquelle l'opinion de l'idiot du village a le m&#234;me poids que celle d'Aristote." </French>
  <German>[TAB]Das allgemeine Wahlrecht gew&#228;hrt jedem vollj&#228;hrigen B&#252;rger eines Landes unabh&#228;ngig von dessen Glaube oder Geschlecht ein Stimmrecht. Wird man bestimmter Verbrechen f&#252;r schuldig gesprochen, droht der Verlust des Wahlrechts.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der Vorteil des allgemeinen Wahlrechts ist die Gleichwertigkeit der Stimmen aller Wahlberechtigten. Allerdings steht das Wahlrecht jedem Menschen unabh&#228;ngig von dessen Intelligenz oder moralischer Integrit&#228;t zu. Zitat eines Unbekannten: "Ich lehne jede Regierung ab, in der die Meinung des Dorftrottels dasselbe Gewicht hat wie die des Aristoteles."</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il suffragio universale ha dato il diritto di voto a tutti, indipendentemente dalla razza, dal sesso e dalla religione. Anche il suffragio universale ha delle limitazioni, malgrado tutto: negli Stati Uniti, per esempio, bisogna aver compiuto i 18 anni per conquistare il diritto di voto ed essere consapevole che alcune azioni criminali possono farlo perdere per sempre.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il punto di forza del suffragio universale &#232; che chiunque ha lo stesso diritto di poter eleggere i propri governatori; il punto debole, tuttavia, &#232; che proprio chiunque ha il diritto di votare, indipendentemente dall'intelligenza, dall'onest&#224; o da qualsiasi altra caratteristica. Come ha detto qualcuno, "rinnego una qualsiasi forma di governo nella quale l'opinione dello scemo del villaggio ha lo stesso peso di quella di Aristotele".</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]El sufragio universal es la extensi&#243;n del derecho al voto a toda la poblaci&#243;n, al margen de su raza, credo o sexo. No obstante, hasta el m&#225;s universal de los sufragios suele distar mucho de ser totalmente universal. En Estados Unidos, por ejemplo, uno debe tener m&#225;s de 18 a&#241;os para poder votar, y ciertos delitos acarrean la p&#233;rdida permanente del derecho.[PARAGRAPH:2]El lado positivo es que todos los ciudadanos contribuyen en la misma medida a la elecci&#243;n de los gobernantes. El negativo es que esto incluye a todos, independientemente de su inteligencia, honestidad o cualquier otra caracter&#237;stica. Como alguien dijo en una ocasi&#243;n: "rechazo cualquier forma de gobierno en la que la opini&#243;n del tonto del pueblo tiene el mismo peso que la de Arist&#243;teles". </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_VASSALAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Vassalage is a feudal term referring to a person who enters a contract with his or her lord, agreeing to serve and protect the lord in return for monetary rewards or ownership or sovereignty over a parcel of land. The contract is often of both political and religious significance binding both parties by the rules of man and of God.[PARAGRAPH:2]Vassalage is often tribal in nature. One tribe conquers another, and rather than killing the conquered tribe or taking over its direct management, the conquering ruler makes the conquered his vassal: the lower ruler continues to maintain control over his people and territory, while paying tribute to his or her lord in the form of money, goods, soldiers or slaves. </English>
  <French>[TAB]La vassalit&#233; est un terme f&#233;odal qui fait r&#233;f&#233;rence aux engagements pris entre des personnes et leur seigneur, l'un promettant de servir et de prot&#233;ger l'autre contre de l'argent, des biens ou m&#234;me la souverainet&#233; sur une parcelle de terres. Ce type de contrat a souvent &#224; la fois une signification politique et religieuse, les deux parties &#233;tant li&#233;es devant les hommes et devant Dieu.[PARAGRAPH:2]La vassalit&#233; est souvent tribale par nature. Une tribu en envahit une autre, mais plut&#244;t que de tuer tout le monde ou de s'emparer des r&#234;nes du pouvoir, le conqu&#233;rant fait du vaincu son vassal : ce dernier continue d'exercer le pouvoir sur son peuple, mais verse un tribut &#224; son seigneur sous la forme d'argent, de biens, de soldats ou d'esclaves. </French>
  <German>[TAB]Vasallen waren in der feudalen Gesellschaft Personen, die ihren Lehnsherren dienten oder diese besch&#252;tzten und f&#252;r ihre Dienste mit Geld, Grundbesitz oder Macht belohnt wurden. Der Vertrag zwischen Lehnsherr und Vasall hatte nicht selten eine politische oder religi&#246;se Bedeutung und war f&#252;r beide Parteien bindend.[PARAGRAPH:2]Das Vasallentum ist vor allem f&#252;r Stammeskulturen typisch. Erobert Stamm A beispielsweise Stamm B, wird Letzterer automatisch ein Vasall des Siegers. Der unterlegene Herrscher bleibt in diesem Fall im Amt und verpflichtet sich, seinen Bezwinger mit Geld, Waren, Soldaten oder Sklaven zu unterst&#252;tzen.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Il vassallaggio &#232; un termine feudale che si riferisce a una persona che stipula un contratto con il proprio signore, per proteggerlo e servirlo in cambio di ricompense monetarie, propriet&#224; o sovranit&#224; su una terra. Il contratto assume spesso un significato politico e religioso, legando entrambe le parti alle leggi umane e divine.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il vassallaggio assume spesso connotazioni di natura tribale. Una trib&#249; conquista un'altra e, invece di sterminarla o prendere il possesso della loro gestione, il vincitore della battaglia trasforma il perdente in un vassallo: il soggiogato continua a mantenere il controllo sulla propria gente e sul territorio, pagando per&#242; dei tributi sotto forma di soldi, beni, soldati o schiavi al proprio signore.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]Vasallaje es un t&#233;rmino feudal que hace referencia a la persona que establece una relaci&#243;n contractual con su se&#241;or en la que se compromete a servirlo y protegerlo a cambio de recompensas pecuniarias o de la propiedad (o usufructo) de una parcela. Normalmente, el contrato tiene connotaciones pol&#237;ticas y religiosas y somete a ambas partes a las leyes del hombre y de Dios.[PARAGRAPH:2]El vasallaje suele ser de naturaleza tribal. Una tribu conquista a otra y, en vez de exterminarla o hacerse cargo de la administraci&#243;n directa de su patrimonio, convierte a los conquistados en vasallos: el gobernante sometido mantiene el control sobre su pueblo y su territorio, pero paga un tributo a su se&#241;or en forma de dinero, mercanc&#237;as, soldados o esclavos. </Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_VICEROYALTY_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]A viceroy is a royal official who governs a country or province in the name of and as representative of a monarch. The term derives from the Latin prefix vice-, meaning "in the place of" and French roi, meaning king. His province or territory is called a viceroyalty.[PARAGRAPH:2]The title was originally used by the Aragonese Crown during the 14th Century to refer to Sardinia and Corsica. The absolutist Kings of Spain employed numerous Viceroys to rule over various parts of their vast empire "where the sun never sets", both European and overseas.</English>
  <French>[TAB]Un vice-roi est un repr&#233;sentant royal qui gouverne un pays ou une province en tant que repr&#233;sentant d'un monarque. Il s'agit de la personne qui agit "&#224; la place de" ("vice-") son roi. Sa province ou son territoire est appel&#233;e vice-royaut&#233;.[PARAGRAPH:2]Ce titre &#233;tait utilis&#233; &#224; l'origine par la Couronne d'Aragon, durant le 14e si&#232;cle, pour d&#233;signer la Sardaigne et la Corse. Les monarques espagnols nommaient de nombreux vice-rois, afin de r&#233;gner sur les diff&#233;rentes r&#233;gions de leur vaste empire, "o&#249; le soleil ne se couche jamais", en Europe et par-del&#224; les oc&#233;ans.</French>
  <German>[TAB]Ein Vizek&#246;nig ist ein k&#246;niglicher W&#252;rdentr&#228;ger, der ein Land oder eine Provinz im Namen bzw. als Repr&#228;sentant des K&#246;nigs regiert. Der Begriff ist von der lateinischen Vorsilbe "Vize" (an Stelle von) abgeleitet. Seine Provinz bzw. seine L&#228;ndereien werden Vizek&#246;nigreich genannt.[PARAGRAPH:2]Urspr&#252;nglich wurde dieser Titel seit dem 14. Jahrhundert vom Aragonischen K&#246;nigshaus f&#252;r Sardinien und Korsika verwendet. Die absolutistischen K&#246;nige Spaniens setzten unz&#228;hlige Vizek&#246;nige ein, um die Kontrolle &#252;ber weite Teile ihres riesigen Reiches, "in dem die Sonne niemals untergeht", sowohl in Europa als auch in &#220;bersee zu sichern.</German>
  <Italian>[TAB]Un vicer&#233; &#232; un funzionario reale che governa un Paese o una provincia nel nome e come rappresentante di un monarca. Il termine deriva dal prefisso latino vice-, che significa &amp;quot;al posto di&amp;quot; e dal francese roi, che significa re. La provincia o il territorio controllato si chiama vicereame.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il titolo venne originariamente usato dalla corona di Aragona, durante il 14&#176; secolo, in riferimento a Sardegna e Corsica. I monarchi assoluti di Spagna usarono numerosi vicer&#233; per governare diverse parti del loro vasto impero, &amp;quot;su cui non tramonta mai il sole&amp;quot;, sia in Europa che oltremare.</Italian>
  <Spanish>[TAB]Un virrey es un delegado real que gobierna un pa&#237;s o una provincia en nombre de un monarca. El t&#233;rmino deriva del lat&#237;n &amp;quot;vice regis&amp;quot;, que quiere decir &amp;quot;en nombre del rey&amp;quot;. Su provincia o territorio se denomina &amp;quot;virreinato&amp;quot;.[PARAGRAPH:2]El t&#237;tulo lo utiliz&#243; originalmente la corona de Arag&#243;n durante el siglo XIV para aludir a C&#243;rcega y Cerde&#241;a. Los reyes absolutistas espa&#241;oles emplearon numerosos virreyes para gestionar su vasto imperio, tanto europeo como de ultramar, &amp;quot;en el que nunca se pon&#237;a el sol&amp;quot;.</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 <TEXT>
  <Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_WARRIOR_CODE_PEDIA</Tag>
  <English>[TAB]Many societies have a distinct class that supplies the nation's fighting manpower during war. Such a class usually sets itself apart from the common run of the people, adopting distinct cultural behaviors and attitudes to meet the special needs of men who must be ready and able to fight at any time. Since powerful military figures tend to dominate their societies, this class often has the wealth and power to make its cultural preferences known throughout the land, finding expression in art and poetry that promotes the ideals of the heroic warrior and provides examples of such to the next generation. Even where an elite martial class is not present or not dominant over the mercantile and agricultural classes, military traditions can spill over into common society and come to dominate it - witness the rise of militarism in 19th century Prussia for an example.[PARAGRAPH:2]In general, this kind of war-culture promotes military fitness among the citizens and makes for a keen, well-led army. On the other hand, it often leads to the neglect of social or economic problems in favor of fixation on martial virtues. It can also lead to arrogant overconfidence when faced with a foe who doesn't share one's own warrior values.</English>
 </TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
