<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- Diplomacy -->
<Civ4GameText>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Please support [OUR_CIV_SHORT] and it's people. We depend on your help!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>This will be of mutual benefit for us both, don't you think so?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RAGNAR_LODBROK_1</Tag>
		<English>Hail and well met, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME], ruler of the glorious [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. So tell me: does [CT_CIV_SHORT] have a lot of rich and unprotected coastal cities, or what?</English>
		<French>Bonjour, [CT_NAME], c'est un vrai plaisir ! Je suis [OUR_NAME], chef des glorieux [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Dites-moi : est-ce que [CT_CIV_SHORT] dispose de nombreuses villes c&#244;ti&#232;res riches et faiblement prot&#233;g&#233;es ?</French>
		<German>Tag auch, [CT_NAME]! Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Staatsoberhaupt des ruhmreichen Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Nun, dann erz&#228;hlt mal: Besitzt Ihr vielleicht ein paar reiche, schutzlose K&#252;stenst&#228;dte?</German>
		<Italian>Salute a te, [CT_NAME]! Io sono [OUR_NAME], glorioso sovrano [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. Parliamo, dunque: [CT_CIV_SHORT] ha molte citt&#224; costiere ricche e poco protette, vero?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos y bienaventuranzas, [CT_NAME]. Soy [OUR_NAME], dirigente de la gloriosa tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Decidme, &#191;tiene o no [CT_CIV_SHORT] muchas ciudades costeras pr&#243;speras e indefensas?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RAMESSES_II_1</Tag>
		<English>Mighty [OUR_NAME], all-powerful god-king of [OUR_CIV_SHORT] welcomes you, [CT_NAME]! Feel free to grovel in terror and awe if the mood takes you.</English>
		<French>[OUR_NAME], tout puissant roi et divinit&#233; des [OUR_CIV_SHORT], vous souhaite la bienvenue, [CT_NAME] ! N'h&#233;sitez pas &#224; vous prosterner devant moi ou &#224; vous &#233;taler &#224; mes pieds si le coeur vous en dit !</French>
		<German>Ich, [OUR_NAME], allmächtiges Staatsoberhaupt des Volkes von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], heiße Euch willkommen, [CT_NAME]! Es steht Euch frei, ehrfürchtig vor mir niederzuknien, wenn Euch danach ist.</German>
		<Italian>Il potente [OUR_NAME], onnipotente e divino leader [OUR_CIV_ADJ] ti d&#224; il benvenuto, [CT_NAME]! Prostrati pure in preda al terrore e alla meraviglia, se ne hai voglia.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El gran [OUR_NAME], rey dios todopoderoso de [OUR_CIV_SHORT] os da la bienvenida, [CT_NAME]. Pod&#233;is postraros ante mí presa de un temor reverencial si se os antoja.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>Our armies are evenly matched, but I believe in a battle I would win out. So that this does not occur I ask you to meet our demands.</English>
		<French>Partager, c'est le d?but de l'amiti?, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Helfen hei?t br?derlich teilen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Se ci tieni a me, condividi, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Compartir es de generosos, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_CIV_SHORT] needs this and demands your assistance!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>Brazil is strong in many ways, [CT_NAME]. Do not force me to show you how strong.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>You are outgunned and outclassed. I suggest you give me what I demand.</English>
		<French>R?pondez ? nos exigences ou vous subirez la foudre de notre "terrible et rapide ?p?e".</French>
		<German>Schlagt ein, wenn Ihr kein zweites Gettysburg erleben wollt! </German>
		<Italian>Dammi ci? che chiedo o proverai l'ira della nostra &amp;quot;terribile e rapida spada.&amp;quot; </Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos esto o sentir?is la c?lera de nuestra &amp;quot;terrible y veloz espada&amp;quot;. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Can you spare this for the people of the [OUR_EMPIRE]?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>My people have faith in me, [CT_NAME]. Please help me not to disappoint them.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>The simplest strategy is for me to ask you for what we need and hope your good will wins out.</English>
		<French>Pourriez-vous donner ceci ? un bon ami, [CT_NAME] ?</French>
		<German>Ihr werdet einem treuen Freund diese kleine Bitte doch nicht abschlagen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Avresti un po' di questi in nome della nostra amicizia, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>&#191;Podr?ais darles esto a unos buenos amigos, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_GENERIC</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME], leader of the great civilization of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</English>
		<German>Seid gegr&#252;&#223;t, [CT_NAME]! Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Anf&#252;hrer der gro&#223;en Zivilisation von [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HARUN_1</Tag>
		<English>Peace be upon you, [CT_NAME] of [CT_CIV_SHORT]. If you would expect the blessings of Allah, be kind to his people, for Allah will help him who moves the ways of Allah.</English>
		<German>Friede sei mit Euch, [CT_NAME] von [CT_CIV_SHORT]. Falls Ihr die Segnungen Allahs erwartet, seid freundlich zu seinem Volk, denn Allah wird dem helfen, der die Wege Allahs bewegt.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ATATURK_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME], the President of the Turkish people. We Turks do not consider our principles as dogmas contained in books that are said to come from heaven. We derive our inspiration not from heaven, or from an unseen world, but directly from life.</English>
		<German>Seid gegr&#252;&#223;t, [CT_NAME]! Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Anf&#252;hrer der gro&#223;en Zivilisation von [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CARDENAS_1</Tag>
		<English>Hola. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I am convinced that the good intentions of a ruler are simply not enough and that the collective factor represented by the workers is indispensable. Don't you agree [CT_NAME]?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHARLES_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome [CT_NAME]. We would welcome friendship with you. Are you greedy of territory, or greedy of piece and quiet?</English>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Wir w&#252;rden Freundschaft mit Euch willkommen hei&#223;en. Giert Ihr nach Eroberungen, oder nach Frieden und Ruhe?</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HAILE_SELASSIE_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings in the name of God, [CT_NAME] of [CT_CIV_SHORT]. We are Emperor [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. We know that material and spiritual progress are essential to man. Will you join us as we ceaselessly work for the equal attainment of both?</English>
		<German>Gr&#252;&#223;e im Namen Gottes, [CT_NAME] von [CT_CIV_SHORT]. Wir sind Kaiser [OUR_NAME] von [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Wir wissen, dass k&#246;rperlicher und spiritueller Fortschritt essentiell f&#252;r den Menschen sind. Werdet Ihr daran teilhaben, wie wir ununterbrochen f&#252;r das gleichzeitige Erlangen von beidem arbeiten?</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. My name is [OUR_NAME], and I am the president of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. My motto is: when there is respect, there is peace!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KHOMEINI_1</Tag>
		<English>I, [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV], greet you. Know that those who speak of nationalism, democracy, and such things want to take our nation away from its mission.</English>
		<German>Ich, [OUR_NAME] von [OUR_CIV_SHORT], gr&#252;&#223;e Euch. Wisset, dass jene, welche von Nationalismus, Demokratie und solchen Dingen sprechen, Eure Nation von ihrer Mission abbringen wollen.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NICHOLAS_II_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME], Emperor of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Dedicating all my efforts to the well-being of my people, I shall guard the concept of Autocracy like all my forefathers did.</English>
		<German>Gr&#252;&#223;e. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Kaiser von [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. W&#228;hrend ich all meine Anstrengungen dem Wohlergehen meines Volkes widme, werde ich das Konzept der Autokratie besch&#252;tzen wie alle meine Vorv&#228;ter.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>Welcome to humble [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. I am [OUR_NAME], leader of this far-reaching and ever progressing country. Tell me, who are you?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>Hello, friend. My name is [OUR_NAME], but you can call me Jose. Or you can call me Francisco. Or you can call me Martin. Just don't call me late for dinner. </English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SANTA_ANNA_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello, [CT_NAME]. I am General Santa Anna, Savior of Mexico! What have you come to offer me in tribute?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], emperor of all the lands below the heavens. With absolute power over numberless minions, do you dare hurt the divine ruler of mighty [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_IVAN_IV_1</Tag>
		<English>[OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT] greets you. I do not praise myself or my courage, but I praise God, for he protected me, a sinful man, from deadly dangers and created me capable of doing many human things.</English>
		<German>[OUR_NAME] von [OUR_CIV_SHORT] gr&#252;&#223;t Euch. Ich lobe weder mich selbst noch meinen Mut, aber ich lobe Gott, denn er besch&#252;tzte mich, einen s&#252;ndigen Mann, vor t&#246;dlichen Gefahren und erm&#246;glichte mir, viele menschliche Dinge zu tun.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_ATATURK_1</Tag>
		<English>We must get ready to build up the friendship between our peoples. How does a people get prepared for such an endeavour? By strengthening the natural bridges that exist between us. Language is a bridge... Religon is a bridge... History is a bridge...</English>
		<German>Wir m&#252;ssen uns bereit machen, die Freundschaft zwischen unseren V&#246;lkern aufzubauen. Wie wird ein Volk auf solch ein Vorhaben vorbereitet? Indem wir die nat&#252;rlichen Br&#252;cken st&#228;rken, die zwischen uns existieren. Sprache ist eine Br&#252;cke ... Religion ist eine Br&#252;cke ... Geschichte ist eine Br&#252;cke ...</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_HAILE_SELASSIE_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, [CT_NAME]. Imagination, devotion, perseverance, together with divine grace, will assure your success. What shall we discuss?</English>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]. Vorstellungskraft, Hingabe, Durchhalteverm&#246;gen, zusammen mit Gottes Gnade, wird Euren Erfolg sichern. Was sollen wir besprechen?</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! It is so great to be at peace with you glorious nation!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>I see you have come to visit, [CT_NAME]. Tell me, what is it you wish to discuss.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>Finally I get to talk to a worthy adversary. What can the [OUR_EMPIRE] do for you?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Asseyez-vous et bavardons un instant.</French>
		<German>Seid gegr??t, [CT_NAME]. Nehmt Platz und lasst uns ein wenig plaudern.</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]. Siediti e parliamo per un po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sentaos y charlemos un rato.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_HAILE_SELASSIE_1</Tag>
		<English>The world is well supplied with people who wish to rule and dominate others. People like you.</English>
		<German>Die Welt ist gut versorgt mit Menschen, die andere beherrschen und dominieren wollen. Menschen wie Euch.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Oh, you again... What are you going to complain about?</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_KHOMEINI_1</Tag>
		<English>If one permits an infidel to continue in his role as a corrupter of the earth, the infidel's moral suffering will be all the worse. If one kills the infidel, and this stops him from perpetrating his misdeeds, his death will be a blessing to him.</English>
		<German>Wenn man einem Ungl&#228;ubigen erlaubt, seine Rolle als Verderber der Erde fortzusetzen, wird das moralische Leiden des Ungl&#228;ubigen umso gr&#246;&#223;er sein. Wenn man den Ungl&#228;ubigen t&#246;tet, und ihn vom Fortsetzen seiner Untaten abh&#228;lt, wird ihm sein Tod ein Segen sein.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_NICHOLAS_II_1</Tag>
		<English>Treachery, cowardice and lies are everywhere - and your nation is no exception.</English>
		<German>Verrat, Feigheit und L&#252;gen sind &#252;berall - und Eure Nation ist keine Ausnahme.</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>Speak fast [CT_CIV_ADJ]. I have enough on my schedule already.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>You lack the guile to trick me. Be warned I will not react well to deceit. </English>
		<French>Que me vaut l'honneur peu enviable de votre pr?sence ?</French>
		<German>Was verschafft mir die zweifelhafte Ehre Eures Besuchs?</German>
		<Italian>E a cosa devo il dubbio onore della tua presenza?</Italian>
		<Spanish>&#191;Y a qu? debemos el dudoso honor de vuestra compa??a?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>The government of the [OUR_EMPIRE] will fulfill its duty to defend its independence, to repel foreign aggression, and accept the struggle to which it has been provoked!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>No way! I shall punish you for your crimes against [OUR_CIV_SHORT] and its people!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>I knew you would beg for peace eventually, but there will be no peace until you surrender.</English>
		<French>Comme un ami m'a dit un jour, "Aucune condition ne saurait ?tre accept?e, hormis une capitulation imm?diate et inconditionnelle." Dommage, n'est-ce pas ?</French>
		<German>Wie ein Freund von mir zu sagen pflegte: 'Ich akzeptiere nur die sofortige und bedingungslose Kapitulation'. ?u?erst treffend, nicht wahr?</German>
		<Italian>Come disse una volta un mio amico: &amp;quot;L'unica cosa accettabile ? una resa incondizionata e immediata.&amp;quot; Conciso, non trovi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Como un amigo m?o dijo una vez: &amp;quot;Ninguna condici?n es aceptable, salvo una rendici?n incondicional e inmediata&amp;quot;. Es una l?stima, &#191;no cre?is?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_JUAREZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Get out of my office!</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_PEDRO_II</Tag>
		<English>You make me sad, [CT_NAME]. Go away.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN</Tag>
		<English>I will now use my cunning knowledge of tactics to ignore you. </English>
		<French>Allez vous faire voir !</French>
		<German>Fahrt zur H?lle!</German>
		<Italian>Sparisci.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Pod?is iros al cuerno.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Your words are but the grunts of a diseased pig, [CT_NAME]. I do not hear them.</English>
		<French>Vos paroles sonnent &#224; mes oreilles tels d'horribles grognements d'un porc agonisant, [CT_NAME]. Je ne les &#233;couterai pas plus longtemps.</French>
		<German>Ihr sprecht mit gespaltener Zunge, [CT_NAME], und ich will es nicht hören!</German>
		<Italian>Le tue parole risuonano come i grugniti di un maiale morente, [CT_NAME]. Un rumore fastidioso che non voglio udire.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vuestras palabras no son más que gruñidos de un cerdo enfermo, [CT_NAME]. Como tales, no las escucho.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Give me this, [CT_NAME] and perhaps our two nations can live in peace for a while longer.</English>
		<French>Donnez-moi ce que je demande, [CT_NAME], et peut-&#234;tre nos deux nations pourront-elles cohabiter en paix quelques temps encore.</French>
		<German>Gebt uns, was wir verlangen, [CT_NAME], dann besteht die Chance, dass unsere Zivilisationen noch eine Weile in Frieden miteinander leben!</German>
		<Italian>Dammi questo, [CT_NAME], e forse le nostre due nazioni vivranno in pace per un altro po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadme esto, [CT_NAME], y es posible que nuestras naciones puedan vivir en paz un poco más.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Hand this over, [CT_NAME], and I might let you continue to exist for a short while longer.</English>
		<French>Donnez-nous ce tribut, [CT_NAME], et il est possible que je vous laisse vivre... quelques temps, en tout cas.</French>
		<German>Her damit, [CT_NAME]! Dann werde ich Euch vielleicht noch eine Weile verschonen!</German>
		<Italian>Dammelo, [CT_NAME], e potrei lasciarti continuare a esistere ancora un po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Entregadnos esto, [CT_NAME] y puede que os deje perdurar un poco más.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Unlikely as it may seem, it appears that your puny civilization has something that we want. I suggest you hand it over quickly. </English>
		<French>Aussi ahurissant que cela puisse para&#238;tre, il semblerait que votre ridicule petite civilisation dispose de quelque chose qui pourrait nous &#234;tre utile. Je vous sugg&#232;re de nous le d&#233;livrer au plus vite.</French>
		<German>So unglaublich es auch klingen mag: Eure mickrige Zivilisation scheint tatsächlich etwas zu haben, was wir wollen. Ihr wärt gut beraten, es uns schnellstens zu überlassen! </German>
		<Italian>Per quanto possa apparire improbabile, a quanto pare la tua insignificante civiltà possiede qualcosa che vogliamo. Ti consiglio di darcelo subito. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Por extraño que suene, parece que vuestra civilización tiene algo que queremos. Os sugiero que nos lo deis rápidamente. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, [CT_NAME]. And how is that undefended civilization of your coming along?</English>
		<French>Bienvenue, [CT_NAME]. Alors, comment &#233;volue donc la situation dans votre petite civilisation si vuln&#233;rable ?</French>
		<German>Willkommen, [CT_NAME]! Und, wie stehen die Dinge in Eurer hilflosen kleinen Zivilisation?</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]. Come vanno le cose per la tua civiltà indifesa?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. ¿Cómo está esa civilización indefensa de la que venís?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Not a chance. The mighty [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people do not care to make peace with cattle-stealing brigands like you.</English>
		<French>N'y comptez pas ! Le puissant peuple des [OUR_CIV_ADJ] ne souhaite pas faire la paix avec des vils voleurs de b&#233;tail de votre esp&#232;ce.</French>
		<German>Keine Chance! Das mächtige [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] Volk hat kein Interesse daran, mit miesen Viehdieben wie Euch Frieden zu schließen! </German>
		<Italian>Neanche per idea. Al potente sovrano [OUR_CIV_ADJ] non può interessare la pace con briganti ladri di bestiame come voi. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Ni en broma. El poderoso pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1] no se molesta ni en hacer las paces con cuatreros bergantes como vosotros. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! The [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people always enjoy meeting vulnerable and undefended new civilizations!</English>
		<French>Mes hommages, [CT_NAME] ! Le peuple des [OUR_CIV_ADJ] est toujours enchant&#233; de rencontrer de nouvelles civilisations vuln&#233;rables et sans d&#233;fense !</French>
		<German>Seid gegrüßt, [CT_NAME]! Das [OUR_CIV_ADJ:3] Volk ist stets hoch erfreut, die Bekanntschaft schutz- und wehrloser neuer Zivilisationen zu machen!</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]! Il sovrano [OUR_CIV_ADJ] è sempre lieto di incontrare nuove civiltà vulnerabili e indifese!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Saludos, [CT_NAME]! El pueblo [OUR_CIV_ADJ:1] siempre se congratula de encontrarse con civilizaciones vulnerables e indefensas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_NATIVE_1</Tag>
		<English>So you have emerged from your fetid country and come to me, [CT_NAME]. To what do I owe this extremely dubious honor?</English>
		<French>Vous avez enfin r&#233;ussi &#224; sortir de cet horrible pays pour venir me voir, [CT_NAME]. Que me vaut un pareil honneur ?</French>
		<German>Oha, Ihr habt Euer stinkendes Land verlassen, um mich zu besuchen, [CT_NAME]? Was verschafft mir denn diese zweifelhafte Ehre?</German>
		<Italian>E così hai lasciato quel tuo fetido paese e sei venuto da me, [CT_NAME]. E a cosa devo questo dubbio onore?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Así que hab&#233;is salido de vuestro f&#233;tido país y hab&#233;is venido a verme, [CT_NAME]. ¿A qu&#233; debo tan dudoso honor?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_MEHMED_1</Tag>
		<English>We require mighty [CT_CIV_SHORT]'s assistance. I hope you won't disappoint us.</English>
		<French>Nous avons besoin de l'aide des [CT_CIV_SHORT]. J'esp&#232;re que vous ne nous décevrez pas.</French>
		<German>Wir könnten die Hilfe des mächtigen Volkes von [CT_CIV_SHORT] brauchen und hoffen doch sehr, dass Ihr uns nicht im Stich lasst!</German>
		<Italian>Chiediamo aiuto alla tua potente civilt&#224;. Spero che non ci deluderai.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Necesitamos la ayuda y la fortaleza de [CT_CIV]. Espero que no nos decepcion&#233;is.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRADE_DEFENSIVE_PACT</Tag>
		<English>A Mutual Protection Pact - Each Party Agrees to Automatically Declare War if the Other Party is Attacked.</English>
		<French>Pacte d'assistance mutuelle : chaque partie accepte de d&#233;clarer automatiquement la guerre si l'autre est attaqu&#233;e.</French>
		<German>Ein Verteidigungsb&#252;ndnis - Beide Parteien stimmen zu, den Angreifern der anderen Partei automatisch den Krieg zu erkl&#228;ren.</German>
		<Italian>Un patto di protezione reciproca: ogni civilt&#224; accetta di dichiarare automaticamente guerra se la civilt&#224; alleata viene attaccata.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Un acuerdo de protecci&#243;n mutua: cada parte accede a declarar autom&#225;ticamente la guerra si alguien ataca a la otra.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_TRADE_SLAVE</Tag>
		<English>Slave Trade</English>
		<German>Sklavenhandel</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TRUDEAU_1</Tag>
		<English>Good day and bonjour, to you [CT_NAME]. The [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people wish for peace, but insist that masters in our own house we must be.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MEIJI_1</Tag>
		<English>Finally we meet [CT_NAME], I have been awaiting your arrival. I am Meiji of Japan. Come, we have much to discuss. You have very nice dress, and I am impressed by your armies. Please, show me your ways and I shall show you the wonders of Japan...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AFONSO_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome to the independent [OUR_CIV_ADJ] lands! I am the king [OUR_NAME], will [CT_CIV_SHORT] recognize [OUR_CIV_SHORT]'s independence or do I need to convince you with my armies?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Je suis [OUR_NAME]. C'est un honneur de vous rencontrer.</French>
		<German>Seid gegr??t, [CT_NAME]. Mein Name ist [OUR_NAME]. Es ist mir eine Ehre, Eure Bekanntschaft zu machen.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Sono [OUR_NAME]. ? davvero un onore incontrarti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Soy [OUR_NAME]. Es todo un honor conoceros.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_AFONSO_1</Tag>
		<English>Here comes my best friend, [CT_NAME]! What brings you today to [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! Asseyez-vous et bavardons un instant.</French>
		<German>Seid gegr??t, [CT_NAME]. Nehmt Platz und lasst uns ein wenig plaudern.</German>
		<Italian>Salve, [CT_NAME]. Siediti e parliamo per un po'.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sentaos y charlemos un rato.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_AFONSO_1</Tag>
		<English>You are an enemy of [OUR_CIV_SHORT], but I will talk to you.</English>
		<French>Que me vaut l'honneur peu enviable de votre pr?sence ?</French>
		<German>Was verschafft mir die zweifelhafte Ehre Eures Besuchs?</German>
		<Italian>E a cosa devo il dubbio onore della tua presenza?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Y a qu? debemos el dudoso honor de vuestra compa??a?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_AFONSO_1</Tag>
		<English>We desperatedly demand your assistance, [CT_NAME]! [OUR_CIV_SHORT]'s future depends on you!</English>
		<French>Pourriez-vous donner ceci ? un bon ami, [CT_NAME] ?</French>
		<German>Ihr werdet einem treuen Freund diese kleine Bitte doch nicht abschlagen, [CT_NAME]?</German>
		<Italian>Avresti un po' di questi in nome della nostra amicizia, [CT_NAME]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podr?ais darles esto a unos buenos amigos, [CT_NAME]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_AFONSO_1</Tag>
		<English>Any chance you share your wealth with [OUR_CIV_SHORT]?</English>
		<French>Partager, c'est le d?but de l'amiti?, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Helfen hei?t br?derlich teilen, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Se ci tieni a me, condividi, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Compartir es de generosos, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_AFONSO_1</Tag>
		<English>Recognizing me as king of the [OUR_EMPIRE] is not enough! I demand the following in tribute!</English>
		<French>R?pondez ? nos exigences ou vous subirez la foudre de notre "terrible et rapide ?p?e".</French>
		<German>Schlagt ein, wenn Ihr kein zweites Gettysburg erleben wollt! </German>
		<Italian>Dammi ci? che chiedo o proverai l'ira della nostra &quot;terribile e rapida spada.&quot; </Italian>
		<Spanish>Dadnos esto o sentir?is la c?lera de nuestra &quot;terrible y veloz espada&quot;. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
