<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ITALY_DESC</Tag>
		<English>The Italians</English>
		<French>The Italians</French>
		<German>The Italians</German>
		<Italian>The Italians</Italian>
		<Spanish>The Italians</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>The Italians</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ITALY_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Italy</English>
		<French>Italie</French>
		<German>Italien</German>
		<Italian>L'Italia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Italia</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Olaszorsz&#225;g</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ITALY_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Italian</English>
		<French>Italien</French>
		<German>Italienisch</German>
		<Italian>Italiano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Italiano</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>olasz</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ITALY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In steady decline since the 2nd century AD, the Roman empire broke into two parts in 285 AD: the Western Roman Empire and the Byzantine Empire in the East. The western part under the pressure of Goths finally dissolved, leaving the Italian peninsula divided into small independent kingdoms and feuding city states for the next 14 centuries, and leaving the eastern part sole heir to the Roman legacy. The italian civilization was born from the ashes of the roman civilization.[PARAGRAPH:2]Following a short recapture of the Italian peninsula by Byzantine Emperor Justinian in the 6th century AD from the Ostrogoths, a new wave of Germanic tribes, the Lombards, soon arrived in Italy from the north. For several centuries the armies of the Byzantines were strong enough to prevent Arabs, the Holy Roman Empire, or the Papacy from establishing a unified Italian Kingdom, but were at the same time too weak to fully unify the former Roman lands themselves. Nevertheless, during early Middle Ages Imperial dynasties such as the Carolingians, the Ottonians and the Hohenstaufens managed to impose their overlordship in Italy.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy's regions were eventually subsumed by their neighbouring empires with their conflicting interests and would remain divided up to the 19th century. It was during this vacuum of authority that the region saw the rise of the Signoria and the Comune. In the anarchic conditions that often prevailed in medieval Italian city-states, people looked to strong men to restore order and disarm the feuding elites. In times of anarchy or crisis, cities sometimes offered the Signoria to individuals perceived as strong enough to save the state, most notably the Della Scala family in Verona, the Visconti in Milan and the Medici in Florence.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy during this period became notable for its merchant Republics. These city-states, oligarchical in reality, had a dominant merchant class which under relative freedom nurtured academic and artistic advancement. The four classic Maritime Republics in Italy were Venice, Genoa, Pisa and Amalfi.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages, the present-day region of Italy was a collection of smaller independent city states and kingdoms and their dependencies.[PARAGRAPH:2]Venice and Genoa were Europe's gateways to trade with the East, with the former producer of the renowned venetian glass. Florence was the capital of silk, wool, banks and jewelry. The Maritime Republics were heavily involved in the Crusades, taking advantage of the new political and trading opportunities, most evidently in the conquest of Zara and Constantinople funded by Venice.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages Italy was divided into smaller city-states and territories: the kingdom of Naples controlled the south, the Republic of Florence and the Papal States the centre, the Genoese and the Milanese the north and west, and the Venetians the east. Fifteenth-century Italy was one of the most urbanised areas in Europe and the birthplace of Renaissance. Florence in particular, with the writings of Dante Alighieri (1265–1321), Francesco Petrarch (1304–1374) and Giovanni Boccaccio (c. 1313–1375), as well as the painting of Giotto di Bondone (1267–1337), is considered the centre of this cultural movement. Scholars like Niccol&#242; de' Niccoli and Poggio Bracciolini scoured the libraries in search of works of classical authors, such as Plato, Aristotle, Euclid, Ptolemy, Cicero and Vitruvius.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Black Death pandemic in 1348 left its mark on Italy by killing one third of the population. The recovery from the disaster led to a resurgence of cities, trade and economy which greatly stimulated the successive phases of Humanism and the Renaissance. In 1494 the French king Charles VIII opened the first of a series of invasions, lasting up to sixteenth century, in a competition between France and Spain for the possession of the country. Ultimately Spain prevailed through the Treaty of Cateau-Cambresis which recognised Spanish dominance over the Duchy of Milan and the Kingdom of Naples. The holy alliance between Habsburg Spain and the Holy See resulted in the systematic persecution of any Protestant movement. Austria succeeded Spain as hegemon in Italy under the Peace of Utrecht. Through Austrian domination, the northern part of Italy gained economic dynamism and intellectual fervor. The French Revolution and the Napoleonic Wars (1796–1815) introduced the ideas of equality, democracy, law and nation. Italy’s population between 1700 and 1800 rose by about one-third, to 18 million.[PARAGRAPH:2]The creation of the Kingdom of Italy was the result of efforts by Italian nationalists and monarchists loyal to the House of Savoy to establish a united kingdom encompassing the entire Italian Peninsula. In the context of the 1848 liberal revolutions that swept through Europe, an unsuccessful war was declared on Austria. Giuseppe Garibaldi, popular amongst southern Italians, led the Italian republican drive for unification in southern Italy, while the northern Italian monarchy of the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia whose government was led by Camillo Benso, conte di Cavour, had the ambition of establishing a united Italian state under its rule. The kingdom successfully challenged the Austrian Empire in the Second Italian War of Independence with the help of Napoleon III, liberating the Lombardy-Venetia. In 1866, Victor Emmanuel II aligned the kingdom with Prussia during the Austro-Prussian War, waging the Third Italian War of Independence which allowed Italy to annex Venice. In 1870, as France during the disastrous Franco-Prussian War abandoned its positions in Rome, Italy rushed to fill the power gap by taking over the Papal State from French sovereignty. Italian unification finally was achieved, and shortly afterwards Italy's capital was moved to Rome.[PARAGRAPH:2]As Northern Italy became industrialized and modernized, Southern Italy and agricultural regions of the north remained under-developed and stagnant, forcing millions of people to migrate to the emerging Industrial Triangle or abroad. The Sardinian Statuto Albertino of 1848, extended to the whole Kingdom of Italy in 1861, provided for basic freedoms, but the electoral laws excluded the non-propertied and uneducated classes from voting. In 1913, male universal suffrage was adopted. The Socialist Party became the main political party, outclassing the traditional liberal and conservative organisations. The high point of Italian emigration was 1913, when 872,598 persons left Italy. Starting from the last two decades of the nineteenth century, Italy developed into a colonial power by forcing Somalia, Eritrea and later Libya and the Dodecanese under its rule. During World War I, Italy at first stayed neutral but in 1915 signed the Treaty of London, entering Entente on the promise of receiving Trento, Trieste, Istria, Dalmatia and parts of Ottoman Empire. During the war, 600,000 Italians died, and the economy collapsed. Under the Peace Treaty of Saint-Germain, Italy obtained just Bolzano-Bozen, Trento, Trieste and Istria in a victory described as "mutilated" by the public.[PARAGRAPH:2]The turbulence that followed the devastation of World War I, inspired by the Russian Revolution, led to turmoil and anarchy. The liberal establishment, fearing a socialist revolution, started to endorse the small National Fascist Party, led by Benito Mussolini. In October 1922 the fascists attempted a coup (the Marcia su Roma, "March on Rome"), but the king ordered the army not to intervene, instead forming an alliance with Mussolini. Over the next few years, Mussolini banned all political parties and curtailed personal liberties, thus forming a dictatorship. In 1935, Mussolini subjugated Ethiopia after a surprisingly lengthy campaign. This resulted in international alienation and the exodus of the country from the League of Nations. A first pact with Nazi Germany was concluded in 1936, and a second in 1938. Italy strongly supported Franco in the Spanish civil war. The country was opposed to Adolf Hitler's annexations of Austria, but did not interfere with it. Italy supported Germany's annexation of Sudetenland, however.[PARAGRAPH:2]On 7 April 1939 Italy occupied Albania, a de facto protectorate for decades, and entered World War II in 1940, taking part in the late stages of the Battle of France. Mussolini, wanting a quick victory like Hitler's blitzkriegs in Poland and France, invaded Greece in October 1940 via Albania but was forced to accept a humiliating defeat after a few months. At the same time, Italy, after initially conquering British Somalia, saw an allied counter-attack lead to the loss of all possessions in the Horn of Africa. Italy was also defeated by British forces in North Africa and was only saved by the urgently dispatched German Africa Corps led by Erwin Rommel. Italy was invaded by the Allies in June 1943, leading to the collapse of the fascist regime and the arrest of Mussolini. In September 1943, Italy surrendered. The country remained a battlefield for the rest of the war, as the allies were moving up from the south and the north was the base for loyalist Italian fascist and German Nazi forces. The whole picture became more complex by the activity of the Italian partisans; see Italian resistance movement. The Nazis left the country on 25 April 1945. This led to the eventual disbanding of Italian fascist forces.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1946, Vittorio Emanuele III's son, Umberto II, was forced to abdicate. Italy became a republic after a referendum held on 2 June 1946, a day celebrated since as Republic Day. This was the first election in Italy allowing women to vote. The Republican Constitution was approved and came into force on 1 January 1948. Under the Paris Peace Treaties of 1947, the eastern border area was lost to Yugoslavia, and, later, the free territory of Trieste was divided between the two states. Fears in the Italian electorate of a possible Communist takeover proved crucial for the first universal suffrage electoral outcome on the 18th of April 1948 when the Democrazia Cristiana, under the undisputed leadership of Alcide De Gasperi, won a resounding victory with 48 percent of the vote. In the 50s Italy became a member of the NATO alliance and an ally of the United States, which helped to revive the Italian economy through the Marshall Plan: until the 60s the country saw a period of prolonged economic growth termed the "Economic Miracle". In 1957, Italy was a signatory to the Treaties of Rome founding the European Economic Community (EEC), which became the European Union (EU) in 1993.[PARAGRAPH:2]From the late 1960s till late 1980s the country experienced a hard economic crisis and the Years of Lead, a period characterised by widespread social conflicts and terrorist acts carried out by extra-parliamentary movements. The Years of Lead culminated in the assassination of the Christian Democracy (DC) leader Aldo Moro in 1978, bringing to an end the "Historic Compromise" between the DC and the Communist Party. In the 1980s, for the first time since 1945, two governments were led by non-Christian-Democrat premiers: a republican (Giovanni Spadolini) and a socialist (Bettino Craxi); the DC remained, however, the main force supporting the government. The Socialist Party (PSI), led by Bettino Craxi, became more and more critical of the Communists and of the Soviet Union; Craxi himself pushed in favour of US president Ronald Reagan's positioning of Pershing missiles in Italy, a move the Communists hotly contested.[PARAGRAPH:2]From 1992 to 2009, Italy faced significant challenges, as voters, disenchanted with past political paralysis, massive government debt, extensive corruption, and organized crime's considerable influence (collectively called Tangentopoli after being uncovered by Mani pulite - "Clean hands") demanded political, economic, and ethical reforms. The scandals involved all major parties, but especially those in the government coalition: between 1992 and 1994 the DC underwent a severe crisis and was dissolved, splitting up into several pieces, while the PSI and the other governing minor parties completely dissolved. The 1994 elections put media magnate Silvio Berlusconi into the Prime Minister's seat. However, he was forced to step down in December when the Lega Nord Party withdrew its support. In April 1996, national elections led to the victory of a centre-left coalition under the leadership of Romano Prodi. Prodi's first government became the third-longest to stay in power before he narrowly lost a vote of confidence, by three votes, in October 1998. A new government was formed by Massimo D'Alema, but in April 2000 he resigned. In 2001, national elections led to the victory of a centre-right coalition under the leadership of Silvio Berlusconi, the centre-right formed a government, and Silvio Berlusconi was able to remain in power for a complete five-year mandate, but with two different governments. The first one (2001–2005) became the longest-lived government in post-war Italy. Italy participated in the US-led military coalition in Iraq. The elections in 2006 were won by the centre-left, allowing Prodi to form his second government, but in early 2008 he resigned because of the collapse of his coalition. In the ensuing new early elections in April 2008, Silvio Berlusconi won to form a government for a fourth time.</English>
		<French>[TAB]In steady decline since the 2nd century AD, the Roman empire broke into two parts in 285 AD: the Western Roman Empire and the Byzantine Empire in the East. The western part under the pressure of Goths finally dissolved, leaving the Italian peninsula divided into small independent kingdoms and feuding city states for the next 14 centuries, and leaving the eastern part sole heir to the Roman legacy. The italian civilization was born from the ashes of the roman civilization.[PARAGRAPH:2]Following a short recapture of the Italian peninsula by Byzantine Emperor Justinian in the 6th century AD from the Ostrogoths, a new wave of Germanic tribes, the Lombards, soon arrived in Italy from the north. For several centuries the armies of the Byzantines were strong enough to prevent Arabs, the Holy Roman Empire, or the Papacy from establishing a unified Italian Kingdom, but were at the same time too weak to fully unify the former Roman lands themselves. Nevertheless, during early Middle Ages Imperial dynasties such as the Carolingians, the Ottonians and the Hohenstaufens managed to impose their overlordship in Italy.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy's regions were eventually subsumed by their neighbouring empires with their conflicting interests and would remain divided up to the 19th century. It was during this vacuum of authority that the region saw the rise of the Signoria and the Comune. In the anarchic conditions that often prevailed in medieval Italian city-states, people looked to strong men to restore order and disarm the feuding elites. In times of anarchy or crisis, cities sometimes offered the Signoria to individuals perceived as strong enough to save the state, most notably the Della Scala family in Verona, the Visconti in Milan and the Medici in Florence.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy during this period became notable for its merchant Republics. These city-states, oligarchical in reality, had a dominant merchant class which under relative freedom nurtured academic and artistic advancement. The four classic Maritime Republics in Italy were Venice, Genoa, Pisa and Amalfi.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages, the present-day region of Italy was a collection of smaller independent city states and kingdoms and their dependencies.[PARAGRAPH:2]Venice and Genoa were Europe's gateways to trade with the East, with the former producer of the renowned venetian glass. Florence was the capital of silk, wool, banks and jewelry. The Maritime Republics were heavily involved in the Crusades, taking advantage of the new political and trading opportunities, most evidently in the conquest of Zara and Constantinople funded by Venice.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages Italy was divided into smaller city-states and territories: the kingdom of Naples controlled the south, the Republic of Florence and the Papal States the centre, the Genoese and the Milanese the north and west, and the Venetians the east. Fifteenth-century Italy was one of the most urbanised areas in Europe and the birthplace of Renaissance. Florence in particular, with the writings of Dante Alighieri (1265–1321), Francesco Petrarch (1304–1374) and Giovanni Boccaccio (c. 1313–1375), as well as the painting of Giotto di Bondone (1267–1337), is considered the centre of this cultural movement. Scholars like Niccol&#242; de' Niccoli and Poggio Bracciolini scoured the libraries in search of works of classical authors, such as Plato, Aristotle, Euclid, Ptolemy, Cicero and Vitruvius.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Black Death pandemic in 1348 left its mark on Italy by killing one third of the population. The recovery from the disaster led to a resurgence of cities, trade and economy which greatly stimulated the successive phases of Humanism and the Renaissance. In 1494 the French king Charles VIII opened the first of a series of invasions, lasting up to sixteenth century, in a competition between France and Spain for the possession of the country. Ultimately Spain prevailed through the Treaty of Cateau-Cambresis which recognised Spanish dominance over the Duchy of Milan and the Kingdom of Naples. The holy alliance between Habsburg Spain and the Holy See resulted in the systematic persecution of any Protestant movement. Austria succeeded Spain as hegemon in Italy under the Peace of Utrecht. Through Austrian domination, the northern part of Italy gained economic dynamism and intellectual fervor. The French Revolution and the Napoleonic Wars (1796–1815) introduced the ideas of equality, democracy, law and nation. Italy’s population between 1700 and 1800 rose by about one-third, to 18 million.[PARAGRAPH:2]The creation of the Kingdom of Italy was the result of efforts by Italian nationalists and monarchists loyal to the House of Savoy to establish a united kingdom encompassing the entire Italian Peninsula. In the context of the 1848 liberal revolutions that swept through Europe, an unsuccessful war was declared on Austria. Giuseppe Garibaldi, popular amongst southern Italians, led the Italian republican drive for unification in southern Italy, while the northern Italian monarchy of the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia whose government was led by Camillo Benso, conte di Cavour, had the ambition of establishing a united Italian state under its rule. The kingdom successfully challenged the Austrian Empire in the Second Italian War of Independence with the help of Napoleon III, liberating the Lombardy-Venetia. In 1866, Victor Emmanuel II aligned the kingdom with Prussia during the Austro-Prussian War, waging the Third Italian War of Independence which allowed Italy to annex Venice. In 1870, as France during the disastrous Franco-Prussian War abandoned its positions in Rome, Italy rushed to fill the power gap by taking over the Papal State from French sovereignty. Italian unification finally was achieved, and shortly afterwards Italy's capital was moved to Rome.[PARAGRAPH:2]As Northern Italy became industrialized and modernized, Southern Italy and agricultural regions of the north remained under-developed and stagnant, forcing millions of people to migrate to the emerging Industrial Triangle or abroad. The Sardinian Statuto Albertino of 1848, extended to the whole Kingdom of Italy in 1861, provided for basic freedoms, but the electoral laws excluded the non-propertied and uneducated classes from voting. In 1913, male universal suffrage was adopted. The Socialist Party became the main political party, outclassing the traditional liberal and conservative organisations. The high point of Italian emigration was 1913, when 872,598 persons left Italy. Starting from the last two decades of the nineteenth century, Italy developed into a colonial power by forcing Somalia, Eritrea and later Libya and the Dodecanese under its rule. During World War I, Italy at first stayed neutral but in 1915 signed the Treaty of London, entering Entente on the promise of receiving Trento, Trieste, Istria, Dalmatia and parts of Ottoman Empire. During the war, 600,000 Italians died, and the economy collapsed. Under the Peace Treaty of Saint-Germain, Italy obtained just Bolzano-Bozen, Trento, Trieste and Istria in a victory described as "mutilated" by the public.[PARAGRAPH:2]The turbulence that followed the devastation of World War I, inspired by the Russian Revolution, led to turmoil and anarchy. The liberal establishment, fearing a socialist revolution, started to endorse the small National Fascist Party, led by Benito Mussolini. In October 1922 the fascists attempted a coup (the Marcia su Roma, "March on Rome"), but the king ordered the army not to intervene, instead forming an alliance with Mussolini. Over the next few years, Mussolini banned all political parties and curtailed personal liberties, thus forming a dictatorship. In 1935, Mussolini subjugated Ethiopia after a surprisingly lengthy campaign. This resulted in international alienation and the exodus of the country from the League of Nations. A first pact with Nazi Germany was concluded in 1936, and a second in 1938. Italy strongly supported Franco in the Spanish civil war. The country was opposed to Adolf Hitler's annexations of Austria, but did not interfere with it. Italy supported Germany's annexation of Sudetenland, however.[PARAGRAPH:2]On 7 April 1939 Italy occupied Albania, a de facto protectorate for decades, and entered World War II in 1940, taking part in the late stages of the Battle of France. Mussolini, wanting a quick victory like Hitler's blitzkriegs in Poland and France, invaded Greece in October 1940 via Albania but was forced to accept a humiliating defeat after a few months. At the same time, Italy, after initially conquering British Somalia, saw an allied counter-attack lead to the loss of all possessions in the Horn of Africa. Italy was also defeated by British forces in North Africa and was only saved by the urgently dispatched German Africa Corps led by Erwin Rommel. Italy was invaded by the Allies in June 1943, leading to the collapse of the fascist regime and the arrest of Mussolini. In September 1943, Italy surrendered. The country remained a battlefield for the rest of the war, as the allies were moving up from the south and the north was the base for loyalist Italian fascist and German Nazi forces. The whole picture became more complex by the activity of the Italian partisans; see Italian resistance movement. The Nazis left the country on 25 April 1945. This led to the eventual disbanding of Italian fascist forces.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1946, Vittorio Emanuele III's son, Umberto II, was forced to abdicate. Italy became a republic after a referendum held on 2 June 1946, a day celebrated since as Republic Day. This was the first election in Italy allowing women to vote. The Republican Constitution was approved and came into force on 1 January 1948. Under the Paris Peace Treaties of 1947, the eastern border area was lost to Yugoslavia, and, later, the free territory of Trieste was divided between the two states. Fears in the Italian electorate of a possible Communist takeover proved crucial for the first universal suffrage electoral outcome on the 18th of April 1948 when the Democrazia Cristiana, under the undisputed leadership of Alcide De Gasperi, won a resounding victory with 48 percent of the vote. In the 50s Italy became a member of the NATO alliance and an ally of the United States, which helped to revive the Italian economy through the Marshall Plan: until the 60s the country saw a period of prolonged economic growth termed the "Economic Miracle". In 1957, Italy was a signatory to the Treaties of Rome founding the European Economic Community (EEC), which became the European Union (EU) in 1993.[PARAGRAPH:2]From the late 1960s till late 1980s the country experienced a hard economic crisis and the Years of Lead, a period characterised by widespread social conflicts and terrorist acts carried out by extra-parliamentary movements. The Years of Lead culminated in the assassination of the Christian Democracy (DC) leader Aldo Moro in 1978, bringing to an end the "Historic Compromise" between the DC and the Communist Party. In the 1980s, for the first time since 1945, two governments were led by non-Christian-Democrat premiers: a republican (Giovanni Spadolini) and a socialist (Bettino Craxi); the DC remained, however, the main force supporting the government. The Socialist Party (PSI), led by Bettino Craxi, became more and more critical of the Communists and of the Soviet Union; Craxi himself pushed in favour of US president Ronald Reagan's positioning of Pershing missiles in Italy, a move the Communists hotly contested.[PARAGRAPH:2]From 1992 to 2009, Italy faced significant challenges, as voters, disenchanted with past political paralysis, massive government debt, extensive corruption, and organized crime's considerable influence (collectively called Tangentopoli after being uncovered by Mani pulite - "Clean hands") demanded political, economic, and ethical reforms. The scandals involved all major parties, but especially those in the government coalition: between 1992 and 1994 the DC underwent a severe crisis and was dissolved, splitting up into several pieces, while the PSI and the other governing minor parties completely dissolved. The 1994 elections put media magnate Silvio Berlusconi into the Prime Minister's seat. However, he was forced to step down in December when the Lega Nord Party withdrew its support. In April 1996, national elections led to the victory of a centre-left coalition under the leadership of Romano Prodi. Prodi's first government became the third-longest to stay in power before he narrowly lost a vote of confidence, by three votes, in October 1998. A new government was formed by Massimo D'Alema, but in April 2000 he resigned. In 2001, national elections led to the victory of a centre-right coalition under the leadership of Silvio Berlusconi, the centre-right formed a government, and Silvio Berlusconi was able to remain in power for a complete five-year mandate, but with two different governments. The first one (2001–2005) became the longest-lived government in post-war Italy. Italy participated in the US-led military coalition in Iraq. The elections in 2006 were won by the centre-left, allowing Prodi to form his second government, but in early 2008 he resigned because of the collapse of his coalition. In the ensuing new early elections in April 2008, Silvio Berlusconi won to form a government for a fourth time.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Italien, vor allem Mittel- und S&#252;ditalien, ist schon seit der Antike ein wichtiges europ&#228;isches Kulturzentrum und war Mittelpunkt des R&#246;mischen Reichs. Zur Zeit Caesars reichte es bis zum Rubikon bei Rimini, unter Kaiser Augustus wurde es bis an den Fu&#223; der Alpen und nach Istrien ausgedehnt.[PARAGRAPH:2]Nach dem Einfall der Goten und vor allem der Langobarden (410 bzw. 568) zersplitterte das Land in eine Reihe von Herrschaftsgebieten. Im 8. und 9. Jahrhundert, besonders unter Pippin und Karl dem Gro&#223;en, dominierten die Franken, doch entwickelte sich unter den Nachfolgern Karls ein eigenes K&#246;nigreich Italien. Seit Otto dem Gro&#223;en geh&#246;rte Italien &#252;berwiegend zum Heiligen R&#246;mischen Reich, der S&#252;den blieb dabei lange byzantinisch. Jedoch eroberten zun&#228;chst Araber ab 827 Sizilien und Teile S&#252;ditaliens. Im fr&#252;hen 11. Jahrhundert begannen Normannen (aus der Normandie) mit der Eroberung S&#252;ditaliens bis zum Ende des 11. Jahrhunderts.[PARAGRAPH:2]Durch den Aufschwung von Handel und Verkehr gewannen insbesondere die St&#228;dte Norditaliens im 11. Jahrhundert zunehmende Selbstst&#228;ndigkeit. Die Normannen und zahlreiche St&#228;dte Oberitaliens unterst&#252;tzten w&#228;hrend des Investiturstreits den Papst. Mit dem Untergang ihrer Dynastie 1268 scheiterten die Versuche der Staufer, die schwindende Reichsgewalt in Italien zu erneuern, obwohl Heinrich VI. das unteritalienische Normannenreich durch Heirat gewonnen hatte. Den S&#252;den beherrschte ab 1268 die franz&#246;sische Dynastie der Anjou, der Norden zerfiel in eine Reihe von formal dem Heiligen R&#246;mischen Reich zugeh&#246;rigen, jedoch beinahe selbstst&#228;ndigen St&#228;dten mit ihrem Umland.[PARAGRAPH:2]Im 14. und 15. Jahrhundert entstanden im Zeitalter der Renaissance Mittelm&#228;chte mit einem enormen wirtschaftlichen und kulturellen Vorsprung. F&#252;nf M&#228;chte, das s&#252;ditalienische K&#246;nigreich (das zunehmend unter spanischen Einfluss geriet), der Kirchenstaat, Florenz, Mailand und Venedig teilten sich in wechselnden Koalitionen die politische Macht und die Ressourcen der Halbinsel.[PARAGRAPH:2]Im Kampf um die Vorherrschaft in Italien ab dem sp&#228;ten 15. Jahrhundert siegte Spanien &#252;ber Frankreich, doch konnte Venedig - wiederum in wechselnden Koalitionen - das Machtgleichgewicht so stabilisieren, dass der spanische Einfluss &#252;berwiegend im S&#252;den sp&#252;rbar war, wenn er auch immer wieder auf Genua und Mailand ausgriff.[PARAGRAPH:2]1796 rissen franz&#246;sische Revolutionstruppen die Macht an sich. 1806 wurde Napoleon K&#246;nig von Italien. Nach dem Zusammenbruch seiner Herrschaft und der Wiederherstellung der Zust&#228;nde vor Napoleon begann die Zeit des Risorgimento (1815-1870). Angetrieben durch die Freiwilligenverb&#228;nde unter Giuseppe Garibaldi und unter F&#252;hrung der Dynastie der Savoyer, K&#246;nige von Piemont-Sardinien, gelang die in drei Unabh&#228;ngigkeitskriegen die Vereinigung Italiens. Am 17. M&#228;rz 1861 wurde Viktor Emanuel II. in Turin zum K&#246;nig Italiens ausgerufen. 1865 wechselte die Hauptstadt nach Florenz. 1866 kamen mit dem dritten Unabh&#228;ngigkeitskrieg auch das &#246;sterreichisch-ungarische Veneto sowie das Friaul zum K&#246;nigreich Italien. Rom wurde dann 1870 erobert und ein Jahr sp&#228;ter zur Hauptstadt des Landes erkoren. Dar&#252;ber hinaus versuchte Italien, &#228;hnlich wie andere europ&#228;ische M&#228;chte, als Kolonialmacht Fu&#223; zu fassen, am Horn von Afrika (Eritrea, erst sp&#228;ter &#228;thiopien) und in Libyen.[PARAGRAPH:2]Da Italien sich zu Beginn des Ersten Weltkriegs aus dem Dreibund gel&#246;st hatte und der Entente beigetreten war, konnte das K&#246;nigreich auf der Seite der Siegerm&#228;chte Julisch Venetien, das Trentino sowie das deutschsprachige S&#252;dtirol annektieren.[PARAGRAPH:2]Im Oktober 1922 &#252;bernahmen Benito Mussolini und seine Fascisti genannten Gefolgsleute durch den Marsch auf Rom die Macht. Schritt f&#252;r Schritt wandelte Mussolini das K&#246;nigreich in einen totalit&#228;ren Staat um und setzte sich selbst als "Duce" (F&#252;hrer) an die Spitze von Volk und Staat. Noch vor Beginn des Zweiten Weltkrieges &#252;berfiel Italien Abessinien und okkupierte das Land. Diese v&#246;lkerrechtswidrige Besetzung war Teil von Mussolinis erkl&#228;rtem Ziel, das antike R&#246;mische Reich wieder aufleben zu lassen. Durch verschiedene Abkommen band sich Mussolini an das Deutsche Reich und Adolf Hitler. Schlie&#223;lich trat Italien auf der Seite der Achsenm&#228;chte, nach merklichem Z&#246;gern des Duce, in den Zweiten Weltkrieg ein. Mit dem R&#252;ckzug der italienischen Truppen vor den anr&#252;ckenden Alliierten und dem Sturz der faschistischen Regierung im Herbst 1943 brach Italien den Dreim&#228;chtepakt, wechselte die Fronten und erkl&#228;rte nunmehr seinem vormals Verb&#252;ndeten den Krieg.[PARAGRAPH:2]Der folgende Einmarsch der deutschen Wehrmacht stie&#223; auf den Widerstand der Resistenza. Nach der Befreiung Mussolinis durch deutsche Fallschirmj&#228;ger in den Apenninen erfolgte die Installation einer Marionettenregierung unter Mussolini in Norditalien bis nach Rom am 23. September 1943 (Italienische Sozialrepublik). Dieser neue Staat blieb mit Deutschland verb&#252;ndet und erkl&#228;rte seinerseits dem von den Alliierten besetzten Teil Italiens den Krieg. Eine frischrekrutierte Armee von 40.000 Freiwilligen (Schwarze Brigaden) standen als vermeintlich legitime Staatsgewalt von Beginn an in einer Art B&#252;rgerkrieg gegen die italienischen Partisanen, der sich die letzten 18 Monate bis zum Ende des Krieges hinzog. Als sich die deutschen Verb&#228;nde im Juni 1944 bis zur "Gotenlinie" im Apennin zur&#252;ckzogen und italienische Partisanen ihre &#252;berf&#228;lle auf deutsche Soldaten verst&#228;rkten, kam es zu Massakern an der Zivilbev&#246;lkerung und weiteren schweren Kriegsverbrechen durch die deutschen Besatzer und Truppen der faschistischen Sozialrepublik Italien. Am 28. April 1945 kapitulierten die Wehrmachtsverb&#228;nde in Italien vor den Westalliierten, die K&#228;mpfe hielten aber noch bis zum 2. Mai 1945 an.[PARAGRAPH:2]Durch den Frontwechsel blieb Italien nach Kriegsende von gr&#246;&#223;eren Gebietsabtretungen verschont (Umland von Triest an Jugoslawien bzw. das heutige Slowenien und Kroatien, Dodekanes an Griechenland, die Gemeinde Tende und La Brigue an Frankreich, sowie Verlust s&#228;mtlicher Kolonien).[PARAGRAPH:2]Eine verfassungsgebende Versammlung beschloss die neue Costituzione della Repubblica Italiana am 22. Dezember 1947. Sie trat zum 1. Januar 1948 in Kraft.[PARAGRAPH:2]Die Nachkriegsgeschichte Italiens zeichnet sich innenpolitisch durch h&#228;ufige Regierungswechsel, allerdings bis 1990 vier Jahrzehnte unter F&#252;hrung oder Hauptbeteiligung der Democrazia Cristiana, au&#223;enpolitisch durch die Gr&#252;ndungsmitgliedschaft in der Europ&#228;ische Wirtschaftsgemeinschaft und wirtschaftlich durch das Wirtschaftswunder (miracolo economico) aus. Nach Jahrzehnten hoher Inflation, auch durch Entwertung der Lira, wurden in den 1990er Jahren die Staatsfinanzen unter Kontrolle gebracht und Italien &#252;bernahm als W&#228;hrung den Euro.[PARAGRAPH:2]Anfang der 90er Jahre wurde die politische Elite des Landes vom Korruptionsskandal Mani pulite weggefegt. Seitdem wird die Politik Italiens von Parteienb&#252;ndnissen um die Figur von Silvio Berlusconi sowie von wechselnden Mitte-links-Koalitionen bestimmt.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La regione geografica italiana fu unita politicamente per la prima volta da Roma con la fondazione della Repubblica nel 509 a.C.; ai romani, dopo i 500 anni di Repubblica e i 500 di Impero, succedette, a partire dal 493 d.C., il Regno ostrogoto, che mantenne l'unit&#224; politica della penisola italiana. Il Regno ostrogoto fu la prima di tante occasioni mancate nel Medioevo per affermare anche nella regione geografica italiana un processo di formazione di coscienza nazionale come gi&#224; era avvenuto in altri Paesi europei. Nel 553 d.C. la penisola italiana e il Regno ostrogoto sono infatti conquistati da un'altra civilt&#224; venuta da fuori: quella bizantina con l'imperatore d'Oriente Giustiniano I deciso a riprendersi il territorio che nel secolo precedente era stato dell'Impero romano d'Occidente. Quasi un ventennio di guerra porta alla devastazione dell'intera penisola italiana e ad una grave crisi demografica, economica, politica e sociale.[PARAGRAPH:2]La dominazione dell'Impero romano d'Oriente fu caratterizzata, oltre che da un aggravamento delle condizioni di vita dei contadini a causa della forte pressione fiscale, anche da una terribile pestilenza che spopola ulteriormente la penisola italiana tra il 559 d.C. e il 562 d.C. La penisola italiana, indebolita e impoverita, non ha quindi la forza di opporsi a una nuova invasione germanica, quella dei Longobardi capeggiati da Alboino, con cui avr&#224; termine l'unit&#224; politica italiana. Tra il 568 d.C. e il 569 d.C. infatti, i Longobardi conquistarono dapprima gran parte dell'Italia centro-settentrionale, che prese il nome di "Langobardia Major", e poi l'Italia meridionale che chiamarono "Langobardia Minor".[PARAGRAPH:2]Nei secoli successivi alla sconfitta dei Longobardi, avvenuta ad opera di Carlo Magno nel 774, ci sono dei tentativi di riguadagnare un'indipendenza persa ormai da secoli ed in particolare l'autonomia dal Sacro Romano Impero tedesco, bench&#233; non si possa certo ancora parlare di sentimento nazionale italiano, tantomeno di patriottismo. Piuttosto le visioni politiche nell'Italia di allora si attestano su due posizioni ben precise: quella dei Guelfi e quella dei Ghibellini, schierati con le due potenze di allora, rispettivamente: il Papato e l'Impero. In questo contesto &#232; famoso l'episodio del 1176 quando una lega di comuni italiani, la Lega Lombarda, con l'appoggio del Papa, si oppose all'imperatore Federico Barbarossa e alle sue mire egemoniche sulla penisola. Questi episodi nascondevano tuttavia interessi di altra natura, soprattutto economici.[PARAGRAPH:2]Con la morte dell'imperatore Federico II (1194-1250) e il tramonto della casa di Svevia, ebbe termine la terribile lotta fra Impero e Papato per l'egemonia politica universale; quando l'Italia si sent&#237; libera dal dominio tedesco, divamp&#242; un grande movimento culturale ed artistico che coinvolse l'intera penisola e i cui semi erano gi&#224; stati gettati proprio dal defunto imperatore, famoso per il suo mecenatismo ed ancora oggi ricordato in Italia. Questo movimento va sotto il nome di Umanesimo e costituir&#224; la base su cui si fonder&#224; un altro movimento di ancor pi&#249; ampia portata e risonanza europea: il Rinascimento. In questo periodo inizia a farsi strada un vero e proprio sentimento nazionale italiano, anche se non riconducibile alle categorie politiche di oggi. Esso si alimentava soprattutto del ricordo dell'antica grandezza di Roma, e trovava nell'identit&#224; religiosa rappresentata dalla Chiesa, idealmente erede delle istituzioni romane, un senso di comune appartenenza.[PARAGRAPH:2]Diversi fattori impedirono tuttavia la nascita di uno stato unitario come stava avvenendo nel resto d'Europa: oltre alla suddivisione in tanti piccoli Comuni, che si tramutarono via via in Signorie, c'era anche il timore da parte del Papato di veder sorgere una potenza statale in grado di compromettere la sua autonomia. Ad ogni modo l'Italia riusc&#236; a respingere le superiori forze degli stati nazionali europei gi&#224; formati o in via di formazione grazie all'intelligenza strategica e diplomatica di alcuni dei suoi capi politici. Esemplare &#232; in proposito la figura di Cosimo de' Medici (1389-1464), Signore di Firenze; la sua politica estera, infatti, mirante al mantenimento di un costante e sottile equilibrio fra i vari stati italiani, sar&#224; profetica nell'individuare nella concordia italiana l'elemento chiave per impedire agli stati stranieri di intervenire nella penisola approfittando delle sue divisioni.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'importanza della strategia di Cosimo, proseguita dal figlio Lorenzo il Magnifico (1449-1492), non venne tuttavia compresa dagli altri pr&#236;ncipi della penisola, ed essa si concluse con la morte di Lorenzo nel 1492. Da allora l'Italia divent&#242; il teatro di numerose invasioni straniere: dapprima da parte dei Francesi ad opera di Carlo VIII, poi delle truppe spagnole di Carlo V. Alla Spagna infine si sostituiranno, nel Settecento, gli Asburgo d'Austria che si impossesseranno di vari domini italiani.[PARAGRAPH:2]Secondo la storiografia risorgimentale, l'unit&#224; politica della nazione italiana sarebbe stata la meta di un sentimento nazionale che si inizierebbe ad osservare per la prima volta solo in epoca napoleonica con l'arrivo nella penisola italiana delle truppe napoleoniche (1796). Il primo accenno esplicito di riscossa nazionale italiana si pu&#242; individuare al termine dell'epoca napoleonica, nel "Proclama di Rimini", con cui Gioacchino Murat, Re di Napoli e fedelissimo di Napoleone, il 30 marzo 1815, durante la guerra austro-napoletana, rivolse un interessato appello a tutti gli italiani affinch&#233; si unissero per salvare il Regno posto sotto la sua sovranit&#224;, unico garante della loro indipendenza nazionale contro un occupante straniero.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il periodo della storia d'Italia in cui l'affermarsi di una coscienza nazionale italiana port&#242; all'unit&#224; politica e quindi alla definitiva affermazione della nazione italiana &#232; detto Risorgimento. Tale periodo, a conclusione del quale si ebbe la definitiva affermazione della nazione italiana, fu un lungo processo che occupa un arco temporale di vari decenni e che si concluse nel 1861 con la nascita del Regno d'Italia sotto la dinastia di Casa Savoia. Le personalit&#224; coinvolte in tale processo furono molte, ma quattro spiccano su tutte: Giuseppe Mazzini, figura eminente del movimento liberale repubblicano italiano ed europeo; Giuseppe Garibaldi, repubblicano e di simpatie socialiste, per molti un eroico ed efficace combattente per la libert&#224; in Europa ed in Sud America; Camillo Benso conte di Cavour, statista in grado di muoversi sulla scena europea per ottenere sostegni, anche finanziari, all'espansione del Regno di Sardegna; Vittorio Emanuele II di Savoia, abile a concretizzare il contesto favorevole con la costituzione del Regno d'Italia.[PARAGRAPH:2]Il regno d'Italia nel 1861 aveva un'estensione territoriale che non comprendeva ancora alcuni territori; in particolare Roma, che fu presa solo il 20 settembre 1870. I problemi diplomatici dovuti dalla "questione romana" furono molteplici e complessi. Un forte elemento di fragilit&#224; era costituito dall'ostilit&#224; della Chiesa cattolica e del clero nei confronti del nuovo Stato, ostilit&#224; che rafforz&#242; dopo il 1870 con la presa di Roma.[PARAGRAPH:2]Le velleit&#224; espansioniste del nuovo stato italiano, in special modo in ambito coloniale (L'Italia avrebbe conquistato negli anni '30 del XX secolo Libia e corno d'Africa) portarono il paese nel 1915 ad intervenire anche nella prima guerra mondiale (1914-1918), al fianco di Impero russo, Francia e Impero britannico, dopo essere rimasta inizialmente neutrale. Nel 1917 ci fu l'episodio chiave del fronte italiano: la disastrosa battaglia di Caporetto (24-26 ottobre 1917), che cost&#242; all'Italia una sconfitta tanto pesante che il termine "Caporetto" &#232; entrato nella lingua italiana come sinonimo di disfatta. Le sorti della guerra furono per&#242; ribaltate attraverso una rapida riorganizzazione dell'esercito (grazie anche ad una leva straordinaria che chiam&#242; alle armi i cosiddetti "Ragazzi del '99", appena diciottenni) e l'anno successivo l'invasione austro-ungarica in Veneto fu fermata. L'Impero era ormai a un passo dal baratro, impossibilitato a sostenere ancora lo sforzo bellico. La controffensiva italiana partita dalla cittadina di Vittorio Veneto il 23 ottobre 1918 port&#242; alla capitolazione dell'Austria-Ungheria e all'armistizio del 3 novembre.[PARAGRAPH:2]La disastrosa situazione sociale, economica, infrastrutturale e demografica dell'Italia uscita dalla guerra provoc&#242; numerosi scontenti, anche perch&#233; le acquisizioni territoriali promesse nel 1915 non ci furono. Il mito della "vittoria mutilata" fu la leva che port&#242; alla nascita di alcuni movimenti nazionalisti reazionari. Il 23 marzo 1919 Benito Mussolini fond&#242; a Milano il "fascio di combattimento" poi divenuto "Partito Nazionale Fascista" (PNF). Mussolini godeva della fiducia dei ceti pi&#249; ricchi e conservatori nonch&#233; della simpatia del re che sperava di contrapporre una forza d'urto efficace contro il socialismo. Nel 1922 Mussolini, approfittando di un governo particolarmente debole e forte di un contingente paramilitare di 50.000 uomini, organizz&#242; una marcia su Roma dove non incontr&#242; alcuna resistenza. Il re incaric&#242; Mussolini di formare un nuovo governo ma questo, nel giro di 3 anni, si sarebbe trasformato in dittatura fascista.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'Italia entr&#242; nella seconda guerra mondiale solo nel 1940 al fianco di Hitler e della Germania nazista, quando sembrava che quest'ultima, che aveva gi&#224; occupato Polonia e Francia, avesse la vittoria in pugno. L'intervento nella seconda guerra mondiale si risolse per l'Italia fascista in un vero disastro. Le sconfitte sia sul fronte africano che su quello russo causarono in Italia vari scioperi e un calo di consensi nei confronti del fascismo e di Mussolini. Nel 1943 il "Duce" venne sfiduciato ed arrestato. Qualche settimana dopo reparti speciali riuscirono a liberarlo e a dargli riparo nel nord Italia, occupato dalle truppe tedesche, mentre al sud gli anglo-americani stavano gi&#224; riconquistando ampie fette di territorio. Il Paese si trov&#242; cos&#236; diviso in due: il Regno del Sud a fianco degli alleati contro la Germania e la Repubblica Sociale Italiana, formata dai reduci fascisti. Di fatto, due stati-fantoccio. Il destino dell'"Asse" italo-tedesco era per&#242; segnato. Il 1945 vedr&#224; la fine della guerra con la vittoria degli alleati e la disfatta completa del nazi-fascismo.[PARAGRAPH:2]La fine della guerra vide l'Italia in condizioni critiche: i combattimenti risalendo la penisola ed i bombardamenti aerei avevano ridotto molte citt&#224; e paesi a cumuli di macerie, le principali vie di comunicazione erano interrotte, il territorio era occupato, i morti, si stima, furono tra i 415000 e 443000, all'epoca l'1% della popolazione totale. Lo scontento popolare nei confronti della monarchia e di Vittorio Emanuele III, soprattutto nell'Italia settentrionale, era elevatissimo. Non gli si perdonava tra l'altro di aver firmato nel 1938 le infami leggi razziali promulgate da Mussolini per "compiacere" l'alleato nazista. Il 2 giugno del 1946 un referendum istituzionale sanc&#236; la fine della monarchia e la nascita della Repubblica Italiana.[PARAGRAPH:2]Dopo i primi difficilissimi anni inizi&#242; nel paese verso la fine degli anni '50 quello che viene chiamato il "miracolo economico" con cui l'Italia riusc&#236; a ridurre il divario industriale ed economico "storico" nei confronti di Germania, Francia e Regno Unito.[PARAGRAPH:2]L'Italia, dopo aver superato momenti anche molto dolorosi e drammatici (le contestazioni del 1968-1969, la crisi economica e gli attentati terroristici di matrice "rossa" e di matrice "nera" negli anni '70) si ritrov&#242; nel 1992 a dover affrontare forse la prova pi&#249; difficile: le indagini sulla corruzione istituzionale che gener&#242; lo scandalo chiamato "Tangentopoli", in cui venne coinvolta e quindi decapitata l'intera classe politica del Paese dando inizio a quella che viene definita impropriamente la "Seconda Repubblica". Oggi il paese si trova ad affrontare di nuovo un periodo di difficolt&#224; e di forti contrapposizioni politiche (figlie in parte di ci&#242; che &#232; accaduto durante Tangentopoli) ed anche economiche, nel pi&#249; grande ambito della crisi della finanza mondiale scoppiata verso la fine del 2008.[PARAGRAPH:2]Avendo istituito col Trattato di Parigi, il 18 aprile 1951, assieme al Belgio, alla Francia, alla Germania Occidentale, al Lussemburgo e ai Paesi Bassi, la Comunit&#224; europea del carbone e dell'acciaio (CECA), l'Italia &#232; membro fondatore della Comunit&#224; economica europea (CEE) e dell'Unione europea (UE) ed ha partecipato a tutti i principali trattati di unificazione europea, compreso l'ingresso nell'area dell'Euro nel 1999. Inoltre &#232; membro fondatore della NATO, del Consiglio d'Europa e dell'Unione Europea Occidentale, aderisce alle Nazioni Unite (per il biennio 2007-2008 &#232; stato membro non-permanente del Consiglio di sicurezza), e fa parte del G7, del G8, del G20 e dell'OCSE.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]In steady decline since the 2nd century AD, the Roman empire broke into two parts in 285 AD: the Western Roman Empire and the Byzantine Empire in the East. The western part under the pressure of Goths finally dissolved, leaving the Italian peninsula divided into small independent kingdoms and feuding city states for the next 14 centuries, and leaving the eastern part sole heir to the Roman legacy. The italian civilization was born from the ashes of the roman civilization.[PARAGRAPH:2]Following a short recapture of the Italian peninsula by Byzantine Emperor Justinian in the 6th century AD from the Ostrogoths, a new wave of Germanic tribes, the Lombards, soon arrived in Italy from the north. For several centuries the armies of the Byzantines were strong enough to prevent Arabs, the Holy Roman Empire, or the Papacy from establishing a unified Italian Kingdom, but were at the same time too weak to fully unify the former Roman lands themselves. Nevertheless, during early Middle Ages Imperial dynasties such as the Carolingians, the Ottonians and the Hohenstaufens managed to impose their overlordship in Italy.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy's regions were eventually subsumed by their neighbouring empires with their conflicting interests and would remain divided up to the 19th century. It was during this vacuum of authority that the region saw the rise of the Signoria and the Comune. In the anarchic conditions that often prevailed in medieval Italian city-states, people looked to strong men to restore order and disarm the feuding elites. In times of anarchy or crisis, cities sometimes offered the Signoria to individuals perceived as strong enough to save the state, most notably the Della Scala family in Verona, the Visconti in Milan and the Medici in Florence.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy during this period became notable for its merchant Republics. These city-states, oligarchical in reality, had a dominant merchant class which under relative freedom nurtured academic and artistic advancement. The four classic Maritime Republics in Italy were Venice, Genoa, Pisa and Amalfi.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages, the present-day region of Italy was a collection of smaller independent city states and kingdoms and their dependencies.[PARAGRAPH:2]Venice and Genoa were Europe's gateways to trade with the East, with the former producer of the renowned venetian glass. Florence was the capital of silk, wool, banks and jewelry. The Maritime Republics were heavily involved in the Crusades, taking advantage of the new political and trading opportunities, most evidently in the conquest of Zara and Constantinople funded by Venice.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages Italy was divided into smaller city-states and territories: the kingdom of Naples controlled the south, the Republic of Florence and the Papal States the centre, the Genoese and the Milanese the north and west, and the Venetians the east. Fifteenth-century Italy was one of the most urbanised areas in Europe and the birthplace of Renaissance. Florence in particular, with the writings of Dante Alighieri (1265–1321), Francesco Petrarch (1304–1374) and Giovanni Boccaccio (c. 1313–1375), as well as the painting of Giotto di Bondone (1267–1337), is considered the centre of this cultural movement. Scholars like Niccol&#242; de' Niccoli and Poggio Bracciolini scoured the libraries in search of works of classical authors, such as Plato, Aristotle, Euclid, Ptolemy, Cicero and Vitruvius.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Black Death pandemic in 1348 left its mark on Italy by killing one third of the population. The recovery from the disaster led to a resurgence of cities, trade and economy which greatly stimulated the successive phases of Humanism and the Renaissance. In 1494 the French king Charles VIII opened the first of a series of invasions, lasting up to sixteenth century, in a competition between France and Spain for the possession of the country. Ultimately Spain prevailed through the Treaty of Cateau-Cambresis which recognised Spanish dominance over the Duchy of Milan and the Kingdom of Naples. The holy alliance between Habsburg Spain and the Holy See resulted in the systematic persecution of any Protestant movement. Austria succeeded Spain as hegemon in Italy under the Peace of Utrecht. Through Austrian domination, the northern part of Italy gained economic dynamism and intellectual fervor. The French Revolution and the Napoleonic Wars (1796–1815) introduced the ideas of equality, democracy, law and nation. Italy’s population between 1700 and 1800 rose by about one-third, to 18 million.[PARAGRAPH:2]The creation of the Kingdom of Italy was the result of efforts by Italian nationalists and monarchists loyal to the House of Savoy to establish a united kingdom encompassing the entire Italian Peninsula. In the context of the 1848 liberal revolutions that swept through Europe, an unsuccessful war was declared on Austria. Giuseppe Garibaldi, popular amongst southern Italians, led the Italian republican drive for unification in southern Italy, while the northern Italian monarchy of the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia whose government was led by Camillo Benso, conte di Cavour, had the ambition of establishing a united Italian state under its rule. The kingdom successfully challenged the Austrian Empire in the Second Italian War of Independence with the help of Napoleon III, liberating the Lombardy-Venetia. In 1866, Victor Emmanuel II aligned the kingdom with Prussia during the Austro-Prussian War, waging the Third Italian War of Independence which allowed Italy to annex Venice. In 1870, as France during the disastrous Franco-Prussian War abandoned its positions in Rome, Italy rushed to fill the power gap by taking over the Papal State from French sovereignty. Italian unification finally was achieved, and shortly afterwards Italy's capital was moved to Rome.[PARAGRAPH:2]As Northern Italy became industrialized and modernized, Southern Italy and agricultural regions of the north remained under-developed and stagnant, forcing millions of people to migrate to the emerging Industrial Triangle or abroad. The Sardinian Statuto Albertino of 1848, extended to the whole Kingdom of Italy in 1861, provided for basic freedoms, but the electoral laws excluded the non-propertied and uneducated classes from voting. In 1913, male universal suffrage was adopted. The Socialist Party became the main political party, outclassing the traditional liberal and conservative organisations. The high point of Italian emigration was 1913, when 872,598 persons left Italy. Starting from the last two decades of the nineteenth century, Italy developed into a colonial power by forcing Somalia, Eritrea and later Libya and the Dodecanese under its rule. During World War I, Italy at first stayed neutral but in 1915 signed the Treaty of London, entering Entente on the promise of receiving Trento, Trieste, Istria, Dalmatia and parts of Ottoman Empire. During the war, 600,000 Italians died, and the economy collapsed. Under the Peace Treaty of Saint-Germain, Italy obtained just Bolzano-Bozen, Trento, Trieste and Istria in a victory described as "mutilated" by the public.[PARAGRAPH:2]The turbulence that followed the devastation of World War I, inspired by the Russian Revolution, led to turmoil and anarchy. The liberal establishment, fearing a socialist revolution, started to endorse the small National Fascist Party, led by Benito Mussolini. In October 1922 the fascists attempted a coup (the Marcia su Roma, "March on Rome"), but the king ordered the army not to intervene, instead forming an alliance with Mussolini. Over the next few years, Mussolini banned all political parties and curtailed personal liberties, thus forming a dictatorship. In 1935, Mussolini subjugated Ethiopia after a surprisingly lengthy campaign. This resulted in international alienation and the exodus of the country from the League of Nations. A first pact with Nazi Germany was concluded in 1936, and a second in 1938. Italy strongly supported Franco in the Spanish civil war. The country was opposed to Adolf Hitler's annexations of Austria, but did not interfere with it. Italy supported Germany's annexation of Sudetenland, however.[PARAGRAPH:2]On 7 April 1939 Italy occupied Albania, a de facto protectorate for decades, and entered World War II in 1940, taking part in the late stages of the Battle of France. Mussolini, wanting a quick victory like Hitler's blitzkriegs in Poland and France, invaded Greece in October 1940 via Albania but was forced to accept a humiliating defeat after a few months. At the same time, Italy, after initially conquering British Somalia, saw an allied counter-attack lead to the loss of all possessions in the Horn of Africa. Italy was also defeated by British forces in North Africa and was only saved by the urgently dispatched German Africa Corps led by Erwin Rommel. Italy was invaded by the Allies in June 1943, leading to the collapse of the fascist regime and the arrest of Mussolini. In September 1943, Italy surrendered. The country remained a battlefield for the rest of the war, as the allies were moving up from the south and the north was the base for loyalist Italian fascist and German Nazi forces. The whole picture became more complex by the activity of the Italian partisans; see Italian resistance movement. The Nazis left the country on 25 April 1945. This led to the eventual disbanding of Italian fascist forces.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1946, Vittorio Emanuele III's son, Umberto II, was forced to abdicate. Italy became a republic after a referendum held on 2 June 1946, a day celebrated since as Republic Day. This was the first election in Italy allowing women to vote. The Republican Constitution was approved and came into force on 1 January 1948. Under the Paris Peace Treaties of 1947, the eastern border area was lost to Yugoslavia, and, later, the free territory of Trieste was divided between the two states. Fears in the Italian electorate of a possible Communist takeover proved crucial for the first universal suffrage electoral outcome on the 18th of April 1948 when the Democrazia Cristiana, under the undisputed leadership of Alcide De Gasperi, won a resounding victory with 48 percent of the vote. In the 50s Italy became a member of the NATO alliance and an ally of the United States, which helped to revive the Italian economy through the Marshall Plan: until the 60s the country saw a period of prolonged economic growth termed the "Economic Miracle". In 1957, Italy was a signatory to the Treaties of Rome founding the European Economic Community (EEC), which became the European Union (EU) in 1993.[PARAGRAPH:2]From the late 1960s till late 1980s the country experienced a hard economic crisis and the Years of Lead, a period characterised by widespread social conflicts and terrorist acts carried out by extra-parliamentary movements. The Years of Lead culminated in the assassination of the Christian Democracy (DC) leader Aldo Moro in 1978, bringing to an end the "Historic Compromise" between the DC and the Communist Party. In the 1980s, for the first time since 1945, two governments were led by non-Christian-Democrat premiers: a republican (Giovanni Spadolini) and a socialist (Bettino Craxi); the DC remained, however, the main force supporting the government. The Socialist Party (PSI), led by Bettino Craxi, became more and more critical of the Communists and of the Soviet Union; Craxi himself pushed in favour of US president Ronald Reagan's positioning of Pershing missiles in Italy, a move the Communists hotly contested.[PARAGRAPH:2]From 1992 to 2009, Italy faced significant challenges, as voters, disenchanted with past political paralysis, massive government debt, extensive corruption, and organized crime's considerable influence (collectively called Tangentopoli after being uncovered by Mani pulite - "Clean hands") demanded political, economic, and ethical reforms. The scandals involved all major parties, but especially those in the government coalition: between 1992 and 1994 the DC underwent a severe crisis and was dissolved, splitting up into several pieces, while the PSI and the other governing minor parties completely dissolved. The 1994 elections put media magnate Silvio Berlusconi into the Prime Minister's seat. However, he was forced to step down in December when the Lega Nord Party withdrew its support. In April 1996, national elections led to the victory of a centre-left coalition under the leadership of Romano Prodi. Prodi's first government became the third-longest to stay in power before he narrowly lost a vote of confidence, by three votes, in October 1998. A new government was formed by Massimo D'Alema, but in April 2000 he resigned. In 2001, national elections led to the victory of a centre-right coalition under the leadership of Silvio Berlusconi, the centre-right formed a government, and Silvio Berlusconi was able to remain in power for a complete five-year mandate, but with two different governments. The first one (2001–2005) became the longest-lived government in post-war Italy. Italy participated in the US-led military coalition in Iraq. The elections in 2006 were won by the centre-left, allowing Prodi to form his second government, but in early 2008 he resigned because of the collapse of his coalition. In the ensuing new early elections in April 2008, Silvio Berlusconi won to form a government for a fourth time.</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>[TAB]In steady decline since the 2nd century AD, the Roman empire broke into two parts in 285 AD: the Western Roman Empire and the Byzantine Empire in the East. The western part under the pressure of Goths finally dissolved, leaving the Italian peninsula divided into small independent kingdoms and feuding city states for the next 14 centuries, and leaving the eastern part sole heir to the Roman legacy. The italian civilization was born from the ashes of the roman civilization.[PARAGRAPH:2]Following a short recapture of the Italian peninsula by Byzantine Emperor Justinian in the 6th century AD from the Ostrogoths, a new wave of Germanic tribes, the Lombards, soon arrived in Italy from the north. For several centuries the armies of the Byzantines were strong enough to prevent Arabs, the Holy Roman Empire, or the Papacy from establishing a unified Italian Kingdom, but were at the same time too weak to fully unify the former Roman lands themselves. Nevertheless, during early Middle Ages Imperial dynasties such as the Carolingians, the Ottonians and the Hohenstaufens managed to impose their overlordship in Italy.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy's regions were eventually subsumed by their neighbouring empires with their conflicting interests and would remain divided up to the 19th century. It was during this vacuum of authority that the region saw the rise of the Signoria and the Comune. In the anarchic conditions that often prevailed in medieval Italian city-states, people looked to strong men to restore order and disarm the feuding elites. In times of anarchy or crisis, cities sometimes offered the Signoria to individuals perceived as strong enough to save the state, most notably the Della Scala family in Verona, the Visconti in Milan and the Medici in Florence.[PARAGRAPH:2]Italy during this period became notable for its merchant Republics. These city-states, oligarchical in reality, had a dominant merchant class which under relative freedom nurtured academic and artistic advancement. The four classic Maritime Republics in Italy were Venice, Genoa, Pisa and Amalfi.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages, the present-day region of Italy was a collection of smaller independent city states and kingdoms and their dependencies.[PARAGRAPH:2]Venice and Genoa were Europe's gateways to trade with the East, with the former producer of the renowned venetian glass. Florence was the capital of silk, wool, banks and jewelry. The Maritime Republics were heavily involved in the Crusades, taking advantage of the new political and trading opportunities, most evidently in the conquest of Zara and Constantinople funded by Venice.[PARAGRAPH:2]During the late Middle Ages Italy was divided into smaller city-states and territories: the kingdom of Naples controlled the south, the Republic of Florence and the Papal States the centre, the Genoese and the Milanese the north and west, and the Venetians the east. Fifteenth-century Italy was one of the most urbanised areas in Europe and the birthplace of Renaissance. Florence in particular, with the writings of Dante Alighieri (1265–1321), Francesco Petrarch (1304–1374) and Giovanni Boccaccio (c. 1313–1375), as well as the painting of Giotto di Bondone (1267–1337), is considered the centre of this cultural movement. Scholars like Niccol&#242; de' Niccoli and Poggio Bracciolini scoured the libraries in search of works of classical authors, such as Plato, Aristotle, Euclid, Ptolemy, Cicero and Vitruvius.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Black Death pandemic in 1348 left its mark on Italy by killing one third of the population. The recovery from the disaster led to a resurgence of cities, trade and economy which greatly stimulated the successive phases of Humanism and the Renaissance. In 1494 the French king Charles VIII opened the first of a series of invasions, lasting up to sixteenth century, in a competition between France and Spain for the possession of the country. Ultimately Spain prevailed through the Treaty of Cateau-Cambresis which recognised Spanish dominance over the Duchy of Milan and the Kingdom of Naples. The holy alliance between Habsburg Spain and the Holy See resulted in the systematic persecution of any Protestant movement. Austria succeeded Spain as hegemon in Italy under the Peace of Utrecht. Through Austrian domination, the northern part of Italy gained economic dynamism and intellectual fervor. The French Revolution and the Napoleonic Wars (1796–1815) introduced the ideas of equality, democracy, law and nation. Italy’s population between 1700 and 1800 rose by about one-third, to 18 million.[PARAGRAPH:2]The creation of the Kingdom of Italy was the result of efforts by Italian nationalists and monarchists loyal to the House of Savoy to establish a united kingdom encompassing the entire Italian Peninsula. In the context of the 1848 liberal revolutions that swept through Europe, an unsuccessful war was declared on Austria. Giuseppe Garibaldi, popular amongst southern Italians, led the Italian republican drive for unification in southern Italy, while the northern Italian monarchy of the Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia whose government was led by Camillo Benso, conte di Cavour, had the ambition of establishing a united Italian state under its rule. The kingdom successfully challenged the Austrian Empire in the Second Italian War of Independence with the help of Napoleon III, liberating the Lombardy-Venetia. In 1866, Victor Emmanuel II aligned the kingdom with Prussia during the Austro-Prussian War, waging the Third Italian War of Independence which allowed Italy to annex Venice. In 1870, as France during the disastrous Franco-Prussian War abandoned its positions in Rome, Italy rushed to fill the power gap by taking over the Papal State from French sovereignty. Italian unification finally was achieved, and shortly afterwards Italy's capital was moved to Rome.[PARAGRAPH:2]As Northern Italy became industrialized and modernized, Southern Italy and agricultural regions of the north remained under-developed and stagnant, forcing millions of people to migrate to the emerging Industrial Triangle or abroad. The Sardinian Statuto Albertino of 1848, extended to the whole Kingdom of Italy in 1861, provided for basic freedoms, but the electoral laws excluded the non-propertied and uneducated classes from voting. In 1913, male universal suffrage was adopted. The Socialist Party became the main political party, outclassing the traditional liberal and conservative organisations. The high point of Italian emigration was 1913, when 872,598 persons left Italy. Starting from the last two decades of the nineteenth century, Italy developed into a colonial power by forcing Somalia, Eritrea and later Libya and the Dodecanese under its rule. During World War I, Italy at first stayed neutral but in 1915 signed the Treaty of London, entering Entente on the promise of receiving Trento, Trieste, Istria, Dalmatia and parts of Ottoman Empire. During the war, 600,000 Italians died, and the economy collapsed. Under the Peace Treaty of Saint-Germain, Italy obtained just Bolzano-Bozen, Trento, Trieste and Istria in a victory described as "mutilated" by the public.[PARAGRAPH:2]The turbulence that followed the devastation of World War I, inspired by the Russian Revolution, led to turmoil and anarchy. The liberal establishment, fearing a socialist revolution, started to endorse the small National Fascist Party, led by Benito Mussolini. In October 1922 the fascists attempted a coup (the Marcia su Roma, "March on Rome"), but the king ordered the army not to intervene, instead forming an alliance with Mussolini. Over the next few years, Mussolini banned all political parties and curtailed personal liberties, thus forming a dictatorship. In 1935, Mussolini subjugated Ethiopia after a surprisingly lengthy campaign. This resulted in international alienation and the exodus of the country from the League of Nations. A first pact with Nazi Germany was concluded in 1936, and a second in 1938. Italy strongly supported Franco in the Spanish civil war. The country was opposed to Adolf Hitler's annexations of Austria, but did not interfere with it. Italy supported Germany's annexation of Sudetenland, however.[PARAGRAPH:2]On 7 April 1939 Italy occupied Albania, a de facto protectorate for decades, and entered World War II in 1940, taking part in the late stages of the Battle of France. Mussolini, wanting a quick victory like Hitler's blitzkriegs in Poland and France, invaded Greece in October 1940 via Albania but was forced to accept a humiliating defeat after a few months. At the same time, Italy, after initially conquering British Somalia, saw an allied counter-attack lead to the loss of all possessions in the Horn of Africa. Italy was also defeated by British forces in North Africa and was only saved by the urgently dispatched German Africa Corps led by Erwin Rommel. Italy was invaded by the Allies in June 1943, leading to the collapse of the fascist regime and the arrest of Mussolini. In September 1943, Italy surrendered. The country remained a battlefield for the rest of the war, as the allies were moving up from the south and the north was the base for loyalist Italian fascist and German Nazi forces. The whole picture became more complex by the activity of the Italian partisans; see Italian resistance movement. The Nazis left the country on 25 April 1945. This led to the eventual disbanding of Italian fascist forces.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1946, Vittorio Emanuele III's son, Umberto II, was forced to abdicate. Italy became a republic after a referendum held on 2 June 1946, a day celebrated since as Republic Day. This was the first election in Italy allowing women to vote. The Republican Constitution was approved and came into force on 1 January 1948. Under the Paris Peace Treaties of 1947, the eastern border area was lost to Yugoslavia, and, later, the free territory of Trieste was divided between the two states. Fears in the Italian electorate of a possible Communist takeover proved crucial for the first universal suffrage electoral outcome on the 18th of April 1948 when the Democrazia Cristiana, under the undisputed leadership of Alcide De Gasperi, won a resounding victory with 48 percent of the vote. In the 50s Italy became a member of the NATO alliance and an ally of the United States, which helped to revive the Italian economy through the Marshall Plan: until the 60s the country saw a period of prolonged economic growth termed the "Economic Miracle". In 1957, Italy was a signatory to the Treaties of Rome founding the European Economic Community (EEC), which became the European Union (EU) in 1993.[PARAGRAPH:2]From the late 1960s till late 1980s the country experienced a hard economic crisis and the Years of Lead, a period characterised by widespread social conflicts and terrorist acts carried out by extra-parliamentary movements. The Years of Lead culminated in the assassination of the Christian Democracy (DC) leader Aldo Moro in 1978, bringing to an end the "Historic Compromise" between the DC and the Communist Party. In the 1980s, for the first time since 1945, two governments were led by non-Christian-Democrat premiers: a republican (Giovanni Spadolini) and a socialist (Bettino Craxi); the DC remained, however, the main force supporting the government. The Socialist Party (PSI), led by Bettino Craxi, became more and more critical of the Communists and of the Soviet Union; Craxi himself pushed in favour of US president Ronald Reagan's positioning of Pershing missiles in Italy, a move the Communists hotly contested.[PARAGRAPH:2]From 1992 to 2009, Italy faced significant challenges, as voters, disenchanted with past political paralysis, massive government debt, extensive corruption, and organized crime's considerable influence (collectively called Tangentopoli after being uncovered by Mani pulite - "Clean hands") demanded political, economic, and ethical reforms. The scandals involved all major parties, but especially those in the government coalition: between 1992 and 1994 the DC underwent a severe crisis and was dissolved, splitting up into several pieces, while the PSI and the other governing minor parties completely dissolved. The 1994 elections put media magnate Silvio Berlusconi into the Prime Minister's seat. However, he was forced to step down in December when the Lega Nord Party withdrew its support. In April 1996, national elections led to the victory of a centre-left coalition under the leadership of Romano Prodi. Prodi's first government became the third-longest to stay in power before he narrowly lost a vote of confidence, by three votes, in October 1998. A new government was formed by Massimo D'Alema, but in April 2000 he resigned. In 2001, national elections led to the victory of a centre-right coalition under the leadership of Silvio Berlusconi, the centre-right formed a government, and Silvio Berlusconi was able to remain in power for a complete five-year mandate, but with two different governments. The first one (2001–2005) became the longest-lived government in post-war Italy. Italy participated in the US-led military coalition in Iraq. The elections in 2006 were won by the centre-left, allowing Prodi to form his second government, but in early 2008 he resigned because of the collapse of his coalition. In the ensuing new early elections in April 2008, Silvio Berlusconi won to form a government for a fourth time.</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TURIN</Tag>
		<English>Turin</English>
		<French>Turin</French>
		<German>Turin</German>
		<Italian>Torino</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tur&#237;n</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Torino</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MILAN</Tag>
		<English>Milan</English>
		<French>Milan</French>
		<German>Mailand</German>
		<Italian>Milano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mil&#225;n</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>M&#237;l&#225;no</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_NAPLES</Tag>
		<English>Naples</English>
		<French>Naples</French>
		<German>Neapel</German>
		<Italian>Napoli</Italian>
		<Spanish>N&#225;poles</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>N&#225;poly</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_RAVENNA</Tag>
		<English>Ravenna</English>
		<French>Ravenna</French>
		<German>Ravenna</German>
		<Italian>Ravenna</Italian>
		<Spanish>R&#225;vena</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Ravenna</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PAVIA</Tag>
		<English>Pavia</English>
		<French>Pavie</French>
		<German>Pavia</German>
		<Italian>Pavia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Pav&#237;a</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>P&#225;via</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_VENICE</Tag>
		<English>Venice</English>
		<French>Venise</French>
		<German>Venedig</German>
		<Italian>Venezia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venecia</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Velence</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PALERMO</Tag>
		<English>Palermo</English>
		<French>Palerme</French>
		<German>Palermo</German>
		<Italian>Palermo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Palermo</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Palermo</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BOLOGNA</Tag>
		<English>Bologna</English>
		<French>Bologne</French>
		<German>Bologna</German>
		<Italian>Bologna</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bolonia</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Bologna</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BARI</Tag>
		<English>Bari</English>
		<French>Bari</French>
		<German>Bari</German>
		<Italian>Bari</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bari</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Bari</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MANTUA</Tag>
		<English>Mantua</English>
		<French>Mantoue</French>
		<German>Mantua</German>
		<Italian>Mantova</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mantua</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Mantova</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_LEGNANO</Tag>
		<English>Legnano</English>
		<French>Legnano</French>
		<German>Legnano</German>
		<Italian>Legnano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Legnano</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Legnano</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PESARO</Tag>
		<English>Pesaro</English>
		<French>Pesaro</French>
		<German>Pesaro</German>
		<Italian>Pesaro</Italian>
		<Spanish>P&#233;saro</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Pesaro</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_URBINO</Tag>
		<English>Urbino</English>
		<French>Urbin</French>
		<German>Urbino</German>
		<Italian>Urbino</Italian>
		<Spanish>Urbino</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Urbino</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_RIMINI</Tag>
		<English>Rimini</English>
		<French>Rimini</French>
		<German>Rimini</German>
		<Italian>Rimini</Italian>
		<Spanish>Rimini</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Rimini</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_FANO</Tag>
		<English>Fano</English>
		<French>Fano</French>
		<German>Fano</German>
		<Italian>Fano</Italian>
		<Spanish>Fano</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Fano</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_FERRARA</Tag>
		<English>Ferrara</English>
		<French>Ferrare</French>
		<German>Ferrara</German>
		<Italian>Ferrara</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ferrara</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Ferrara</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ANCONA</Tag>
		<English>Ancona</English>
		<French>Ancône</French>
		<German>Ancona</German>
		<Italian>Ancona</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ancona</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Ancona</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PERUGIA</Tag>
		<English>Perugia</English>
		<French>P&#233;rouse</French>
		<German>Perugia</German>
		<Italian>Perugia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Perugia</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Perugia</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BENEVENTO</Tag>
		<English>Benevento</English>
		<French>B&#233;n&#233;vent</French>
		<German>Benevento</German>
		<Italian>Benevento</Italian>
		<Spanish>Benevento</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Benevento</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MODENA</Tag>
		<English>Modena</English>
		<French>Mod&#232;ne</French>
		<German>Modena</German>
		<Italian>Modena</Italian>
		<Spanish>M&#243;dena</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Modena</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PARMA</Tag>
		<English>Parma</English>
		<French>Parme</French>
		<German>Parma</German>
		<Italian>Parma</Italian>
		<Spanish>Parma</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Parma</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_REGGIOEMILIA</Tag>
		<English>Reggio Emilia</English>
		<French>Reggio d'&#233;milie</French>
		<German>Reggio Emilia</German>
		<Italian>Reggio Emilia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Reggio Emilia</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Reggio Emilia</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MESSINA</Tag>
		<English>Messina</English>
		<French>Messine</French>
		<German>Messina</German>
		<Italian>Messina</Italian>
		<Spanish>Micina</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Messina</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PADUA</Tag>
		<English>Padua</English>
		<French>Padoue</French>
		<German>Padua</German>
		<Italian>Padova</Italian>
		<Spanish>Padua</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Padova</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CAGLIARI</Tag>
		<English>Cagliari</English>
		<French>Cagliari</French>
		<German>Cagliari</German>
		<Italian>Cagliari</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cagliari</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Cagliari</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_FORLI</Tag>
		<English>Forl&#236;</English>
		<French>Forl&#236;</French>
		<German>Forl&#236;</German>
		<Italian>Forl&#236;</Italian>
		<Spanish>Forl&#236;</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Forl&#236;</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_VICENZA</Tag>
		<English>Vicenza</English>
		<French>Vicenza</French>
		<German>Vicenza</German>
		<Italian>Vicenza</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vicenza</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Vicenza</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TRIESTE</Tag>
		<English>Trieste</English>
		<French>Trieste</French>
		<German>Triest</German>
		<Italian>Trieste</Italian>
		<Spanish>Trieste</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Trieszt</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_LATINA</Tag>
		<English>Latina</English>
		<French>Latina</French>
		<German>Latina</German>
		<Italian>Latina</Italian>
		<Spanish>Latina</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Latina</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MONZA</Tag>
		<English>Monza</English>
		<French>Monza</French>
		<German>Monza</German>
		<Italian>Monza</Italian>
		<Spanish>Monza</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Monza</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AVELLINO</Tag>
		<English>Avellino</English>
		<French>Avellino</French>
		<German>Avellino</German>
		<Italian>Avellino</Italian>
		<Spanish>Avellino</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Avellino</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ITALY_BERSAGLIERE</Tag>
		<English>Bersagliere</English>
		<French>Bersagliere</French>
		<German>Bersagliere</German>
		<Italian>Bersagliere</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bersagliere</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Bersagliere</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ITALIAN_ART_STUDIO</Tag>
		<English>Art Studio</English>
		<French>Atelier</French>
		<German>Atelier</German>
		<Italian>Art Studio</Italian>
		<Spanish>Art Studio</Spanish>
		<Hungarian>Art Studio</Hungarian>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CAVOUR</Tag>
		<English>Cavour</English>
		<French>Cavour</French>
		<German>Cavour</German>
		<Italian>Cavour</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cavour</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>

