<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 Beyond the Sword -->
<!-- Modified by the Civ Gold Team -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HO_CHI_MINH</Tag>
		<English>Ho Chi Minh</English>
		<French>Ho Chi Minh</French>
		<German>Ho Chi Minh</German>
		<Italian>Ho Chi Minh</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ho Chi Minh</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_TAIZONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Taizong[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of Tang Dyansty China[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]January 23, 599 – July 10, 649 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Emperor Taizong of Tang (Táng Tàizong, January 23, 599 – July 10, 649), personal name Li Shìmín , was the second emperor of the Tang Dynasty of China, ruling from 626 to 649. As he encouraged his father, Li Yuan (later Emperor Gaozu) to rise against Sui Dynasty rule at Taiyuan in 617 and subsequently defeated several of his most important rivals, he was ceremonially regarded as a cofounder of the dynasty along with Emperor Gaozu.[PARAGRAPH:1]He is typically considered one of the greatest, if not the greatest, emperor in all of Chinese history. Throughout the rest of Chinese history, Emperor Taizong's reign was regarded as the exemplary model against which all other emperors were measured, and his "Reign of Zhen'guan" (????) was considered a golden age of Chinese history and required study for future crown princes. During his reign, Tang China flourished economically and militarily. For more than a century after his death, Tang China enjoyed peace and prosperity.[PARAGRAPH:1]In 630, Emperor Taizong sent his general Li Jing against Eastern Tujue -- to which Tang had once submitted -- defeating and capturing its Jiali Khan Ashina Duobi and destroying Eastern Tujue power. This made Tang the dominant power in eastern Asia, and Emperor Taizong subsequently took the title of Tian Kehan ("Heavenly Khan").[3][PARAGRAPH:1]The modern Chinese historian Bo Yang opined that Emperor Taizong achieved greatness by accepting criticism that others would find difficult to accept and trying hard not to abuse his absolute power (using Emperor Yang of Sui as a negative example), as well as employing capable chancellors Fang Xuanling, Du Ruhui, and Wei Zheng. Emperor Taizong's wife Empress Zhangsun served as a capable assistant to him as well.[4]</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TAIZONG_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings [CT_NAME] . I am [OUR_NAME] ,emperor of all the lands below the heavens .With absolute power over numberless minions , do you dare hurt the divine ruler of mighty [OUR_CIV_SHORT] . </English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>